<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8180032</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1968916</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dose finding study of granisetron in patients receiving high-dose cisplatin chemotherapy. The Granisetron Study Group.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Riviere</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Centre Francois Baclesse, Caen, France.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>1994</year></pub-date><volume>69</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>971</lpage><abstract><p>The efficacy and safety of three different doses of granisetron (2 micrograms kg-1, group A; 10 micrograms kg-1, group B; 40 micrograms kg-1, group C) were compared in a randomised, double-blind study of 157 patients due to receive high-dose cisplatin therapy (mean dose &#x0003e; 97 mg m-2). In each group, up to two 3 mg rescue doses of granisetron were allowed if more than mild nausea or vomiting occurred. In group A 30.8%, in group B 61.5% and in group C 67.9% of patients were complete responders (i.e. no vomiting or nothing worse than mild nausea) during the first 24 h. These differences are significant between groups A and B, and A and C. There were no statistically significant differences in any efficacy variable between the 10 micrograms kg-1 and 40 micrograms kg-1 groups, although in each case the trend favoured the higher dose. Additional rescue doses resulted in resolved or improved symptoms in 95.3% for the first rescue dose and 93.3% for the second. Over the 7 days of the study, 82.7%, 82.7% and 86.8% of patients in groups A, B and C respectively were treated with granisetron alone. Headache was the most common side-effect, reported by 9.6% of patients; the majority of headaches were mild. There was no difference between the treatment groups regarding the adverse event rate. We concluded that prophylactic doses of 10 or 40 micrograms kg-1 lead to a safe and satisfactory degree of control of nausea and vomiting induced by high-dose cisplatin.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00195-0171.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="967" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00195-0172.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="968" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00195-0173.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="969" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00195-0174.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="970" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00195-0175.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="971" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

