<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11335194</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1240286</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">sc271_5_1835</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Lead poisoning from homemade wine: a case study.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mangas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Visvanathan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Alphen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Environmental Health Service, Department of Human Services, Adelaide, South Australia, Australia. sam.mangas@dhs.sa.gov.au</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>109</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><abstract><p>A 66-year-old man suffered the symptoms of severe lead poisoning for 2 years before diagnosis. The man had a blood lead level (PbB) on admission to hospital of 98 microg/dL. A detailed investigation revealed that the poisoning occurred as a result of drinking a homemade red wine, for which analyses showed a lead concentration up to 14 mg/L--70 times the Australian maximum limit for lead in wine. The source of the lead was a highly corroded enamel bathtub in which grape crushings and juice were stored for a week prior to bottling. The corrosion of the enamel surface of the bathtub had resulted in pitted patches up to 1 mm in depth along the side of the bathtub. Powdering of the tub surface was evident below a level where wine had been in contact with the sides of the tub. The homemade wine had a pH of 3.8, which would have greatly contributed to the solubilization of metals from the glaze. We conducted a test in which commercial red wine of similar pH and containing &#x0003c; 0.2 mg/L lead was placed in this tub for 7 days. Subsequent testing revealed a lead level of 310 mg/L. This high lead concentration is consistent with the surface area of enamel on the bathtub being in contact with a small liquid volume as in the case of the leaching test using commercial red wine. This case study highlights the importance of the use of food-grade materials for the preparation and storage of homemade beverages or food.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

