<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">1899195</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1971630</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Subrenal capsule assay in selection of chemotherapy after operation for recurrent ovarian cancer.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Venesmaa</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ylikorkala</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>I and II Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Helsinki University Central Hospital, Finland.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>1991</year></pub-date><volume>63</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><abstract><p>Forty-six patients with recurrent ovarian cancer were reoperated, and cancer samples for the subrenal capsule assay (SRCA) were collected from 23 of them, whereas this test was not done in the remaining 23 control patients. The SRCA was evaluable in 22 cases (96%). Taken together, no significant difference appeared in the 3 years' survival figures between the groups: seven of 22 patients (32%) with the evaluable SRCA and six of 23 control patients (26%) were alive. However, a further analysis of the data revealed that the SRCA guided the selection of chemotherapy only in 15 patients, whereas tumour samples were resistant to all cytostatics tested in six cases and toxic side-effects limited the clinical application of the test results in the remaining one case. Four of the 11 patients (36%) whose further chemotherapy was strictly chosen based on the SRCA and seven of the 24 patients (29%) whose treatment was based on physician's choice survived at least 3 years. Our conclusion is that the SRCA is of limited value in the selection of second-line chemotherapy in recurrent ovarian cancer.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00209-0088.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="84" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00209-0089.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="85" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00209-0090.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="86" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

