<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11673125</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1240446</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">sc271_5_1835</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Gastrointestinal effects associated with soluble and insoluble copper in drinking water.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pizarro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Araya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gidi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uauy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Instituto de Nutrici&#x000f3;n y Tecnolog&#x000ed;a de los Alimentos (INTA), Universidad de Chile, Santiago, Chile. fpizarro@uec.inta.uchile.cl</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>109</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>952</lpage><abstract><p>The aim of this study was to determine whether total copper or soluble copper concentration is associated with gastrointestinal signs and symptoms. Forty-five healthy adult women (18-55 years of age), living in Santiago, Chile, ingested tap water with 5 mg/L of copper containing different ratios of soluble copper (copper sulfate) and insoluble copper (copper oxide) over a 9-week period. Three randomized sequences of the different copper ratios (0:5, 1:4, 2:3, 3:2, and 5:0 mg/L) were followed. Subjects recorded their water consumption and gastrointestinal symptoms daily on a special form. Mean water consumption was similar among groups. Serum copper levels, ceruloplasmin, and activities of liver enzymes were within normal limits. No differences were detected between the means of biochemical parameters at the beginning and at the end of the study. Twenty subjects presented gastrointestinal disturbances at least once during the study, 9 suffered diarrhea (with or without abdominal pain and vomiting), and the other 11 subjects reported abdominal pain, nausea, or vomiting. No differences were found in incidence of abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea regardless of the ratio of copper sulfate to copper oxide. In conclusion, both copper sulfate (a soluble compound) and copper oxide (an insoluble compound) have comparable effects on the induction of gastrointestinal manifestations, implying that similar levels of ionic copper were present in the stomach.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

