<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7889887</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1566627</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Essentiality of boron for healthy bones and joints.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Newnham</surname><given-names>R E</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Rex Newnham and Associates, North Yorkshire, England.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>1994</year></pub-date><volume>102</volume><issue>Suppl 7</issue><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><abstract><p>Since 1963, evidence has accumulated that suggests boron is a safe and effective treatment for some forms of arthritis. The initial evidence was that boron supplementation alleviated arthritic pain and discomfort of the author. This was followed by findings from numerous other observations epidemiologic and controlled animal and human experiments. These findings included a) analytical evidence of lower boron concentrations in femur heads, bones, and synovial fluid from people with arthritis than from those without this disorder; b) observation evidence that bones of patients using boron supplements are much harder to cut than those of patients not using supplements; c) epidemiologic evidence that in areas of the world where boron intakes usually are 1.0 mg or less/day the estimated incidence of arthritis ranges from 20 to 70%, whereas in areas of the world where boron intakes are usually 3 to 10 mg, the estimated incidence of arthritis ranges from 0 to 10%; d) experimental evidence that rats with induced arthritis benefit from orally or intraperitoneally administered boron; e) experimental evidence from a double-blind placebo-boron supplementation trial with 20 subjects with osteoarthritis. A significant favorable response to a 6 mg boron/day supplement was obtained; 50% of subjects receiving the supplement improved compared to only 10% receiving the placebo. The preceding data indicate that boron is an essential nutrient for healthy bones and joints, and that further research into the use of boron for the treatment or prevention of arthritis is warranted.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="envhper00403-0084.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="83" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00403-0085.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="84" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00403-0086.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="85" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

