<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Crit Care</journal-id><journal-title>Critical Care</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1364-8535</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1466-609X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11094499</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">137251</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">cc686</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/cc686</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Commentary</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Percutaneous tracheostomy: comparison of Ciaglia and Griggs		  techniques</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kost</surname><given-names>Karen M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>kmkost@yahoo.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>McGill University, Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2000</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2000</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ccforum.com/content/4/3/143"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2000</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2000</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2000 Current Science Ltd</copyright-statement><abstract><p>Endoscopic percutaneous dilatational tracheostomy is at least as			 safe as standard open tracheostomy in the operating room (OR). Recently, a			 single dilator was introduced to accomplish dilatation of the tracheal aperture			 in one step, thus obviating the need for multiple graduated dilators.			 Experience with endoscopic percutaneous tracheostomy (PCT) using the single			 dilator in 40 patients to date supports the premise that the procedure is safe,			 rapid, and technically simple. In the study by A&#x000f1;on <italic>et al</italic>, two			 very different techniques, are compared: the Ciaglia percutaneous dilatational			 tracheostomy technique using multiple dilators and the Griggs percutaneous			 technique using guidewire-dilating forceps. Although relative complication			 rates for the two techniques are not significantly different, both procedures			 are performed in a 'blind' fashion, without the benefit of a			 bronchoscope. The reported incidence of serious complications in this study is			 high, and almost certainly avoidable with the addition of direct bronchoscopic			 visualization. Operative time is reported to be shorter with the Griggs			 technique, but this finding is unlikely to hold true for the single dilator			 technique, which reduces procedure time to less than 15 min. This author's			 experience with bedside endoscopic PCT using the single dilator indicates that			 it is a safe, rapid and cost-effective procedure with a low complication			 rate.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Ciaglia</kwd><kwd>complications</kwd><kwd>endoscopic percutaneous dilatational tracheostomy</kwd><kwd>Griggs</kwd><kwd>single dilator</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Almost two-thirds of modern-day tracheostomies are performed on adult,		  intubated intensive care unit patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Moving these		  critically ill patients with all their monitors to the OR has inherent risks		  and increases demands on OR time, which is expensive and often in short supply		  [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. PCT may be performed at the bedside and		  independently of OR schedules. My experience with over 150 endoscopically		  guided PCTs using the Cook Percutaneous Tracheostomy Introducer set (Cook		  Critical Care, Bloomington, IN, USA) with multiple graduated dilators has		  demonstrated that the procedure is at least as safe as conventional		  tracheostomy in the OR. In a comparative study by Kost and Zeitouni		  (unpublished data), endoscopic PCT compared favorably with conventional		  tracheostomy in the OR, with complication rates of 16 and 30%, respectively.		  These findings have been substantiated in a number of other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Percutaneous tracheostomy using a single dilator</title><p>In an attempt to streamline the technique of PCT, a single dilator was		  recently introduced to replace the previously required multiple dilators, thus		  reducing the number of steps required to complete the procedure. Dilatation of		  the tracheal aperture, which previously required multiple steps, can now be		  accomplished in a single step. This single dilator is sharply tapered and		  angled with a soft, hydrophillically coated tip. The procedure is suitable only		  in adult, intubated intensive care unit patients. It is contraindicated in the		  following situations: in emergencies; in the presence of an unprotected airway;		  in patients who require a positive end-expiratory pressure greater than		  20 cmH<sub>2</sub>O; and in children. It is also contraindicated in patients		  with a midline neck mass and in those with uncontrolled coagulopathies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p><p>The procedure, using the single dilator, is performed with the head		  extended on the chest, using a standard preparation and drape. The patient is		  ventilated on 100% oxygen and vital signs are continuously monitored. Local		  anesthesia augmented by intravenous sedation is required. A 1.5 cm incision is		  placed one to two fingerbreadths above the cricoid cartilage, and the		  subcutaneous fat is separated using a curved hemostat. At this point, a		  flexible bronchoscope is inserted and aligned with the tip of the endotracheal		  tube (ETT). The bronchoscope and ETT are slowly withdrawn until the incision is		  maximally trans-illuminated, allowing continuous visualization of the entire		  procedure. A 14-gauge Teflon catheter introducer needle is inserted between the		  first and second, or second and third tracheal rings. A J-wire threaded through		  the intracath allows placement of an introducer dilator. This initial		  enlargement of the tracheal aperture facilitates positioning of the guiding		  catheter over the J-wire (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). It is this		  J-wire/guiding catheter unit that forms the backbone over which the single		  dilator is inserted in an arc-like manner, accomplishing sufficient dilatation		  in one step (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). In contrast, when using the		  multiple dilator kit, the tracheal aperture is sequentially enlarged using a		  series of graduated dilators. The final step in both techniques involves		  inserting a preloaded tracheostomy tube over the J-wire/guiding catheter unit		  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>).</p><p>This procedure, using the single dilator, is currently being		  prospectively evaluated, with data available in 40 patients. All cases were		  performed or supervised by the same surgeon under continuous bronchoscopic		  guidance. There were 21 males and 19 females studied, who ranged in age from 20		  to 84 years. Shiley tracheostomy tubes (Mallinckrodt Medical TPI Inc, Irvine,		  CA, USA) were placed in all patients with the size chosen according to the		  patient's needs. Thirty-one patients received Shiley no.8 tubes, whereas the		  remainder were fitted with Shiley no.6 tubes. Procedure time was 5-10 min. The		  overall complication rate was 10%. In one patient, arterial oxygen saturation		  briefly decreased to 84% for 20 s as a result of intratracheal bleeding.		  Postoperative oozing occurred in one patient, requiring only local measures for		  control. Two patients, each with significant coagulopathies, had more		  significant postoperative bleeding of approximately 250 cm<sup>3</sup>. Both of		  these patients responded to local measures and correction of the underlying		  coagulopathy. On follow up, six patients died with their tracheostomies <italic>in		  situ</italic>, 28 are alive with their tracheostomies <italic>in situ</italic>, and six		  have been successfully decannulated.</p><p>The 10% complication rate encountered with the single dilator compares		  favorably with the 16% complication rate using the multiple dilators. The		  single dilator also significantly shortens operative time by several minutes by		  eliminating multiple steps in the procedure. These early data suggest that		  endoscopic PCT using the single dilator is a safe, rapid and technically simple		  procedure.</p></sec><sec><title>Ciaglia and Griggs techniques</title><p>There are several other PCT techniques described, many of which are		  fundamentally different from each other. Comparisons are important in resolving		  safety issues.</p><p>Two very different techniques were compared in the study by A&#x000f1;on		  <italic>et al</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], primarily in terms of complications		  and operative times. Although an interesting study, the report suffers from		  inherent weaknesses that raise questions about the validity of the conclusions		  reached.</p><p>First, the technical details provided are sparse, making it unclear		  exactly how the procedures were performed. Reviewing these details is important		  because they may have a direct bearing on the incidence of certain		  complications. In the Ciaglia technique, after the initial incision the		  subcutaneous fat is spread horizontally and no attempt is made to carry the		  dissection further, which could indeed result in bleeding from the thyroid		  gland. The authors mention 'repositioning' the ETT to just below		  the vocal cords. Without the use of a bronchoscope for trans-illumination		  through a previously made incision, how can this be done safely without a		  significant risk of accidental extubation? Both techniques were performed in a		  'blind' manner, without the use of a bronchoscope. There is		  increasing evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] that		  endoscopy, which allows direct step-by-step visualization of the procedure,		  significantly reduces the incidence of serious complications such as posterior		  tracheal tears, false passage, pneumothorax and subcutaneous emphysema. Indeed,		  in the article by A&#x000f1;on <italic>et al</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], a total		  of 15 complications occurred in 10 out of 63 patients. Six of these		  complications occurred in two patients, both of whom had tracheal tears; as a		  consequence of these tracheal tears, both patients also suffered a		  deterioration in oxygen saturation and developed subcutaneous emphysema. A		  false passage developed in another patient. It is likely that all seven		  aforementioned complications could have been avoided with bronchoscopy, which		  would have allowed visualization of the posterior tracheal wall and prevented		  the tears and creation of a false passage. This would have reduced the		  complication rate from 15 out of 63 (23%) to eight out of 15 (13%).</p><p>Whereas the Ciaglia technique involves blunt dilatation of an initial		  tracheal aperture by displacing adjacent tissue, in the Griggs technique		  dilatation of the tracheal aperture is achieved by passing a dilating forceps		  over the guidewire, into the trachea. Opening these forceps, which resemble a		  nasal speculum, forcibly dilates the tracheal aperture and any intervening		  tissue. Because the desirable tracheostomy site (between first and second or		  between second and third tracheal rings) often corresponds to the anatomical		  location of the thyroid isthmus, the latter may be torn on opening the dilating		  forceps, thus increasing the risk of bleeding. Three out of the four cases of		  hemorrhage occurred in the Griggs guidewire dilating forceps group. Indeed, the		  potential also exists for over-zealous insertion of the forceps through the		  posterior tracheal wall and even into the esophagus, particularly because the		  procedure is blind.</p><p>The second shortcoming of the study by A&#x000f1;on <italic>et al</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] is the lack of long-term follow up, and therefore the		  incidence of complications such as tracheal stenosis and tracheomalacia is		  unknown. Review of the literature suggests a low incidence of these		  complications in the endoscopic dilatational PCT technique.</p><p>Finally, reduced procedure time is often touted as an additional		  advantage of bedside PCT. A&#x000f1;on <italic>et al</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]		  noted a significantly lower procedure time in the Griggs guidewire dilating		  forceps technique compared with the Ciaglia technique employing multiple		  dilators. Although this may be so, it is unlikely that this difference would		  hold with the new Ciaglia single dilator kit. My experience indicates that the		  procedure can easily be performed in less than 15 min.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, bedside endoscopic dilatational PCT is a safe,		  cost-effective alternative to standard open tracheostomy in the OR. Proper		  patient selection and attention to technical detail are essential elements in		  maintaining low complication rates. In particular, direct step-by-step		  visualization with bronchoscopy adds immeasurably to the margin of safety by		  largely preventing serious complications such as false passage, pneumothorax,		  posterior tracheal wall tears and subcutaneous emphysema.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeitouni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kost</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tracheostomy: a retrospective review of 281 patients.</article-title><source>J Otolaryngol</source><year>1994</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8170024</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Indeck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Risk, cost and benefit of transporting ICU patients for special			 studies.</article-title><source>J Trauma </source><year>1988</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1020</fpage><lpage>1025</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3135417</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hazard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernitone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative clinical trial of standard operative tracheostomy with			 percutaneous tracheostomy.</article-title><source>Crit Care Med</source><year>1991</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1018</fpage><lpage>1024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1860325</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fildes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizock</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Comparison of percutaneous and surgical tracheostomies.</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>1996</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>480</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8697854</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kost</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Percutaneous tracheostomy.</article-title><source>Comprehensive Management of Swallowing Disorders. Edited by			 Carrau RL, Murry T. San Diego: Singular Publishing,</source><year>1999</year><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>284</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>A&#x000f1;on</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Escuela</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Percutaneous tracheostomy: comparison of Ciaglia and Griggs			 techniques.</article-title><source>Crit Care</source><year>2000</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11056749</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dulguerov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gysin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Perneger</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevrolet</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Percutaneous or surgical tracheostomy: a meta-analysis.</article-title><source>Crit Care Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1617</fpage><lpage>1625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10470774</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moe</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoeckli</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weymuller</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Percutaneous tracheostomy: a comprehensive evaluation.</article-title><source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source><year>1999</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10214787</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The guiding catheter is placed over the guidewire, forming the				unit over which the single dilator is introduced. Note the bronchoscope within				the ETT, trans-illuminating the incision and allowing direct visualization of				the procedure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cc686-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The single dilator is introduced in an arc-like motion over the				guidewire/guiding catheter unit. Note the expected mild compression of the				anterior tracheal wall. The integrity of the posterior wall is verified through				the bronchoscope.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cc686-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The tracheostomy tube, preloaded with the appropriate dilator, is				inserted over the guidewire/guiding catheter unit. The guidewire, guiding				catheter and dilator are removed and replaced with the tracheostomy tube inner				cannula. The patient is now ventilated through the tracheostomy tube.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cc686-3"/></fig></sec></back></article>


