<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11133405</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1240206</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">sc271_5_1835</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A 4-year-old girl with manifestations of multiple chemical sensitivities.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Pediatric Environmental Health Subspecialty Unit and Clinical Toxicology Program, Children's Hospital Boston, MA 02115, USA. woolf@a1.tch.harvard.edu</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2000</year></pub-date><volume>108</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1219</fpage><lpage>1223</lpage><abstract><p>Multiple chemical sensitivities (MCS) syndrome, also known as idiopathic environmental intolerance, is a controversial diagnosis that encompasses a wide range of waxing and waning, subjective symptoms referable to more than one body system and provoked by exposure to low levels of chemicals, foods, or other agents in the environment. Although MCS has been studied extensively, a unifying mechanism explaining the illness remains obscure, and clinicians are divided as to whether such a medical entity exists separately from psychosomatic syndromes. MCS is an adult diagnosis; there is little reference to pediatric cases in the scientific literature. In this case from the Pediatric Environmental Health Subspecialty Unit at Boston's Children's Hospital, I present the case of a preschool child who had suffered from milk allergy and poor weight gain as an infant, and then later developed asthma, allergic symptoms, sinusitis, headaches, fatigue, and rashes precipitated by an expanding variety of chemicals, foods, and allergens. I review definitions, mechanisms, diagnostic strategies, and management, and discuss some uniquely pediatric features of MCS as illustrated by this case.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

