<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mediators Inflamm</journal-id><journal-title>Mediators of Inflammation</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0962-9351</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11577993</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1781709</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects after inhalation of (1--&#x0003e;3)-beta-D-glucan in healthy humans.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thorn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><email>jorgen.thorn@envmed.gu.se</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beijer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rylander</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Environmental Medicine, G&#x000f6;teborg University, Sweden.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><abstract><p>BACKGROUND AND AIM: This study was performed to assess the effects of an exposure to a pure (1--&#x0003e;3)-beta-D-glucan, a cell wall component of fungi, plants and certain bacteria. METHODS: Twenty-one healthy subjects inhaled saline or (1--&#x0003e;3)-beta-D-glucan suspended in saline in a random, double-blind, cross-over design. They were examined before exposure and 24 and 72h afterwards with spirometry, blood sampling and collection of induced sputum. Differential cell counts and eosinophilic cationic protein (ECP) were determined in blood and sputum, and myeloperoxidase (MPO), tumour necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-alpha), and interleukin (IL)-8 and IL-10 were determined in sputum supernatants. TNF-alpha was determined after cultivation of blood mononuclear cells. RESULTS: In sputum, inhalation of saline caused a significant increase in ECP and TNF-alpha. (1--&#x0003e;3)-beta-D-Glucan inhalation caused a further increase in these cytokines, although not statistically significantly different from the increase induced by inhalation of saline alone. In blood, the number of eosinophils was significantly decreased 72 h after the challenge with (1--&#x0003e;3)-beta-D-glucan. This effect was not found after the inhalation of saline alone. TNF-alpha production from stimulated blood mononuclear cells was significantly decreased 72 h after the (1--&#x0003e;3)-beta-D-glucan inhalation as compared with the increase induced by saline inhalation. CONCLUSIONS: The results suggest that (1--&#x0003e;3)-beta-D-glucan causes a different type of response as compared with inflammatory agents such as bacterial endotoxin that cause a neutrophil-dominated inflammatory response.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

