<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Dis Obstet Gynecol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IDOG</journal-id><journal-title>Infectious Diseases in Obstetrics and Gynecology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1064-7449</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1098-0997</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17485816</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1779617</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/IDOG/2006/95618</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Douching With Water Works Device for Perceived Vaginal Odor With or Without Complaints of Discharge in Women With No Infectious Cause of Vaginitis: A Pilot Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chatwani</surname><given-names>Ashwin J.</given-names></name><xref rid="a1" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>Sarmina</given-names></name><xref rid="a2" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>Salma</given-names></name><xref rid="a2" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jeronis</surname><given-names>Stacey</given-names></name><xref rid="a2" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dandolu</surname><given-names>Vani</given-names></name><xref rid="a3" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="a1"><sup>1</sup>Division of Gynecology, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Temple University Hospital,
3401 N Broad Street, Philadelphia, PA 19140, USA</aff><aff id="a2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Temple University Hospital, 3401 N Broad Street, Philadelphia, PA 19140, USA</aff><aff id="a3"><sup>3</sup>Division of Urogynecology and Pelvic Reconstructive Surgery, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Temple University Hospital, 3401 N Broad Street, Philadelphia, PA 19140, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Ashwin J. Chatwani: <email>chatwani@temple.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>2006</volume><elocation-id>95618</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2006 Ashwin J. Chatwani et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which
                        permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work 
                        is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><p><italic>Objective</italic>. To determine if douching with Water Works device for 1 month can (1) lower or eliminate perceived vaginal odor by subject; (2) have any effects on
vaginal ecosystem. <italic>Methods</italic>. Ten women with perceived vaginal odor with or without
discharge, douched every day for 4 weeks in an open-label, nonrandomized
pilot study. Primary outcome measures included perceived vaginal odor by
subject, lactobacilli score from Nugent slide, and acceptance of the Water
Works douching system. Secondary outcome included the safety of using this
douching device. <italic>Results</italic>. At week 4, there was improvement in vaginal odor (<italic>P</italic> = .0006) and there was no significant change in lactobacilli score.
<italic>Conclusion</italic>. Douching with Water Works device is associated with reduction or
elimination of vaginal odor without adversely affecting the vaginal
ecosystem.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Vaginal symptoms, including abnormal odor with or without
complaints of discharge, are relatively common complaints for
gynecologic consultation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The evaluation of vaginal
complaints is based primarily on the diagnosis of bacterial
vaginosis (BV), trichomoniasis, and vaginal candidiasis (VVC)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Healthy women may experience vaginal discharge. The
quantity of discharge appears to vary from woman to woman and
during an individual woman's menstrual cycle. Normal vaginal fluid
may have an odor that can be unpleasant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Although BV is
the most prevalent cause of vaginal discharge or malodor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>],
studies in a variety of settings have demonstrated that neither BV
nor any pathogenic microbe can be found in approximately a third
of symptomatic women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. The presence or absence of a microbe corresponds poorly with the presence or absence of
symptoms. Clinicians are often faced with symptoms for which there
are no obvious cause.</p><p>Douching has been reported with a variety of adverse outcomes
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Studies suggest that the effects of douching are modulated by the products used for
douching [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], the reason, timing in relation to sexual
activity and menstrual cycle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. A variety of
commercial and homemade products are used for different reasons
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The determinants of douching behavior are poorly
understood even though it is widely practiced by many women in the
United States [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Although the question to douche or not
to douche is still being debated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], possible benefits
of douching are also suggested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p><p>Anecdotal evidence suggests that stainless steel has an effect in reducing
odors and is so used to reduce odors on hands by chefs. Water Works is a
medical grade, light weight (1 oz) stainless steel douching device that was
developed to aid in the treatment of vaginal infections. A pilot clinical
trial of subjects with BV using a stainless steel device showed potential
for reducing and even eliminating vaginal odor. There is no known treatment
for vaginal odor of nonbacterial origin. In addition pharmaceutical
interventions are not appropriate in the face of the inability to identify a
cause of odor. Purpose of our study was to evaluate whether douching with
Water Works device is potentially beneficial for the treatment of abnormal
vaginal odor while maintaining a normal vaginal ecosystem.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p>This open-label, nonrandomized pilot study was conducted at the Gynecology
Clinic of Temple University Hospital. The study protocol was approved by the
Temple University Institutional Review Board. Females attending the
clinic who complained of abnormal vaginal odor were screened for vaginal
infection. If clinical examination did not reveal any infection, the subject
was invited to participate in the study. Major inclusion criteria included:
(1) age 18 years and older; (2) complaint of abnormal odor with or without
complaints of discharge, (3) odor scale 3 or greater (on a scale of
0&#x02013;5, five being the worst); (4) subject not treated for BV, VVC with
intravaginal, oral antifungal medications or antibiotics, within the last 14
days of enrollment. Exclusion criteria included: (1) pregnancy; (2) under
treatment for cervical neoplasia; (3) abnormal anatomy or pathology of the
vagina; (4) known HIV positive; (5) currently menstruating; (6) external
factor (s) producing the odor and (6) body mass index (BMI) of 33 or
greater.</p></sec><sec sec-type="study design"><title>STUDY DESIGN</title><p>Women who met eligibility criteria were asked to participate in the study.
Informed consent was obtained. All subjects were treated for a total of 4
weeks. Each patient underwent entry visit, 2nd visit after two weeks of
douching and 3rd visit after 4 weeks of douching.</p></sec><sec sec-type="clinical methods during entry visit"><title>CLINICAL METHODS DURING ENTRY VISIT</title><p>Standardized history and information on present genital symptoms,
pregnancy history, contraceptive status and prior vaginitis
history was taken. Same physician examined each patient and
results were recorded on a standard form. Patient perceived
vaginal odor scores were recorded. The vaginal pH was measured and
vaginal swabs were collected from the posterior and lateral
vaginal fornices in all patients. Saline wet mount and 10% <chem-struct>KOH</chem-struct>
microscopy of vaginal secretions as well as Amine (&#x0201c;whiff&#x0201d;) test
were performed. Papanicolaou (Pap) smear were done when results
were not available or collected within 12 months. Gram stains for
Nugent score slides were sent to a central laboratory to maintain
the uniformity of the readings. Pregnancy test (urine HCG), OSOM
Trichomonas rapid test or <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> culture
(in subjects with a negative wet mount for trichomonads),
<italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> DNA test, <italic>Neisseria
gonorrhoeae</italic> DNA test were done. Herpes simplex virus culture was
done only if suspected. Vaginal yeast culture was done on all
subjects.</p></sec><sec sec-type="investigational product"><title>INVESTIGATIONAL PRODUCT</title><p>Water Works device is made of medical grade stainless steel. The
kit includes a customized water container and tubing. It is a
gravity-fed douching device, listed with the FDA that is Class I
(21 CFR 884.5900). 32 ounces tepid tap water was used as douching
fluid. Water container was hung approximately 3 feet above
the vagina (eye level). It was designed to give a water pressure
around 15 mm of mercury. Total douching time was approximately
2 min with constant manipulation of the douching device to
make contact with all of the vaginal walls.</p></sec><sec sec-type="treatment regimen"><title>TREATMENT REGIMEN</title><p>All subjects were instructed on how to use the treatment device and asked to
douche once daily with the exception of the days of evaluation and
menstruation. They were refrained from the use of other douches and
intravaginal products (eg, feminine deodorant sprays, spermicides,
tampons, and diaphragms) during the 4-week study period. They were not
allowed to take oral/intravaginal antibiotics or antifungal agents during
the 4-week study periods. Each subject kept a brief diary where they
recorded their own assessment of vaginal odor and other vaginal symptoms
during the whole length of study period. During 2nd and 3rd visits the
speculum examination of the vagina were repeated. Swabs for vaginal pH,
whiff test, saline and 10% <chem-struct>KOH</chem-struct> microscopy, were taken. Gram stain for
Nugent score was sent to the central laboratory. Perceived vaginal odor
score by the subjects were recorded.</p></sec><sec sec-type="sample size and statistical analysis"><title>SAMPLE SIZE AND STATISTICAL ANALYSIS</title><p>This is a pilot study designed to estimate potential effect sizes so we can
more reliably estimate sample size requirements for a randomized, controlled
trial. Based upon data from 10 subjects, simple descriptive statistics were
calculated. We used Student's <italic>t</italic>-test for continuous, paired variables.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>We screened 50 symptomatic women who were examined by the same gynecologist
at Temple University Hospital, Department of OB/GYN between May 2005 and
September 2005. Ten subjects met criteria and were enrolled for this pilot
study. All the enrolled patients were African American. The mean age of the
participants was 37.3 &#x000b1;  10.15 (mean &#x000b1; standard deviation) years.</p><p>At the screening visit (Entry visit), all women complained of
strong vaginal odor. The mean vaginal odor score was 4.4&#x000b1; 0.3
(range 0&#x02013;5). This odor was significantly reduced (<italic>P</italic> = .016)
after 2 weeks of vaginal douching to 2.4 &#x000b1; 0.6 (mean &#x000b1; standard error). Odor score was further reduced to 1.7 &#x000b1; 0.6
(<italic>P</italic> = .0006) after 4 weeks of douching (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).
Five out of 10 subjects perceived complete abatement of odor at
the end of study. Lactobacilli score from the Nugent slide was
4.0 &#x000b1; 0 (mean &#x000b1; standard error) on entry visit, and showed
no significant decrease during 2nd (3.3 &#x000b1; 0.3) and 3rd (3.5 &#x000b1; 0.4) visits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Mean vaginal pH was
4 at both entry visit and final visit. At the end of treatment no
statistically significant change of vaginal pH was noted.</p><p>Acceptability of the douching by the subjects was very high; one developed
asymptomatic BV detected by Nugent score. All the subjects completed the
study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The results of the present study, performed in 10 subjects with
perceived vaginal odor with no infectious cause of vaginitis,
confirm the efficacy and safety of the douching once
daily for 4 weeks. At the first follow-up visit after 2 weeks of
vaginal douching the perceived vaginal odor was 40% reduced.
The second follow-up visit after 4 weeks of treatment further
confirmed the effectiveness of douching by reducing the odor by
59% of baseline value. Half of the subjects showed complete
recovery of their complaint of vaginal odor. Lactobacilli are the
predominant bacteria in normal vaginal flora [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. They
maintain an acidic environment (pH of 4.5 or less in normal
vagina), considered to be one of the protective mechanisms of the
vagina [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Several in vitro and in vivo experiments in
humans have examined how douching affects vaginal pH and
microflora [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Douching may wash away lactobacilli and
protective factors and weaken the defense system in the vaginal
ecology. In our study, douching induced no negative modification
of the vaginal flora, as observed by lactobacilli score from
Nugent slides and vaginal pH determination. Although douching has
not been recommended for frequent use, previous study of daily
douching caused no significant alterations in vaginal pH, which is
in support of our finding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. BV is likely to occur when
the balance between protective organism and potential pathogens is
adversely altered.</p><p>Intensity and methods of douching, especially douching with pressure,
have been associated with adverse outcomes. Therefore, the risk of ascending
infection from the pressure of douching may be greatest around the time of
ovulation when the cervical os is gaping and the mucus is thin. Recent study
did not support the relation between douching and either
gonococcal/chlamydial genital infection or pelvic inflammatory
diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. The Water Works douching device is designed so that the
water is directed downward away from the cervical os and also it is gravity
fed to avoid the ascending infection. We did not observe any symptoms of
pelvic infection during the length of study.</p><p>There are several limitations to our study. Vaginal
discharge and odor were self-reported by participants, and at
present, there are no validated instruments for objective
assessment of vaginal symptoms. The size of small study population
is our other limitation, but examination of all patients by the
same physician and reading of slides for Nugent score by the same
person at a central laboratory are the strengths of our study.
Because this was a nonblinded study, there is the potential of
reporting bias by both the clinician and the subject. Finally we
did not attempt to follow up the patients to determine long-term
effect of frequent douching.</p><p>Our findings suggest that further study of douching in a randomized,
controlled trial is warranted. Future studies should also optimize the
length and frequency of treatment. Nonetheless, our data suggest that the
Water Works Douching Device is beneficial for the treatment of vaginal odor
with no objective findings of vaginal infection while maintaining a
normal vaginal ecosystem.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</title><p>The study was supported by a grant from Abbott Research Group, Pittsburgh, Pa, USA.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of vaginitis</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic></source><year>1991</year><volume>165</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1168</fpage><lpage>1176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1951572</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Rakel</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bope</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vulvovaginitis</article-title><source><italic>Conn's Current Therapy</italic></source><year>2003</year><publisher-loc>Philadelphia, Pa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>WB Saunders</publisher-name><fpage>1149</fpage><lpage>1152</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mulley</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Goroll</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulley</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Approach to the patient with a vaginal discharge</article-title><source><italic>Primary Care Medicine: Office Evaluation and Management of the Adult Patient</italic></source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Philadelphia, Pa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><fpage>702</fpage><lpage>707</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ingalls</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sexually transmitted diseases</article-title><source><italic>Textbook of Primary Care Medicine</italic></source><year>1996</year><publisher-loc>St. Louis, Mo</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mosby-Year Book</publisher-name><fpage>856</fpage><lpage>857</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajamanoharan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozniak</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial vaginosis, ethnicity, and the use of genital cleaning agents: a case control study</article-title><source><italic>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</italic></source><year>1999</year><volume>26</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10458635</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaaf</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Stable</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Borchardt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The limited value of symptoms and signs in the diagnosis of vaginal infections</article-title><source><italic>Archives of Internal Medicine</italic></source><year>1990</year><volume>150</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1929</fpage><lpage>1933</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2393324</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Heidrich</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fihn</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Establishing the cause of genitourinary symptoms in women in a family practice. Comparison of clinical examination and comprehensive microbiology</article-title><source><italic>Journal of the American Medical Association</italic></source><year>1984</year><volume>251</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>620</fpage><lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6690835</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Leybovich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaginal douching and adverse health effects: a meta-analysis</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of Public Health</italic></source><year>1997</year><volume>87</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1207</fpage><lpage>1211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9240115</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>La Ruche</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Messou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali-Napo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vaginal douching: association with lower genital tract infections in African pregnant women</article-title><source><italic>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</italic></source><year>1999</year><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10225584</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joesoef</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumampouw</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Linnan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Idajadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>St Louis</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Douching and sexually transmitted diseases in pregnant women in Surabaya, Indonesia</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic></source><year>1996</year><volume>174</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8571993</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Voigt</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Daling</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaginal douching and reduced fertility</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of Public Health</italic></source><year>1996</year><volume>86</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>844</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8659660</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scholes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Stergachis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Grayston</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaginal douching as a risk factor for acute pelvic inflammatory disease</article-title><source><italic>Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic></source><year>1993</year><volume>81</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8459976</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavlova</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro inhibition of commercial douche products against vaginal microflora</article-title><source><italic>Infectious Diseases in Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic></source><year>2000</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10805365</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does douching promote ascending infection?</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Reproductive Medicine</italic></source><year>1992</year><volume>37</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>930</fpage><lpage>938</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1460612</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The repertoire of human efforts to avoid sexually transmissible diseases: past and present. Part 2: strategies used during or after sex</article-title><source><italic>Sexually Transmitted Infections</italic></source><year>2000</year><volume>76</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10858708</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional intravaginal practices and the heterosexual transmission of disease: a review</article-title><source><italic>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</italic></source><year>2000</year><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10782738</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Czerwinski</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adult feminine hygiene practices</article-title><source><italic>Applied Nursing Research</italic></source><year>1996</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8771856</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The great douching debate: to douche, or not to douche</article-title><source><italic>Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic></source><year>2000</year><volume>95</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10711568</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monif</surname><given-names>GRG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The great douching debate: to douche, or not to douche</article-title><source><italic>Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic></source><year>1999</year><volume>94</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10511372</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tevi-B&#x000e9;nissan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e9;lec</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000e9;vy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vivo semen-associated pH neutralization of cervicovaginal secretions</article-title><source><italic>Clinical and Diagnostic Laboratory Immunology</italic></source><year>1997</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9144379</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Horowitz</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mardh</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic>Vaginitis and Vaginosis</italic></source><year>1991</year><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley-Liss</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwebke</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatch</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaginal infections</article-title><source><italic>Women &#x00026; Health</italic></source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>San Diego, Calif</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>360</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juliano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Piu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanetti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro antibacterial activity of antiseptics against vaginal lactobacilli</article-title><source><italic>European Journal of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases</italic></source><year>1992</year><volume>11</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1166</fpage><lpage>1169</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glynn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Daily douching: effect on vaginal mucosa</article-title><source><italic>Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic></source><year>1963</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>640</fpage><lpage>642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14082288</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ness</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kip</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Douching, pelvic inflammatory disease, and incident gonococcal and chlamydial genital infection in a cohort of high-risk women</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of Epidemiology</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>161</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15632269</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Perceived vaginal odor scored from the visual analog scale by subjects shows significant
reduction (*<italic>P</italic> = .016) on 2nd visit with further reduction
(**<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .0006) on 3rd visit. Data presented as mean
&#x000b1; standard error, <italic>n</italic> = 10.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IDOG2006-95618.001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Lactobacilli score from the Nugent slide at entry, 2nd and 4th visit showed no significant
(<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; .05) decrease from baseline during 2nd and 3rd visit. Data
expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error, <italic>n</italic> = 10.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IDOG2006-95618.002"/></fig></sec></back></article>





