<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Dis Obstet Gynecol</journal-id><journal-title>Infectious Diseases in Obstetrics and Gynecology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1064-7449</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1098-0997</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16240515</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1784567</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The efficacy and safety of a single dose of Clindesse vaginal cream versus a seven-dose regimen of Cleocin vaginal cream in patients with bacterial vaginosis.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Faro</surname><given-names>Sebastian</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Skokos</surname><given-names>Campbell K</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><collab>Clindesse Investigators Group</collab></contrib></contrib-group><aff>The Woman's Hospital of Texas, Houston, Texas 77054, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><abstract><p>OBJECTIVE: To determine whether a single dose of Clindesse vaginal cream is comparable in efficacy and safety to Cleocin vaginal cream administered once daily for 7 days in the treatment of bacterial vaginosis. STUDY DESIGN: This multicenter, randomized, single-blind, parallel-group study enrolled 540 patients with BV infections. Treatment consisted of either a single intravaginal dose of Clindesse or 7 daily doses of Cleocin. Efficacy and safety were assessed 21-30 days after the start of treatment. The efficacy endpoints were Investigator Cure, Clinical Cure (a composite of all 4 Amsel's criteria and Investigator Cure), Nugent Cure (Nugent score &#x0003c; 4), and Therapeutic Cure (a composite of Clinical Cure and Nugent Cure). Resolution of individual Amsel's criteria was also evaluated. Treatment-emergent adverse events were monitored throughout the study. RESULTS: There were no significant differences in cure rates between the Clindesse and Cleocin treatment groups in Investigator Cure (P=0.702), Clinical Cure (P=0.945), Nugent Cure (P=0.788), or Therapeutic Cure (P=0.572). Results were also similar for 3 of 4 and 2 of 4 Amsel's criteria and for each individual Amsel's criterion (all P-values &#x0003e;0.200). Ninety-five percent confidence intervals for each endpoint were consistent with equivalence between the 2 products. There was no significant difference between the treatment groups in the incidence of treatment-emergent adverse events (P=0.386). CONCLUSIONS: A single dose of Clindesse vaginal cream is equivalent in safety and efficacy to a 7-dose regimen of Cleocin vaginal cream in the treatment of bacterial vaginosis. This represents a significant advance in the treatment of bacterial vaginosis.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

