<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Dis Obstet Gynecol</journal-id><journal-title>Infectious Diseases in Obstetrics and Gynecology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1064-7449</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1098-0997</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10449266</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1784744</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1098-0997(1999)7:4&#x0003c;186::AID-IDOG4&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-Z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of 5-fluorouracil for the treatment of cervicovaginal human papillomavirus.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>M M</given-names></name><email>holmesm@musc.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>S H</given-names><suffix>2nd</suffix></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vermillion</surname><given-names>S T</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Medical University of South Carolina, Charleston 29425, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>1999</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><abstract><p>OBJECTIVE: To compare intravaginal 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) and placebo for the treatment of cervical and/or vaginal human papillomavirus (HPV). METHODS: A randomized, placebo-controlled trial was performed. Women with HPV detected visually or by Papanicolaou (Pap) test and confirmed by colposcopic biopsy were randomized to receive either intravaginal 5-FU cream or an intravaginal placebo cream. Women with cervical or vaginal intraepithelial neoplasia were excluded. The primary outcome measure was cytologic regression of HPV as determined by Pap test screening 4 to 6 months after treatment. The secondary outcome was cytologic evidence of disease progression at both the 4-6-month and 12-month follow-up evaluations. Data were analyzed using the Chi square test with significance established at P &#x0003c; 0.05. RESULTS: A total of forty patients were randomized, and thirty patients had a follow-up Pap test 4 to 6 months after treatment. Of those patients treated with 5-FU, 28% demonstrated regression of HPV on cytologic evaluation, compared with 69% of those treated with placebo (P &#x0003c; 0.05). Twelve-month follow-up cytology was available from 18 of the study participants. There were no significant differences in the frequency of cytologic progression or regression between groups at 12 months. CONCLUSION: Four to six months post treatment, the use of intravaginal 5-FU for the treatment of cervical or vaginal HPV is associated with a lower rate of regression than the use of placebo.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

