<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9432971</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1533022</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Birth weight and sex of children and the correlation to the body burden of PCDDs/PCDFs and PCBs of the mother.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vartiainen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jaakkola</surname><given-names>J J</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saarikoski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tuomisto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Division of Environmental Health, National Public Health Institute, Kuopio, Finland.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>106</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><abstract><p>Polychlorinated dibenzo-p-dioxins (PCDDs), polychlorinated dibenzofurans (PCDFs), and polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) were analyzed in 167 random human milk samples from urban and rural areas in Finland. Dietary habits and background information on each mother and child were gathered by questionnaire. Body mass indexes (BMI) before pregnancy and delivery in the rural area were 5-10% higher than in the urban area, but fat content of mother's milk was about 10% higher in the urban area. The mean weights of children (+/- standard deviation) were similar in the rural and urban areas among primiparae, 3,500 +/- 597 g and 3,505 +/- 454 g, respectively, although dioxin international toxic equivalents (I-TEQs) were significantly higher in the urban area. The mother's level of education did not affect the weight of the child, but concentrations of PCDDs/PCDFs (I-TEQ, 2,3,4,7,8-Cl5 dibenzofuran,1,2, 3,7,8-Cl5 dibenzodioxin) and PCBs [sum of PCBs (sumPCB), PCB-TEQ, and most PCB congeners] increased with advanced education. This is considered to be due to differences in the mother's consumption of fish. The birth weight, especially of boys, slightly decreased with increasing concentrations of I-TEQ, 2,3,4,7,8-Cl5 dibenzofuran, 1,2,3, 7,8-Cl5 dibenzodioxin, and 2,3,7,8-Cl4 dibenzodioxin; however, when the analysis was restricted to primiparae, there was no statistically significant correlation between birth weight and the concentrations of PCDDs/PCDFs. No correlation was found between the weight of the child and PCBs, PCB-TEQs, or individual PCB congeners in the whole material or among primiparae, or among boys or girls. The concentrations of PCDDs/PCDFs and PCBs inhuman milk were modeled for primiparae by weighing fish consumption, age of mother, milk fat content, and BMI before pregnancy. The linear regression resulted in values of R = 0.67 and 0.30 for the modeled dioxin I-TEQs in the urban and rural areas, respectively, and the corresponding values for sumPCBs of R = 0.60 and 0.11. The increase of PCDD/PCDF body burden was calculated to be on average 0.58 pg I-TEQ/g milk fat/year in the urban area and 0.39 pg I-TEQ/g milk fat/year in the rural area.</p><sec sec-type="scanned-figures"><title>Images</title><fig id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0053-a" xlink:role="63"/></fig><fig id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0054-a" xlink:role="64"/></fig><fig id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0055-a" xlink:role="65"/></fig></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0051.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="61" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0052.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="62" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0053.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="63" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0054.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="64" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0055.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="65" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0056.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="66" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

