<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8260367</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1968636</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A randomised trial of three or six courses of etoposide cyclophosphamide methotrexate and vincristine or six courses of etoposide and ifosfamide in small cell lung cancer (SCLC). I: Survival and prognostic factors. Medical Research Council Lung Cancer Working Party.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bleehen</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Girling</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Machin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>1993</year></pub-date><volume>68</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1150</fpage><lpage>1156</lpage><abstract><p>A total of 458 eligible patients, from 21 centres, with histologically or cytologically confirmed SCLC were allocated at random to three chemotherapy regimens, each given at 3-week intervals. In two regimens, etoposide, cyclophosphamide, methotrexate and vincristine were given for a total of either three courses (ECMV3) or six courses (ECMV6). In the third regimen, etoposide and ifosfamide were given for six courses (EI6). Patients with limited disease (56% of the total) also received radiotherapy to the primary site after the third course of chemotherapy in all three groups. A partial response occurred in 45% of 144 ECMV3 patients, 48% of 141 ECMV6, and 53% of 141 EI6 patients assessed, and a complete response in a further 15%, 9%, and 13% respectively, giving total response rates of 60%, 57%, and 67%, respectively. There was no overall survival advantage to any of the three regimens. At 1 year, 24%, 29%, and 30% of patients were alive, and at 2 years 7%, 8%, and 9%, respectively. The median survival time was 7.4 months in the ECMV3 group, 8.6 months in the ECMV6 group and 8.8 months in the EI6 group. The individual factors: poor performance status, extensive disease, the presence of dysphagia and a raised white blood cell count on admission adversely affected prognosis. The results do not exclude the possibility of a minor survival advantage with the two 6-course regimens. The findings on quality of life are presented in the companion paper (MRC Lung Cancer Working Party, 1993b).</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0106.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1150" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0107.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1151" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0108.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1152" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0109.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1153" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0110.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1154" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0111.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1155" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0112.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1156" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

