<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8318412</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1968314</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Is 6-thioguanine more appropriate than 6-mercaptopurine for children with acute lymphoblastic leukaemia?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lennard</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lilleyman</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>University of Sheffield Department of Medicine, Royal Hallamshire Hospital, UK.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>1993</year></pub-date><volume>68</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><abstract><p>The cytotoxic activity of 6-mercaptopurine (6-MP) is affected by thiopurine methyltransferase (TPMT), a genetically regulated and variable intracellular enzyme. 6-Thioguanine (6-TG), a closely related thiopurine, is less affected by that enzyme and so it may be a more reliable drug-at least for patients with constitutionally high TPMT activity. We attempted to assess its suitability as an alternative by comparing the pharmacokinetics of both drugs in a small group of children with lymphoblastic leukaemia (ALL). Patients were included who were in their second or subsequent remission, who would otherwise have received 6-MP, and on whom pharmacokinetic data concerning 6-MP metabolism had been collected in a previous remission. Plasma 6-TG concentrations were assayed following an oral dose of 40 mg m-2, and the accumulation and fluctuation of intracellular (erythrocyte, RBC) 6-TG nucleotides (6-TGNs) were measured at regular intervals during daily oral therapy. Seven children were studied. Plasma 6-TG concentrations were low and cleared within 6 h of oral dosing. At 7 days, 6-TGN concentrations ranged from 959 to 2361 pmol 8 x 10(-8) RBCs, in all cases significantly higher (P = 0.002) than those produced by the same patients on 6-MP. After a total therapy time of 35 patient months, a modest rise of alanine aminotransferase was seen on one occasion, otherwise no toxicity apart from myelosuppression was encountered. In the context used, 6-TG appears well tolerated and produces higher concentrations of intracellular cytotoxic metabolites than 6-MP. For children constitutionally 'resistant' to the traditional drug, if not all, it may be a preferable alternative.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00197-0196.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="186" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00197-0197.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="187" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00197-0198.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="188" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00197-0199.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="189" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00197-0200.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="190" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

