<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mediators Inflamm</journal-id><journal-title>Mediators of Inflammation</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0962-9351</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11759109</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1781718</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cell adhesion molecules and hyaluronic acid as markers of inflammation, fibrosis and response to antiviral therapy in chronic hepatitis C patients.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Granot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><email>etgranot@md2.huji.ac.il</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shouval</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ashur</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Pediatric Gastroenterology Unit, Pediatrics Department, Hebrew University-Hadassah Medical School, PO. Box 12000, Jerusalem 91120, Israel.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><abstract><p>OBJECTIVE: Cell adhesion molecules (intracellular adhesion molecule-1 (ICAM-1), vascular cell adhesion molecule-1 (VCAM-1)) and hyaluronic acid, markers of inflammation and fibrosis were monitored in hepatitis C patients to determine whether changes in plasma levels, during antiviral treatment, can predict long-term response to therapy. METHODS: In 55 patients with chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV), 33 treated with interferon (IFN) and 22 treated with IFN + ribavirin, sera was collected prior to treatment, at 3 + 6 months of therapy and 6 months post-treatment. Levels of ICAM-1, VCAM-1 and hyaluronic acid were correlated with alanine aminotransferase levels, HCV-RNA-polymerase chain reaction status and histological fibrosis scoring. RESULTS: A decrease in ICAM-1 levels at 3 and 6 months of therapy, compared with pretreatment levels, was observed in responders to IFN + ribavirin therapy but this decrease in ICAM-1 levels was not evident following cessation of treatment. Hyaluronic acid levels, in both treatment groups, did not differ significantly between responders and non-responders. Hyaluronic acid levels did correlate, significantly, with degree of fibrosis whereas VCAM-1 levels were marginally increased only in patients with moderate (grade III) fibrosis. CONCLUSIONS: Monitoring of VCAM-1 and hyaluronic acid, during antiviral therapy, does not differentiate between responders and non-responders. A decrease in ICAM-1 levels during IFN + ribavirin treatment is associated with response to therapy, and its efficacy in predicting long-term response should be further substantiated.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

