<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">2145964</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1971476</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The clinical and endocrine effects of 4-hydroxyandrostenedione alone and in combination with goserelin in premenopausal women with advanced breast cancer.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dowsett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hedley</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gazet</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>H. T.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coombes</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Clinical Oncology Unit, St George's Hospital Medical School, London, UK.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>1990</year></pub-date><volume>62</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><abstract><p>The aromatase inhibitor, 4-hydroxyandrostenedione (4OHA) is an effective treatment for advanced post-menopausal breast cancer. The clinical and endocrine effects of 4OHA treatment were studied in five pre- and perimenopausal women with metastatic breast cancer. Serum oestradiol levels were not significantly reduced as a result of treatment with 500 mg of 4OHA by weekly i.m. injections and no patient had a tumour response. Four patients were subsequently treated with the luteinising hormone releasing hormone (LHRH) analogue, gosereline, and three had objective responses. The endocrine effects of combined treatment with goserelin (Zoladex), and 4OHA were studied in a further five premenopausal women. Serum oestradiol levels after treatment with goserelin alone were typical of post-menopausal women. Addition of 4OHA led to a further suppression of oestradiol to within the range observed in post-menopausal patients treated with further suppression of oestradiol to within the range observed in post-menopausal patients treated with 4OHA. Six patients whose tumours had regressed as a result of goserelin treatment and who subsequently relapsed were then given combined treatment. Four of the six experienced a second remission. We conclude that while 4OHA alone is unlikely to be a satisfactory treatment for premenopausal patients with advanced breast cancer, 4OHA in conjunction with goserelin leads to profound suppression of oestradiol. The combination of LHRH analogue and aromatase inhibitor may prove to be a superior treatment to LHRH analogue alone in these patients.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00218-0131.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="679" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00218-0132.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="680" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00218-0133.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="681" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00218-0134.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="682" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00218-0135.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="683" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

