<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Dis Obstet Gynecol</journal-id><journal-title>Infectious Diseases in Obstetrics and Gynecology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1064-7449</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1098-0997</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9785106</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1784789</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1098-0997(1998)6:3&#x0003c;109::AID-IDOG3&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-S</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Daily oral grepafloxacin vs. twice daily oral doxycycline in the treatment of Chlamydia trachomatis endocervical infection.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>W M</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D H</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hook</surname><given-names>E W</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R B</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>SUNY Health Science Center at Brooklyn 11203, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><abstract><p>OBJECTIVE: To compare the efficacy and safety of a 7-day course of treatment with oral grepafloxacin, 400 mg once daily, and oral doxycycline, 100 mg twice daily, in patients with chlamydial cervicitis. METHODS: Women aged 18 years or older attending 17 sexually transmitted disease clinics in the United States who had clinical signs of mucopurulent cervicitis or who had a recent positive culture or nonculture test for Chlamydia trachomatis or who had contact with a male partner with a positive culture for C. trachomatis were enrolled into this randomized, double-blind, active-controlled clinical study. The diagnosis of chlamydial cervicitis was based on culture for C. trachomatis. Patients were randomized to receive a 7-day course of treatment with either oral grepafloxacin, 400 mg once daily, or oral doxycycline, 100 mg twice daily. Response to therapy was assessed 3-8 days and 21-28 days after completion of treatment. The primary measure of efficacy was eradication of C. trachomatis at the 21-28 day follow-up visit. Clinical success, defined as improvement or complete resolution of the signs and symptoms of cervicitis, was a secondary measure of efficacy. RESULTS: Of the 451 female patients enrolled, 228 received grepafloxacin and 223 received doxycycline. In all, 154/451 (35%) patients were evaluable at the 21-28 day follow-up (81 who received grepafloxacin and 73 who received doxycycline). Microbiologic and clinical success rates demonstrated the equivalence of the two treatments. The C. trachomatis eradication rates were 96.3% (78/81) and 98.6% (72/73) for patients receiving grepafloxacin or doxycycline, respectively. The two study drugs were also equivalent in resolving clinical signs and symptoms, with clinical success rates of 88.9% (64/72) and 89.5% (51/57) for patients treated with grepafloxacin and doxycycline, respectively. Both drugs were well tolerated, with 47% of patients receiving grepafloxacin and 46% of patients receiving doxycycline experiencing drug-related adverse events, none of which was serious. CONCLUSIONS: Seven days of treatment with oral grepafloxacin, 400 mg once daily, was as effective as 7 days of treatment with oral doxycycline, 100 mg twice daily, in patients with cervicitis caused by C. trachomatis. Both agents were well tolerated and had comparable safety profiles. Grepafloxacin's once-daily dosing regimen may offer advantages in terms of patient compliance.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

