<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7889886</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1566644</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of boron supplementation on bone mineral density and dietary, blood, and urinary calcium, phosphorus, magnesium, and boron in female athletes.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meacham</surname><given-names>S L</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Taper</surname><given-names>L J</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Volpe</surname><given-names>S L</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Human Nutrition, Winthrop University, Rock Hill, South Carolina 29733.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>1994</year></pub-date><volume>102</volume><issue>Suppl 7</issue><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><abstract><p>The effects of boron supplementation on blood and urinary minerals were studied in female college students--17 athletes and 11 sedentary controls--over a one-year period. The athletes had lower percent body fat and higher aerobic capacities than sedentary controls. Athletic subjects consumed more boron in their normal diets than sedentary subjects; all other dietary measures were similar between the two groups. The athletes showed a slight increase in bone mineral density, whereas the sedentary group showed a slight decrease. Serum phosphorus concentrations were lower in boron-supplemented subjects than in subjects receiving placebos, and were lower at the end of the study period than during baseline analysis. Activity depressed changes in serum phosphorus in boron-supplemented subjects. Serum magnesium concentrations were greatest in the sedentary controls whose diets were supplemented with boron, and increased with time in all subjects. A group x supplement interaction was observed with serum magnesium; exercise in boron-supplemented subjects lowered serum magnesium. In all subjects, calcium excretion increased over time; in boron-supplemented subjects, boron excretion increased over time. In all subjects, boron supplementation affected serum phosphorus and magnesium, and the excretion of urinary boron.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="envhper00403-0080.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="79" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00403-0081.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="80" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00403-0082.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="81" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00403-0083.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="82" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

