<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">1733432</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1977364</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Time to loco-regional recurrence after resection of Dukes' B and C colorectal cancer with or without adjuvant postoperative radiotherapy. A multivariate regression analysis.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bentzen</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balslev</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Teglbjaerg</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hanberg-S&#x000f8;rensen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bone</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>N. O.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bertelsen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></contrib><etal/></contrib-group><aff>Danish Cancer Society, Department of Experimental Clinical Oncology, Aarhus C.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>1992</year></pub-date><volume>65</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><abstract><p>Factors influencing time to loco-regional recurrence were identified in a multivariate regression analysis of data from a series of 468 radically operated patients (260 Dukes' B and 208 Dukes' C) with carcinoma of the rectum and the rectosigmoid. A number of clinical and pathological characteristics were prospectively collected and recorded. In addition, carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) was measured within 1 week before surgery. The endpoint used was recurrence below the level of the umbilicus. All patients were followed for at least 5 years or until time of death. The two Dukes' stages B and C were analysed in two separate analyses using the Cox proportional hazards model. In patients with Dukes' B tumours, an increased risk of loco-regional recurrence was associated with perineural invasion, tumour located less than 10 cm from the anal verge, patient aged above 70 years, and small tumour size. In patients with Dukes' C tumours, the necessity to resect neighbour organs, perineural and venous invasion, tumour located less than 10 cm from the anal verge, and large tumour size were all associated with a poor loco-regional outcome. Postoperative radiotherapy was not a significant prognosticator for loco-regional control. An update of the 5-year results of the randomised study of post-operative radiotherapy (50 Gy with 2 Gy per fraction in an overall treatment time of 7 weeks) showed no survival benefit from adjuvant radiotherapy in either Dukes' category and no statistically significant improvement in the 5-year loco-regional control rate. However, when the comparison was restricted to a group of high-risk patients there was a statistically significant benefit from radiotherapy with respect to loco-regional control (P = 0.03) but not with respect to survival (P = 0.23). The potential advantage, in terms of the required number of patients, of restricting clinical trials of intensified loco-regional therapies to the high-risk patients, is illustrated.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00065-0110.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="102" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00065-0111.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="103" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00065-0112.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="104" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00065-0113.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="105" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00065-0114.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="106" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00065-0115.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="107" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

