<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Dis Obstet Gynecol</journal-id><journal-title>Infectious Diseases in Obstetrics and Gynecology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1064-7449</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1098-0997</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">12530484</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1784609</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of adjuvant imiquimod 5% cream on sustained clearance of anogenital warts following laser treatment.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hoyme</surname><given-names>U B</given-names></name><email>uhoyme@klinikum-erfurt.de</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hagedorn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>A E</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schneede</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hopfenm&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schorn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Helios Klinikum Erfurt, Germany.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2002</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><abstract><p>OBJECTIVES: Imiquimod is an immune response modifier that has demonstrated a good efficacy and relatively low recurrence rates in comparison to other genital wart treatment modalities. The primary objective of this open-label study was to evaluate the effect on sustained clearance of treated lesions and the safety of patient-applied topical imiquimod after laser therapy of external anogenital warts. METHODS: After laser treatment of visible external anogenital warts the ablated region(s) were treated with imiquimod 5% cream three times/week over 12 weeks beginning when the wound healing process was completed, followed by a six-month treatment-free observation period for the assessment of sustained clearance of treated lesions. RESULTS: A total of 211 male and female patients was enrolled in the study. After 12 weeks of treatment, 65.4% of all patients showed sustained clearance. During the treatment period, 15 patients (7.1% of 211 patients) presented with recurrent warts in the treated areas, and 58 (27.5%) patients were excluded for other reasons. During the six-month follow-up period, ten additional patients (7.3% of 138 patients) developed wart recurrences. The application of imiquimod 5% cream was well tolerated. The number of patients with adverse events related to study medication declined from the first month of treatment until the end of the third month. Most frequently, mild to moderate itching, burning, pain and erythema were reported. CONCLUSIONS: After laser therapy and sufficient wound healing, administration of imiquimod 5% cream three times/week appears to be safe and to reduce the incidence of wart recurrences.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

