<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10379008</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1566653</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">sc271_5_1835</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Occupational asthma and contact dermatitis in a spray painter after introduction of an aziridine cross-linker.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leffler</surname><given-names>C T</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Milton</surname><given-names>D K</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Occupational Health Program, Department of Environmental Health, Harvard School of Public Health, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>1999</year></pub-date><volume>107</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><abstract><p>A 23-year-old spray painter developed contact dermatitis and respiratory difficulty characterized by small airways obstruction shortly after the polyfunctional aziridine cross-linker CX-100 began to be used in his workplace as a paint activator. The symptoms resolved after he was removed from the workplace and was treated with inhaled and topical steroids. Painters may have an increased risk of asthma due to exposure to a variety of agents, such as isocyanates, alkyd resins, and chromates. This case illustrates the importance of using appropriate work practices and personal protective equipment to minimize exposure. Occupational asthma is diagnosed by a history of work-related symptoms and exposure to known causative agents. The diagnosis is confirmed by serial pulmonary function testing or inhalational challenge testing. The risk of asthma attributable to occupational exposures is probably underappreciated due to underreporting and to inappropriate use of narrow definitions of exposure in epidemiologic studies of attributable risk.</p><sec sec-type="scanned-figures"><title>Images</title><fig id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><graphic xlink:href="envhper00512-0128-a" xlink:role="600"/></fig></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="envhper00512-0127.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="599" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00512-0128.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="600" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00512-0129.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="601" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

