<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cardiothorac Surg</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Cardiothoracic Surgery</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1749-8090</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16984626</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1586008</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1749-8090-1-27</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1749-8090-1-27</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation of 17-mm St. Jude Medical Regent prosthetic aortic heart valves by rest and dobutamine stress echocardiography</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Minardi</surname><given-names>Giovanni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>giovanni.minardi@libero.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Manzara</surname><given-names>Carla</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>cmanzara@scamilloforlanini.rm.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Creazzo</surname><given-names>Vittorio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>vcreazzo@scamilloforlanini.rm.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maselli</surname><given-names>Daniele</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>dmaselli@scamilloforlanini.rm.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Casali</surname><given-names>Giovanni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>gcasali@scamilloforlanini.rm.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pulignano</surname><given-names>Giovanni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>gipulig@yahoo.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Musumeci</surname><given-names>Francesco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>fmusumeci@scamilloforlanini.rm.it</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Cardiology and Cardiovascular Surgery, Azienda Ospedaliera, S.Camillo-Forlanini, Rome, Italy</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cardiothoracicsurgery.org/content/1/1/27"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2006 Minardi et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Minardi et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Minardi
               Giovanni
               
               giovanni.minardi@libero.it
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Evaluation of 17-mm St. Jude Medical Regent prosthetic aortic heart valves by rest and dobutamine stress echocardiography
         </dc:title><dc:date>2006</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Journal of Cardiothoracic Surgery 1(1): 27-. (2006)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1749-8090(2006)1:1&#x0003c;27&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1749-8090</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The prosthesis used for aortic valve replacement in patients with small aortic root can be too small in relation to body size, thus showing high transvalvular gradients at rest and/or under stress conditions. This study was carried out to evaluate rest and Dobutamine stress echocardiography (DSE) hemodynamic response of 17-mm St. Jude Medical Regent (SJMR-17 mm) in relatively aged patients at mean 24 months follow-up.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods and results</title><p>The study population consisted of 19 patients (2 men, 17 women, mean age 69.2 &#x000b1; 7.3 years). All patients underwent rest Doppler echocardiography before and after surgery and basal and DSE at follow up (infused at rate of 5 micrg/Kg/min and increased by 5 microg/Kg/min at 5 min intervals up to 40 microg/Kg/min). The following parameters were evaluated at rest and/or under DSE: heart rate (HR), ejection fraction (EF), cardiac output (CO), peak and mean velocity and pressure gradients (MxV, MnV, MxPG, MnPG), effective orifice area (EOA), indexed EOA (EOAi), left ventricular mass (LVM), indexed LVM (LVMi), Velocity Time Integral at left ventricular outflow tract (VTI LVOT) and transvalvular (Aortic VTI), Doppler velocity index (DVI). At rest MxPG and MnPG were 29.2 &#x000b1; 7.1 and 16.6 &#x000b1; 5.8mmHg, respectively; EOA and EOAi resulted 1.14 &#x000b1; 0.3 cm<sup>2</sup> and 0.76 &#x000b1; 0.2 cm<sup>2</sup>/m<sup>2</sup>; DVI was normal (0.50 &#x000b1; 0.1). At follow-up LVM and LVMi decreased significantly from pre-operative value of 258 &#x000b1; 43g and 157.4 &#x000b1; 27.7g/m<sup>2</sup> to 191 &#x000b1; 23.8g and 114.5 &#x000b1; 10.6g/m<sup>2</sup>, respectively. DSE increased significantly HR, CO, EF, MxGP (up to 83.4 &#x000b1; 2 1.9mmHg), MnPG (up to 43.2 &#x000b1; 12.7mmHg). EOA, EOAi, DVI increased insignificantly (from baseline up to 1.2 &#x000b1; 0.4 cm<sup>2</sup>, 0.75 &#x000b1; 0.3cm<sup>2</sup>/m<sup>2</sup> and 0.48 &#x000b1; 0.1 respectively). Two patients developed significant intraventricular gradients.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>These data show that SJMR 17-mm prostheses can be safely implanted in aortic position in relatively aged patients, offering a satisfactory hemodynamic performance at rest and under DSE, with full utilization of its available orifice, suggesting that a possible mild prosthesis-patient mismatch is not an issue of clinical relevance when this small prosthesis is used. Rest and Dobutamine stress echocardiography is a useful and effective means for evaluating prosthesis hemodynamics and for monitoring the expected LVH regression.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Patients who have received prosthetic heart valves are usually followed by clinical evaluation and basal echocardiographic examinations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Patients who receive a small aortic valve prosthesis may remain asymptomatic following surgery and Doppler echocardiography may show normal or mild elevated transvalvular gradients at rest, even in patients with large body surface area (BSA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. However, this may not be representative of a patient's daily activities. Evaluation of valve hemodynamic response during stress conditions may offer useful information, simulating preclinical valve "dysfunction" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Information derived from exercise stress echocardiography is limited because of the difficulty in obtaining adequate Doppler signals either due to the respiratory-related artefacts or to the increased chest wall motion during or immediately after exercise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Recently, dobutamine stress echocardiography (DSE) has been proposed as an alternative and equally effective means for the hemodynamic evaluation of small aortic prosthetic valves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. This pharmacological test does not have the above limitations. This study was carried out to evaluate rest and DSE hemodynamic response of 17 mm St. Jude Medical Regent (SJMR-17 mm) aortic prosthesis in relatively aged patients. The SJM Regent is a new-generation mechanical heart valve that represents the design evolution of the St. Jude Hemodynamic Plus (SJM HP) series. It is constructed of pyrolytic carbon which has a modified external profile that achieves a larger geometric orifice area without changing the existing design of the pivot mechanism or blood-contact surface area. The SJMR-17 mm valve, having a large actual (nominal) orifice area (AOA) as provided by manufacturer equivalent to a standard valve one size larger, seemed appropriate to be implanted and evaluated in relatively aged patients with aortic valve stenosis and small aortic root, where other alternatives, such as annulus enlargement, in order to make space for a larger valve prosthesis were not suitable because of the increased operative risk.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Patient population</title><p>The study population consisted of nineteen consecutive patients of mean age 69.2 &#x000b1; 7.3 years (2 men, 17 women), who 36 &#x000b1; 12 months before had received a SJMR-17 mm aortic valve, after sizing the aortic annulus and deciding not to attempt to enlarging it. This cohort represents <bold>7% </bold>of patients (19/265) who underwent aortic valve replacement (AVR) over four years at our Centre. AVR had been performed for rheumatic or degenerative valve disease resulting in severe stenosis. In one patient with degenerative mitral valve disease and moderate-severe valvular regurgitation concomitant valve replacement had been performed and in two patients with significant CAD single coronary artery by-pass grafting. Four patients with degenerative mitral valve disease and less than moderate mitral regurgitation had been treated with AVR alone. All patients but one were in sinus rhythm at the time of the study; none had had a myocardial infarction or angina pectoris after the operation. Demographic data are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. All patients underwent basal echocardiography before cardiac surgery and 1 month after surgery and were controlled every year by clinical examinations. At mean distance of 24 months after surgery patients were enrolled in the study and underwent rest echocardiography and DSE. Beta-blockers were discontinued in all patients 24 hours before the test, whilst patients on ace-inhibitors and calcium antagonists continued their medication. Informed written consent was obtained from all patients.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and Clinical variables.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Variables</td><td align="center">N&#x000b0; (%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Females/males</td><td align="center">17/2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean age (years)</td><td align="center">69.2 &#x000b1; 7.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean Body Surface Area (m2)</td><td align="center">1.68 &#x000b1; 0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean Body Mass Index (Kg/m2)</td><td align="center">24.6 &#x000b1; 7.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetes</td><td align="center">4 (21)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Coronary Artery Disease history</td><td align="center">4 (21)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hypertension</td><td align="center">8 (42)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hypothyroidism</td><td align="center">2 (10.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Smoking history</td><td align="center">5 (26.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Previous Transient Ischemic Attack</td><td align="center">4 (21)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Previous carotid endarterectomy</td><td align="center">1 (5.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peripheral vascular disease</td><td align="center">2 (10.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Atrial fibrillation</td><td align="center">1 (5.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</td><td align="center">4 (21)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean New York Heart Association Functional class</td><td align="center">2.75 &#x000b1; 0.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean Canadian cardiovascular Class</td><td align="center">1.63 &#x000b1; 0.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Left ventricular ejection fraction &#x0003c;35%</td><td align="center">1 (5.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mitral valve disease</td><td align="center">5 (26.3)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Study protocol</title><p>All studies (pre-operative, post-operative and follow-up) were performed with the use of 2.5&#x02013;3.5 MHz transducer interfaced to the SONOS 5500 (Agilent Technologies, Andover, Mass) by same physicians (G.M., C.M., G.P.). The baseline study with standard M-Mode and 2-D measurements was completed according ASE criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] and left ventricular mass (LVM) as well as left ventricular mass index (LVMi) were measured. Dobutamine was then infused intravenously starting at 5 microg/Kg/min and increased by 5 microg/Kg/min at 5 min intervals up to 40 microg/Kg/min. The DSE was terminated if any of the following end-points were met: (1) target heart rate &#x0003e;85% of maximal predicted, (2) angina or progressive dyspnoea, (3) 2-mm ST-segment depression 80 msec after the J point, (4) hypertension (systolic blood pressure &#x0003e;220, diastolic blood pressure &#x0003e;120 mmHg), (5) hypotension (drop in systolic blood pressure &#x0003e;30 mmHg), (6) frequent or polymorphous ventricular ectopic beats, (7) supraventricular tachyarrhythmias. Heart rate (HR) and a 12-lead ECG were recorded continuously; blood pressure, ejection fraction (EF), cardiac output (CO), peak and mean pressure gradients (MxPG, MnPG), effective orifice area (EOA), effective orifice area index (EOAi) as well as Doppler velocity index (DVI) were measured at baseline and at the end of each increment of dobutamine.</p></sec><sec><title>Measurements and calculations</title><p>The MxPG across the prosthesis was estimated by the modified Bernoulli equation (4 V<sup>2</sup>); the MnPG was derived by planimetry of the Doppler envelope. Measurements from at least three velocity envelopes were averaged to assure consistency. The EOA was calculated by the continuity equation: EOA (cm<sup>2</sup>)= CSA LVOT &#x000d7; V LVOT integral/V Transprosthetic integral, where CSA is cross-sectional area, LVOT is left ventricular outflow tract, and V is velocity integral. Assuming a circular shape, the CSA LVOT was calculated as: 3.14 &#x000d7; (D/2)<sup>2</sup>, where D is the inner diameter of the left ventricular outflow tract. The V LVOT was obtained with pulsed-wave Doppler in the left ventricular outflow tract proximal to the aortic prosthesis from the apical five-chamber view; the V Transprosthetic was obtained with continuous-wave Doppler from the apical five-chamber view. The EOAi was calculated by the formula EOA/BSA (body surface area). LVM was derived from Devereux's formula and LVMi from LVM/BSA. The DVI was calculated by the formula: V integral LVOT/V integral transprosthetic (normal value &#x0003e;0.40). The CO was derived from the formula: stroke volume (CSA &#x000d7; V LVOT integral) X HR.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Group statistics were expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD. Paired Student's test was used to measure the variations of the parameters documented between baseline and follow-up. The non-linear relation between mean trans-prosthetic gradients at rest and EOAi was analysed by means of scatterplots and exponential curve estimation regression statistics. All analyses were performed by using SPSS 11.0 statistical software. A p value &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Pre-operative and post-operative echocardiographic data are reported in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. At the time of the study the mean NYHA class was significantly lower than pre-operatively (1.3 &#x000b1; 0.6 vs 2.75 &#x000b1; 0.86, p &#x0003c; 0.001). The basal transprosthetic mean and maximal flow velocities were, respectively, 1.7 &#x000b1; 0.2 and 2.6 &#x000b1; 0.3 m/sec; consequently MnPG and peak MxPG were 16.6 &#x000b1; 5.8 and 29.2 &#x000b1; 7.1 mmHg; EOA and EOAi resulted 1.14 &#x000b1; 0.3 cm<sup>2 </sup>and 0.76 &#x000b1; 0.2 cm<sup>2</sup>/m<sup>2</sup>; DVI was normal (0.50 &#x000b1; 0.1) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). A non-linear relation between mean transprosthetic gradient at rest and EOAi was found, being patients with EOAi &#x0003c;0.85 cm<sup>2</sup>/m<sup>2 </sup>on the steep portion of the curve, where gradients are relatively high (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). LVM and LVMi decreased from pre-operative values of 258 &#x000b1; 43g and 157.4 &#x000b1; 27.7g/m<sup>2</sup> to 191 &#x000b1; 23.8g and 114.5 &#x000b1; 10.6 g/m<sup>2</sup>, respectively (p &#x0003c; 0.00001 and &#x0003c;0.0001) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Individual data regarding a possible link between rest and stress gradients, EOAi and regression of hypertrophy are reported in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>. All patients completed DSE without complications. Four patients had occasional premature atrial and/or ventricular beats, which did not preclude them from completing the test. With dobutamine, HR increased from a baseline of 64.5 &#x000b1; 10 to 100.6 &#x000b1; 28 beats/min (p &#x0003c; 0.001); CO increased from a baseline of 4.7 &#x000b1; 1.6 L/min to 8.2 &#x000b1; 2 L/min (p &#x0003c; 0.0001); EF increased from a baseline of 58.4 &#x000b1; 8% to 68 &#x000b1; 9.9% (p &#x0003c; 0.008). Basal systolic and diastolic blood pressure did not change significantly during test, whilst the double product increased significantly. At peak dobutamine, the mean and maximal flow velocities increased from baseline to 2.9 &#x000b1; 0.4 and 4.5 &#x000b1; 0.5 m/sec., respectively (p &#x0003c; 0.0001 and &#x0003c;0.0001); the MnPG and MxPG increased significantly from baseline, achieving, respectively, 43.2 &#x000b1; 12.7 and 83.4 &#x000b1; 21.9 mmHg (p &#x0003c; 0.0001 and p &#x0003c; 0.0001). EOA, EOAi and DVI changed during the test. At peak dobutamine, these parameters had an insignificant increase, EOA and EOAi from baseline to stress 1.2 &#x000b1; 0.4 cm<sup>2 </sup>and 0.75 &#x000b1; 0.3 cm<sup>2</sup>/m<sup>2 </sup>(p = 0.34 and 0.45) respectively, the DVI from baseline to stress 0.48 &#x000b1; 0.1 (p = 0.72). Changes of all parameters are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>. Two out of the 19 patients developed significant subvalvular or intraventricular gradients during DSE. The mean NYHA class did not change significantly during the test or soon after.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Pre- and post-operative echocardiographic data.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Variables</td><td align="center">before surgery</td><td align="center">after surgery</td><td align="center">p-value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">BSA m2</td><td align="left">1.6 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">LVOT mm</td><td align="left">17.5 &#x000b1; 1.5</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Effective Orifice Area (cm2)</td><td align="left">0.6 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="left">1.1 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Indexed Effective Orifice Area (cm2/m2)</td><td align="left">0.36 &#x000b1; 0.9</td><td align="left">0.7 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Maximal velocity (m/sec)</td><td align="left">4.6 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td align="left">2.7 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean velocity (m/sec)</td><td align="left">3.6 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td align="left">1.8 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Maximal gradient (mmHg)</td><td align="left">88.2 &#x000b1; 20.3</td><td align="left">32.6 &#x000b1; 11.3</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean gradient (mmHg)</td><td align="left">53.5 &#x000b1; 13.6</td><td align="left">16.6 &#x000b1; 5.8</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">VTI LVOT (cm)</td><td align="left">25.5 &#x000b1; 6.9</td><td align="left">27.45 &#x000b1; 9.6</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">VTI transvalvular (cm)</td><td align="left">105.3 &#x000b1; 20.1</td><td align="left">57.2 &#x000b1; 15.79</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Doppler Velocity Index</td><td align="left">0.24 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td align="left">0.47 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Left Ventricular Mass (g)</td><td align="left">258 &#x000b1; 43</td><td align="left">NA</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Indexed Left Ventricular Mass (g/m2)</td><td align="left">157.4 &#x000b1; 27.7</td><td align="left">NA</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Relation between mean transprosthetic gradient at rest and indexed effective orifice area.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1749-8090-1-27-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Pre- and post-operative left ventricular mass index values in individual patients (LVMi pre and post).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1749-8090-1-27-2"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Echocardiographic data at rest and under DSE at follow up.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Variables</td><td align="center">at rest</td><td align="center">under peak stress</td><td align="center">p-value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Effective Orifice Area (cm2)</td><td align="left">1.14 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td align="left">1.2 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Indexed Effective Orifice Area (cm2/m2)</td><td align="left">0.76 &#x000b1; 0.20</td><td align="left">0.75 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Maximal velocity (m/sec)</td><td align="left">2.6 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td align="left">4.5 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean velocity (m/sec)</td><td align="left">1.7 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="left">2.9 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Maximal gradient (mmHg)</td><td align="left">29.2 &#x000b1; 7.1</td><td align="left">83.4 &#x000b1; 21.9</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean gradient (mmHg)</td><td align="left">16.6 &#x000b1; 5.8</td><td align="left">43.2 &#x000b1; 12.7</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Doppler Velocity Index</td><td align="left">0.50 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td align="left">0.48 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">VTI LVOT (cm)</td><td align="left">32.1 &#x000b1; 10.5</td><td align="left">34.2 &#x000b1; 7.7</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">VTI transprosthetic (cm)</td><td align="left">62.8 &#x000b1; 13.7</td><td align="left">72.5 &#x000b1; 17.3</td><td align="center">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction</td><td align="left">58.4 &#x000b1; 8</td><td align="left">68 &#x000b1; 9.9</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cardiac Output (L/min)</td><td align="left">4.7 &#x000b1; 1.6</td><td align="left">8.2 &#x000b1; 2</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heart rate (b/min)</td><td align="left">64.5 &#x000b1; 10</td><td align="left">100.6 &#x000b1; 28</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Systolic pressure (mmHg)</td><td align="left">139 &#x000b1; 23</td><td align="left">152 &#x000b1; 26</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diastolic pressure (mmHg)</td><td align="left">77 &#x000b1; 10.6</td><td align="left">77 &#x000b1; 12.5</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Double Product</td><td align="left">8978 &#x000b1; 2184</td><td align="left">15225 &#x000b1; 5147</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Left Ventricular Mass (g)</td><td align="left">191 &#x000b1; 23.8</td><td align="left">NA</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Indexed Left Ventricular Mass (g/m2)</td><td align="left">114 &#x000b1; 10.6</td><td align="left">NA</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Rest and peak gradients, indexed effective orifice area and regression of left ventricular hypertrophy in individual patients.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Patient</td><td align="center">Rest Max PG (mmHg)</td><td align="center">Rest Mean PG (mmHg)</td><td align="center">Stress Max PG (mmHg)</td><td align="center">Stress Mean PG (mmHg)</td><td align="center">Rest Indexed EOA (cm2/m2)</td><td align="center">Delta LVMi (g/m2)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">29,00</td><td align="center">15,00</td><td align="center">50,00</td><td align="center">23,00</td><td align="center">0,63</td><td align="center">-115</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">16,00</td><td align="center">6,90</td><td align="center">51,00</td><td align="center">22,50</td><td align="center">1,39</td><td align="center">-126</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">35,50</td><td align="center">17,30</td><td align="center">50,00</td><td align="center">28,00</td><td align="center">0,47</td><td align="center">-7</td></tr><tr><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">39,40</td><td align="center">19,10</td><td align="center">48,00</td><td align="center">24,00</td><td align="center">0,54</td><td align="center">-33</td></tr><tr><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">62,70</td><td align="center">31,80</td><td align="center">65,00</td><td align="center">30,00</td><td align="center">0,83</td><td align="center">-50</td></tr><tr><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">14,00</td><td align="center">7,70</td><td align="center">40,00</td><td align="center">21,00</td><td align="center">1,05</td><td align="center">-40</td></tr><tr><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">44,10</td><td align="center">26,30</td><td align="center">58,00</td><td align="center">28,00</td><td align="center">0,65</td><td align="center">8</td></tr><tr><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">29,00</td><td align="center">15,00</td><td align="center">45,00</td><td align="center">22,00</td><td align="center">0,63</td><td align="center">-65</td></tr><tr><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">38,00</td><td align="center">18,00</td><td align="center">45,00</td><td align="center">30,00</td><td align="center">0,61</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">29,00</td><td align="center">14,00</td><td align="center">113,00</td><td align="center">58,00</td><td align="center">0,98</td><td align="center">-17</td></tr><tr><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">35,00</td><td align="center">19,00</td><td align="center">83,00</td><td align="center">44,00</td><td align="center">0,49</td><td align="center">-60</td></tr><tr><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">35,00</td><td align="center">19,00</td><td align="center">72,00</td><td align="center">32,00</td><td align="center">0,62</td><td align="center">-39</td></tr><tr><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">30,00</td><td align="center">15,00</td><td align="center">114,00</td><td align="center">58,00</td><td align="center">0,55</td><td align="center">-18</td></tr><tr><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">42,00</td><td align="center">20,00</td><td align="center">93,00</td><td align="center">39,00</td><td align="center">0,81</td><td align="center">-39</td></tr><tr><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">28,00</td><td align="center">16,00</td><td align="center">65,00</td><td align="center">38,00</td><td align="center">0,84</td><td align="center">-34</td></tr><tr><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">23,00</td><td align="center">11,00</td><td align="center">101,00</td><td align="center">59,00</td><td align="center">0,75</td><td align="center">-28</td></tr><tr><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">25,00</td><td align="center">14,00</td><td align="center">62,00</td><td align="center">33,00</td><td align="center">0,83</td><td align="center">-20</td></tr><tr><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">29,00</td><td align="center">15,00</td><td align="center">73,00</td><td align="center">41,00</td><td align="center">0,48</td><td align="center">-76</td></tr><tr><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">35,00</td><td align="center">17,00</td><td align="center">63,00</td><td align="center">28,00</td><td align="center">0,71</td><td align="center">-21</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>EOA: Effective orifice area; PG: pressure gradient; LVMi: left ventricular mass index</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Two-dimensional and Doppler echocardiography is an accurate, reliable and non invasive tool for assessing prosthetic heart valves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. However, the ideal means for testing valve function requires rest and stress hemodynamic evaluation, under various flow conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Recently, DSE has been proposed as an alternative means for evaluating valve hemodynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. In this study we used basal and dobutamine 2-dimensional and Doppler echocardiography for assessing aortic SJMR-17 mm prostheses, implanted in patients with a small aortic root, the use of which is controversial because of the small orifice area. In our experience SJMR-17 mm prostheses showed rest mean and peak gradients of 16.6 &#x000b1; 5.8 and 29.2 &#x000b1; 7.1 mmHg similar to the gradients reported in literature for SJM standard or HP valves of larger sizes (19&#x02013;21 mm), respectively of 17.2 &#x000b1; 3.3 and 33 &#x000b1; 4 mmHg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], and slightly higher when compared to other larger (21&#x02013;23 mm) bileaflet mechanical valves, respectively of 15 &#x000b1; 2.6 and 27.7 &#x000b1; 4 mmHg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], although there was a large overlap between the values of these variables. When we compared EOA and EOAi of SJMR-17 mm with the reported results of larger (19&#x02013;23 mm) mechanical valves, we found values slightly lower respectively 1.14 &#x000b1; 0.3 cm<sup>2 </sup>vs 1.21 &#x000b1; 0.19 cm<sup>2 </sup>and 0.76 &#x000b1; 0.2 cm<sup>2</sup>/m<sup>2 </sup>vs 0.88 &#x000b1; 0.2 cm<sup>2</sup>/m<sup>2</sup>. The finding of average EOAi &#x0003c; 0.85 cm<sup>2</sup>/m<sup>2 </sup>might suggest that the majority of patients had a mild prosthesis-patient mismatch (PPM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. During DSE mean and peak flow velocity, and mean and peak gradients rose markedly. Similar results were obtained in previous studies which evaluated prosthetic valves of different types and sizes under stress conditions, induced by exercise or dobutamine echocardiography [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. These studies clearly demonstrated a strong, inverse correlation between prosthetic size and basal and stress gradients, namely smaller valves with more elevated mean and peak gradients. Large BSA and young age have also been considered as predictors of unfavorable hemodynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The relation between BSA and gradients is still controversial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. No correlation was found in our study. Young age (&#x0003c;50 years), especially in patients who are physically active, has been reported as predictor of potential PPM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. It has therefore been suggested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] that in patients requiring a 19 mm valve or smaller, prostheses with the largest actual (nominal) orifice area (AOA) as provided by manufacturer, or other types of valve prostheses, i.e. stentless porcine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>], aortic homograft [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] or pulmonary autograft [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] should be considered. As an alternative patients could be subjected to an aortic root enlargement procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. However, the increased operative risk of this procedure must be considered. In our study BSA and age of patients were 1.68 &#x000b1; 0.2 m<sup>2 </sup>and 69.2 &#x000b1; 7.3 years, respectively and SJMR-17 mm prostheses, having an AOA equivalent to a standard valve one size larger, seemed appropriate. Our patients are older than those usually enrolled in published studies, in which the mean age is 62.5 &#x000b1; 5.5 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. The transprosthetic valve gradient depends on the valve type and size, the diastolic filling period, and the ventricular loading conditions. Therefore, it should be noted that high gradients do not necessarily mean prosthetic stenosis. Since the volumetric flow in the outflow tract equals the volumetric flow through the prosthetic valve (Q LVOT=Q prosthesis), the rise in cardiac output generated by DSE increases the flow velocities on the two sides of the valve orifice, maintaining the EOA basically unchanged [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. This principle of conservation of mass was clearly demonstrated in our study when the continuity equation (Q LVOT &#x000d7; A LVOT= Q transprosthetic &#x000d7; A transprosthetic) was applied at baseline and at peak stress: the aortic valve area remained relatively unchanged despite a significant increase in transprosthetic gradients. Such a finding is highly expected as mechanical valves, because of their stiff components, are less prone to accommodating larger stroke volume by increasing their effective area. These results confirm previous data derived from patients with larger size mechanical aortic prosthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], suggesting that a mild-moderate PPM could not always be an issue of clinical relevance[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Some authors have found that PPM leads to higher mortality rates[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], others have found no effects on overall mortality[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>], but its clinical impact probably seems to be related to both severity of LV workload and function, thus suggesting the fact that a diseased ventricle is much more sensitive to increased afterload[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The DVI, which is a further guide to valve orifice behaviour, independent of measurement of LVOT diameter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], has been evaluated only in few studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. In our study it remained substantially unchanged during stress, according to EOA and EOAi. During dobutamine infusion CO, EF, HR and double product increased significantly, confirming published data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p><p>The influence of prosthesis size on change in LVM remains controversial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. Some studies found a strong correlation between prosthetic size and left ventricular hypertrophy (LVH) regression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>], others did not support this finding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. Moreover, other studies found that the degree of mass regression may vary markedly from one patient to another[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. In this series the LVM and LVMi decreased significantly from pre-operative, returning to a normal range. Thus the SJMR-17 mm prosthesis, which increases EOA of the aortic valve and consequently reduces the pressure gradient, probably eliminates one of the factors stimulating LVH. These findings seem to confirm the positive effect of AVR on LVH irrespective of prosthesis size and of mild PPM. Furthermore, the increase in maximal and mean trans-prosthetic gradients during DSE, which mimics stress conditions of patient's daily activities, seems to be without clinical importance in this sample population, represented however by relatively aged patients. Two patients who had isolated AVR developed significant dynamic outflow obstruction during DSE, without clinical symptoms. This phenomenon has been observed in patients with proven or suspected CAD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] (prevalence of 3.8&#x02013;7.5%) or in patients who have undergone concomitant mitral valve repair [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. The suspected mechanisms are: increased myocardial contractility, decreased venous return to the left ventricle, mitral valve systolic anterior motion or peculiar characteristics of left ventricular geometry. This finding was detected in up to 60% of patients with a small aortic prosthesis by Hunziker et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], but has not been confirmed by other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. To our knowledge, this is the first report dealing with patients with 17 mm prosthetic aortic valves. The use of dobutamine as in our protocol was not associated with side effects, confirming previous data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. It would appear that this test can be safely used in relatively aged patients, which represent a growing population requiring aortic valve replacement. An additional advantage of using the "full" protocol is the ability to assess coronary artery disease, by analysis of left ventricle segmental wall motion under stress conditions.</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations of the study</title><p>The small number of patients examined demonstrates the rarity of patients potentially requiring a 17 mm aortic valve prosthesis. In this experience the 17 mm aortic valve prosthesis was implanted in relatively aged patients, older than those usually enrolled in published studies. It is therefore difficult to differentiate the hemodynamic response in younger patients who have a more active life. Methodologically, a major limitation of continuous-wave Doppler is the possibility of overestimating valvular flow velocity and pressure gradients and underestimating the valve area by continuity equation, as a consequence of pressure-recovery phenomenon. Since the rest and dobutamine prosthetic assessment are both subject to the same limitation, the ensuing intra-individual comparison that follows is statistically valid.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In relatively aged patients with a small aortic root, the SJMR-17 mm valves can be implanted, because of their satisfactory hemodynamic profile at rest and under pharmacological stress conditions. Basal and dobutamine echocardiography is a useful and effective means for evaluating prosthesis hemodynamics (gradients, EOA, DVI and indexed values) and for monitoring the expected LVH regression. A standard methodology for studying aortic prostheses in basal conditions, using these echocardiographic paramethers, is warranted.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>GM and FM made substantial contributions to conception and design of the study, analysis and interpretation of data; GM, CM, VC, DM, GP, and GC made substantial contributions in acquisition of clinical, surgical and echocardiographic data; GM and GP performed the statistical analysis; GM, GP and FM have been involved in drafting the manuscript and revising it critically ; FM has given final approval of the version to be published.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to Laura Bussolotti, Luca Guerrieri, Attilia Caroselli, Marina Rotoloni, Alda Lorettu for their skillful nursing assistance.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zabalgoitia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>O'Rourke RA (ed.)</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Echocardiographic assessment of prosthetic heart valves</article-title><source>Current Problems in Cardiology</source><year>1992</year><volume>XVII</volume><publisher-name>C.V. Mosby Company, Littleton, MA</publisher-name><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1499327</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenhek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Normal values for Doppler echocardiographic assessment of heart valve prostheses</article-title><source>J Am Soc Echocardiogr</source><year>2003</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1116</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14608282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/S0894-7317(03)00638-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Paulis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommariva</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tondo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagliaricci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiariello</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Doppler echocardiography evaluation of CarboMedics valve in patients with small aortic annulus and valve prosthesis-body surface area mismatch</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>1994</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8028380</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bednarz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupovitch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abruzzo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Borok</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerber</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Piccione</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoganathan</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of small-diameter aortic mechanical prostheses: physiological relevance of the Doppler gradient, utility of flow augmentation, and limitations of orifice area estimation</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1998</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>866</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9738641</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Carlo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Milano</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mecozzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bortolotti</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serial Doppler echocardiographic evaluation of small-sized Sorin Bicarbon prostheses</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2003</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12928629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5223(02)73395-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van den Brink</surname><given-names>RBA</given-names></name><name><surname>Verheul</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Koelemay</surname><given-names>MJW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunning</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Value of exercise Doppler echocardiography in patients with prosthetic or bioprosthetic cardiac valves</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1734650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0002-9149(92)90235-Q</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiseth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Levang</surname><given-names>OW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tangen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rein</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Skjaerpe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exercise hemodynamics in small (&#x0003c;21 mm) aortic valve prostheses assessed by Doppler echocardiography</article-title><source>Am Heart J;</source><year>1993</year><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izzat</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Birdi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelini</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of hemodynamic performances of St. Jude Medical and CarboMedics 21 mm aortic prostheses by means of dobutamine stress echocardiography</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>1996</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8583814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5223(96)70450-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zabalgoitia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopec</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Oneschuk</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Linn</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Rourke</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of dobutamine stress echocardiography in assessing mechanical aortic prostheses: comparison with exercise echocardiography</article-title><source>J Heart Valve Dis</source><year>1997</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9183723</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liau</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of dobutamine on aortic valve indexes in asymptomatic patients with bileaflet mechanical prostheses in the aortic valve position</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>1546</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9185654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9149(97)00192-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunziker</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Spondlin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hediger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Burckhardt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Buser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term follow-up and dobutamine stress echocardiography of 19-mm prosthetic heart valves</article-title><source>Echocardiography</source><year>1998</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11175091</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsukamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hachiro</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Muraki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional evaluation of the bileaflet mechanical valve in the aortic position using dobutamine stress echocardiography</article-title><source>Jpn Circ J</source><year>1998</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9856597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1253/jcj.62.817</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silberman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaheen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzivoni</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapira</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Strass-Liviatan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitran</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of exercise hemodynamics among nonstented aortic bioprostheses, mechanical valves, and normal native aortic valves</article-title><source>J Card Surg</source><year>1998</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>412</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10440658</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morsy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Usama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elkhashab</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Aziz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hemodynamic performance of stentless porcine bioprosthesis and mechanical bileaflet prosthesis using dobutamine stress echocardiography</article-title><source>Semin Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2001</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11805961</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelini</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of exercise and dobutamine echocardiography in the hemodynamic assessment of small size mechanical aortic valve prostheses</article-title><source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>692</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11932169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1010-7940(02)00071-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahn</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>DeMaria</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kisslo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weyman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recommendations regarding quantification in M-mode echocardiography: results of survey of echocardiographic measurements</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1978</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1072</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">709763</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blais</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumesnil</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Baillot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Simard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pibarot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of valve prosthesis-patients mismatch on short-term mortality after aortic valve replacement</article-title><source>Circulation</source><volume>108</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><comment>2003 Aug 26</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12912812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000085167.67105.32</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taggart</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prosthesis patient mismatch in aortic valve replacement: possible but pertinent?</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2006</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16455673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehi757</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niinami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aomi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomioka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koyanagi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparison of the in vivo performance of the 19-mm St. Jude Hemodynamic Plus and 21-mm standard valve</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2002</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>1120</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12400755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-4975(02)03891-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gelsomino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morocutti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Col</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fasullo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Carella</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Spedicato</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Livi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early in vivo hemodynamic result after aortic valve replacement with the St. Jude Medical Regent mechanical heart valve in patients with pure aortic stenosis</article-title><source>J Card Surg</source><year>2003</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12757339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1540-8191.2003.02003.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yacoub</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepper</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of valve substitute on changes in left ventricular function and hypertrophy after valve replacement</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>1996</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8783993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-4975(96)00438-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Feindel</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Scully</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakowskie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aortic valve replacement with a stentless porcine aortic valve: a six-year experience</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>1994</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>1030</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7983872</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sintek</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Khonsari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Small aortic root in the elderly: use of stentless bioprosthesis</article-title><source>J Heart Valve Dis</source><year>1996</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>S308</fpage><lpage>S313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8953459</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coverdale</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ormiston</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrat Boyes</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Doppler echocardiography in the assessment of the homograft aortic valve</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><year>1989</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>1466</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2729134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0002-9149(89)90009-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hachida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koyanagi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aortic valve replacement in small aortic annulus with or without annular enlargement</article-title><source>J Heart Valve Dis</source><year>1996</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>S289</fpage><lpage>S293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8953456</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pibarot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Landry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chayer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumesnil</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of aortic valve effective orifice area by Doppler echocardiography: effects of valve inflow shape anf flow rate</article-title><source>J Am Soc Echocardiogr</source><year>2004</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>756</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15220901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.echo.2004.03.030</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanayama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Christakis</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallidi</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fremes</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Joyner</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinants of incomplete mass regression following aortic valve replacement for aortic stenosis</article-title><source>J Card Surg</source><year>2005</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15985127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1540-8191.2005.200485.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaudino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alessandrini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Glieca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Luciani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciellini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pragliola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Morelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Canosa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasso</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Possati</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival after aortic valve replacement for aortic stenosis: does left ventricular mass regression have a clinical correlate?</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15615799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehi012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawford</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nihoyannopulous</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Echocardiographic assessment of artificial heart valves: British Society of Echocardiography position paper</article-title><source>Br Heart J</source><year>1994</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8011398</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jazayeri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecarnot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saleh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouchot</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Renaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical experience and Doppler echocardiographic assessment of the first one hundred ATS AP (advanced performance) prosthetic valve in the aortic position</article-title><source>J Heart Valve Dis</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14565717</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaturi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapira</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rotstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Birnbaum</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vered</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of aortic valve replacement on left ventricular mass assessed by echocardiography</article-title><source>Eur J Echocardiogr</source><year>2000</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12086209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/euje.2000.0014</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bech-Hanssen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Caidahl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Myken</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallentin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of aortic valve replacement, prosthesis type, and size on functional outcome and ventricular mass in patients with aortic stenosis</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>1999</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10384185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5223(99)70141-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tasca</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cirillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalla Tomba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mhagna</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Troise</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Quaini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of the improvement of valve area achieved with aortic valve replacement on the regression of left ventricular hypertrophy in patients with pure aortic stenosis</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2005</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>1291</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15797064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2004.09.002</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pellikka</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Monahan</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tajik</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic intraventricular obstruction during dobutamine stress echocardiography: a new observation</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1992</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>1429</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1423956</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>YRCL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Left ventricular geometry and dynamic intracavitary left ventricular obstruction during dobutamine stress echocardiography</article-title><source>Am J Card Imaging</source><year>1996</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scandura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcidiacono</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Felis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbagallo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Deste</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Drago</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Giuffrida</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Left ventricular outflow dynamic obstruction during dobutamine stress echocardiography: the probable mechanisms and clinical implications</article-title><source>Cardiologia</source><year>1998</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9922586</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jebara</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihaileanu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Acar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brizard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grare</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Latremuille</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chauvaud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabiani</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Deloche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpentier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Left ventricular outflow tract ostruction after mitral valve repair. Results of the sliding leaflet technique</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1993</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


