<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8391304</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1968287</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The control of acute cisplatin-induced emesis--a comparative study of granisetron and a combination regimen of high-dose metoclopramide and dexamethasone. Granisetron Study Group.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chevallier</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Service de M&#x000e9;dicine Interne et Chimioth&#x000e9;rapie, Centre Henri Becquerel, Rouen, France.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>1993</year></pub-date><volume>68</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><abstract><p>The anti-emetic efficacy and safety of granisetron, a highly selective and potent 5-HT3 receptor antagonist, was compared with that of high-dose metoclopramide plus dexamethasone in 281 patients due to receive single-day cisplatin chemotherapy (&#x0003e; or = 49 mg m-2). In this single-blind, multicentre study, granisetron (40 micrograms kg-1) was administered as a single prophylactic 5-min infusion. Dexamethasone (12 mg) was administered as a 30-min infusion followed by a loading dose of 3 mg kg-1 metoclopramide. A maintenance dose of metoclopramide 4 mg kg-1 was then infused over 8 h. A single prophylactic dose of granisetron was as effective as the combination regimen in the prevention of cisplatin-induced emesis. Of 143 granisetron-treated patients, 100 (70%) were complete responders (no vomiting and no or only mild nausea) compared with 93/138 (67%) patients who received the comparator regimen. Twenty-three percent of granisetron-treated patients experienced one of more adverse events compared with 33% of patients in the comparator group. No extrapyramidal reactions were reported in the granisetron group compared with 13 in comparator-treated patients (8%). This difference was significant (P &#x0003c; 0.05). The commonest adverse event in the granisetron group, headache (9.8%) described by the majority of patients as mild, was significantly higher than that reported in the comparator group (3% P = 0.02). Granisetron appears to be a safe and effective agent which can be used as a single agent for the prophylaxis of cisplatin-induced emesis. The simplicity of administration, a single 5-min infusion prior to chemotherapy, and the lack of somnolence or extrapyramidal reactions offer clear advantages over the comparator combination regimen.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00197-0186.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="176" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00197-0187.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="177" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00197-0188.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="178" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00197-0189.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="179" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00197-0190.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="180" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

