<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8381298</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1968225</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Colorectal adenomas and diet: a case-control study of subjects participating in the Nottingham faecal occult blood screening programme.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hawtin</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hardcastle</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>I. D.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>SEARCH Programme, Unit of Analytical Epidemiology, International Agency for Research on Cancer, Lyon, France.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>1993</year></pub-date><volume>67</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><abstract><p>Diets high in animal fat and protein and low in fibre and calcium are thought to be factors in the etiology of colorectal cancer. Intakes of these nutrients were determined in three groups participating in a randomised trial of faecal occult blood (FOB) screening. A diet history was obtained by interview from 147 patients with colorectal adenomas, 153 age and sex matched FOB-negative controls (a) and 176 FOB-positive controls without colorectal neoplasia (b). Unconditional logistic regression was used to estimate relative risks (RR) and 95% confidence limits (increases) adjusted for age, sex and social class. After adjustment for total energy intake, no associations were found with total, saturated or mono-unsaturated fat, or calcium intake. For total fibre intake there were non-linear relationships with both control groups with the crude RR for highest quintiles of total fibre intake compared to the lowest being 0.6, although this pattern was no longer apparent after adjustment for energy intake with group (a). In comparison with group (b) cereal fibre intake showed a more consistent inverse relationship with adenoma prevalence with the RR for ascending quintiles of intake being 1.0, 0.7 (0.3-1.6), 0.5 (0.3-1.1), 0.7 (0.4-1.4) and 0.3 (0.1-0.6) (trend chi 2 = 8.80, p = 0.003). In comparison with group (a), the adjusted RR for the highest quintile of cereal fibre intake compared with the lowest was 0.6, but no clear trend was apparent. There was an unexpected positive relationship between adenomas and polyunsaturated fat intake with the RR for having an adenoma being 1.0, 2.8 (1.3-6.1), 1.6 (0.7-3.4), 3.5 (1.6-7.5) and 2.3 (1.1-5.0) for ascending quintiles of polyunsaturated fat intakes (trend chi 2 = 4.8, P = 0.03) in comparison with group (a) only. Our data, while providing no support for the role of dietary animal fat or protein, do support the protective role of dietary cereal fibre in the etiology of colorectal adenomas.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00203-0187.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="177" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00203-0188.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="178" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00203-0189.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="179" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00203-0190.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="180" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00203-0191.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="181" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00203-0192.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="182" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00203-0193.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="183" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00203-0194.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="184" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

