<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Respir Res</journal-id><journal-title>Respiratory Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1465-9921</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1465-993X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16212675</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1277850</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1465-9921-6-113</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1465-9921-6-113</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Asthma and COPD in cystic fibrosis intron-8 5T carriers. A population-based study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>Morten</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>dahlos2003@yahoo.dk</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tybj&#x000e6;rg-Hansen</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>at-h@rh.dk</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>peter.lange@hh.hosp.dk</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nordestgaard</surname><given-names>B&#x000f8;rge G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>brno@herlevhosp.kbhamt.dk</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Clinical Biochemistry, Herlev University Hospital, DK-2730 Herlev, Denmark</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Clinical Biochemistry, Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen University Hospital, DK-2100 Copenhagen &#x000d8;, Denmark</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Hvidovre University Hospital, DK-2650, Hvidovre, Denmark</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>The Copenhagen City Heart Study, Bispebjerg University Hospital, DK-2200 Copenhagen N, Denmark</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://respiratory-research.com/content/6/1/113"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Dahl et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Dahl et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Dahl
               Morten
               
               dahlos2003@yahoo.dk
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Asthma and COPD in cystic fibrosis intron-8 5T carriers. A population-based study
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Respiratory Research 6(1): 113-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1465-9921(2005)6:1&#x0003c;113&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1465-9921</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Carriers of cystic fibrosis intron-8 5T alleles with high exon-9 skipping could have increased annual lung function decline and increased risk for asthma or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>We genotyped 9131 individuals from the adult Danish population for cystic fibrosis 5T, 7T, 9T, and F508del alleles, and examined associations between 11 different genotype combinations, and annual FEV<sub>1 </sub>decline and risk of asthma or COPD.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>5T heterozygotes vs. 7T homozygous controls had no increase in annual FEV<sub>1 </sub>decline, self-reported asthma, spirometry-defined COPD, or incidence of hospitalization from asthma or COPD. In 5T/7T heterozygotes vs. 7T homozygous controls we had 90% power to detect an increase in FEV<sub>1 </sub>decline of 8 ml, an odds ratio for self-reported asthma and spirometry-defined COPD of 1.9 and 1.7, and a hazard ratio for asthma and COPD hospitalization of 1.8 and 1.6, respectively. Both 5T homozygotes identified in the study showed evidence of asthma, while none of four 5T/F508del compound heterozygotes had severe pulmonary disease. 7T/9T individuals had annual decline in FEV<sub>1 </sub>of 19 ml compared with 21 ml in 7T homozygous controls (t-test:P = 0.03). 6.7% of 7T homozygotes without an F508del allele in the <italic>cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator </italic>gene reported asthma vs. 11% of 7T/9T individuals with an F508del allele (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>:P = 0.01) and 40% of 7T homozygotes with an F508del allele (P = 0.04). 7T homozygotes with vs. without an F508del allele also had higher incidence of asthma hospitalization (log-rank:P = 0.003); unadjusted and adjusted equivalent hazard ratios for asthma hospitalization were 11 (95%CI:1.5&#x02013;78) and 6.3 (0.84&#x02013;47) in 7T homozygotes with vs. without an F508del allele.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Polythymidine 5T heterozygosity is not associated with pulmonary dysfunction or disease in the adult Caucasian population. Furthermore, our results support that F508del heterozygosity is associated with increased asthma risk independently of the 5T allele.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) are caused by complex interactions between environmental and genetic factors. A putative genetic risk factor for asthma and COPD is the <italic>cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR) </italic>gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. This gene encodes a cAMP-regulated channel with chloride activity in pulmonary epithelia. When channel activities are absent, cystic fibrosis with life-threatening airways obstruction due to thickened secretions and secondary pulmonary infection develop [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The most common cause of cystic fibrosis is homozygosity for the phenylalanine-508 deletion (F508del), explaining about 70% of cystic fibrosis worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p><p>We previously showed that persons heterozygous for a F508del deletion are overrepresented among people with asthma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Another more common variant, the 5T allele, could likewise be involved in asthma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] or COPD. This variation is in the polythymidine tract of the <italic>CFTR </italic>gene and has mainly been associated with congenital bilateral absence of the vas deferens, a monosymptomatic form of cystic fibrosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. However, it may also be associated with increased risk of obstructive lung disease, particularly bronchiectasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Because most previous studies on lung disease in 5T carriers were based on case patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], currently we know little about the risk for obstructive lung disease in 5T carriers in the general population.</p><p>Three common alleles are known in the polythymidine tract, 5T, 7T, and 9T. The polythymidine tract is situated in intron-8 near the acceptor splice site for exon-9 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. The shorter this polythymidine tract is, the more often exon-9 is skipped from CFTR mRNA. Transcripts missing exon-9 increases from 1%&#x02013;13% in 9T homozygotes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>] to 12%&#x02013;25% in 7T homozygotes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] to 66%&#x02013;90% in 5T homozygotes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. CFTR mRNA without exon-9 leads to a protein with no chloride channel activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Thus, carriers of 5T with high exon-9 skipping have reduced channel activities and could have increased susceptibility for obstructive lung disease. This could be particularly relevant for 5T carriers exposed to additional risk factors for lung disease such as tobacco smoke or familial predisposition to lung disease. Variations in the genes for mannose-binding lectin and &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-antitrypsin have been studied as modifiers of cystic fibrosis lung disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>] and could also potentially influence risk of lung disease in 5T heterozygotes. Allele frequencies in whites are approximately 5% for the 5T allele, 84% for 7T, and 11% for 9T [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>].</p><p>We hypothesised that carriers of the 5T allele have increased annual lung function decline and increased risk for asthma or COPD. To test this hypothesis, we genotyped 9131 individuals from the adult Danish population for the 5T, 7T, and 9T alleles in the <italic>CFTR </italic>gene. We combined polythymidine and F508del genotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], and examined associations between 11 different genotype combinations, and annual FEV<sub>1 </sub>decline and risk of asthma or COPD. We also examined whether other common risk factors for lung disease or variations in the genes for mannose-binding lectin and &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-antitrypsin significantly add to risk of lung disease in 5T carriers.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Subjects participated in the 1976&#x02013;78, 1981&#x02013;83, and/or 1991&#x02013;94 examination of the Copenhagen City Heart Study, a prospective epidemiological study initiated in 1976&#x02013;78 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. Participants aged 20 years and above were selected randomly after age stratification into 5-year age groups from among residents of Copenhagen. Of the 17180 individuals invited, 10135 participated, 9259 gave blood, and 9131 were genotyped for the polythymidine tract variants of the <italic>cystic fibrosis conductance membrane regulator </italic>(<italic>CFTR</italic>) gene. Details of study procedures and some characteristics of non-responders are described elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. More than 99% were Whites of Danish descent. All participants gave written informed consent, and Herlev University Hospital and the ethics committee for Copenhagen and Frederiksberg approved the study (# 100.2039/91).</p><p>Participants filled out a self-administered questionnaire, which was validated by the participant and an investigator on the day of attendance. Participants reported on long-term occupational exposure to dust or welding fumes, pulmonary symptoms (dyspnea, wheezing, bringing up phlegm), familial predisposition to asthma (having at least one sibling with asthma), smoking habits (current smoker, ex-smoker, never-smoker), type of smoking and daily tobacco consumption. An estimate of life-time tobacco exposure (in packyears) was calculated as: daily tobacco consumption (g) times duration of smoking (years) divided by 20 (g/pack). If at least once during the study period participants aswered "Yes" to the question "Do you suffer from asthma?", we recorded they had self-reported asthma. Medication for asthma / bronchitis was "Yes" to the question "Do you daily take medication for asthma / bronchitis?" Additional information on hospitalizations due to asthma (ICD8: 493; ICD10: J45&#x02013;46) and COPD (ICD8: 491&#x02013;492; ICD10: J41&#x02013;44) was drawn from the Danish National Hospital Discharge Register from May 1st 1976 through December 31st 2000. We confirmed in the Danish National Hospital Discharge Register covering all hospital discharges in Denmark, that no participants in the sample were ever hospitalized for cystic fibrosis.</p><p>Forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV<sub>1</sub>) and forced vital capacity (FVC) were measured with an electronic spirometer (model N403, Monaghan, Littleton, Colo.) at the 1976&#x02013;78 and 1981&#x02013;83 examinations and with a dry wedge spirometer (Vitalograph, Maidenhead, UK) at the 1991&#x02013;94 examination. At each examination, three sets of values were obtained, and as a criterion for correct performance of the procedure, at least two measurements of FEV<sub>1 </sub>and FVC differing by less than 5% had to be produced. The highest set of FEV<sub>1 </sub>and FVC were used in the analyses as percentage of predicted value using internally derived reference values based on a subsample of healthy never smokers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Annual decline in FEV<sub>1 </sub>(ml/year) was calculated as FEV<sub>1 </sub>(ml) obtained at the latest measurement minus the FEV<sub>1 </sub>value obtained at the first measurement, times 365.25 divided by the number of days between the two measurements (in years<sup>-1</sup>). Spirometry defined COPD was FEV<sub>1</sub>&#x0003c;80% predicted and FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC&#x0003c;0.7, excluding self-reported asthma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>].</p><p>We amplified the polythymidine tract variants in intron-8 by nested polymerase chain reaction using the primerpairs: 5'-TAATGGATCATGGGCCATGT-3'and 5'-ACAGTGTTGAATGTGGTGCA-3' (first step reaction), and 5'-<underline>CCGCCGC</underline>TGTGTGTGTGTGTGTGTTTTT-3' and 5'GCTTTCTCAAATAATTCCCC-HEX-3' (second step reaction) (mismatch underlined) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Products of 52 bp (5T allele), 53 bp (6T allele), 54 bp (7T allele), and 56 bp (9T allele) were seperated by capillary electrophoresis on an ABI 310 sequenator. Tamra 350 marker was added to samples before analysis, and each analysis ran dummy standard, water control, and positive controls. The F508del allele in the <italic>CFTR </italic>gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], S and Z alleles in the <italic>Serine Protease Inhibitor-A1 </italic>gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>], and B, C, and D alleles in the <italic>Mannose-Binding Lectin-2 </italic>gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>] were identified using polymerase chain reaction followed by restriction enzyme digestion as described. Diagnoses of polythymidine alleles in 5T/F508del genotypes, 5T/5T, 6T/7T, and 69 randomly selected 5T/9T, 7T/9T, 7T/7T, 5T/7T, 9T/9T genotypes were confirmed by sequencing. All 7T/7T F508del genotypes were re-analyzed to confirm their diagnosis, using sequencing (7T/7T) and RFLP-PCR (F508del). The number of TG repeats adjacent to the 5T allele in 5T/F508del and 5T/5T genotypes were determined by sequencing. For each polythymidine allele, expected exon-9 skipping was half the middle value of the ranges of skipping observed in homozygotes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]; expected exon-9 skipping was not estimated in individuals with F508del heterozygosity.</p><p>Linkage disequilibrium between the 9T and F508del alleles was tested by the linkage utility program "EH" <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://linkage.rockefeller.edu"/>, which estimates allele and haplotype frequencies with and without allelic association. The linkage disequilibrium coefficient D was calculated as D = P<sub>22 </sub>- p<sub>2</sub>q<sub>2</sub>, where P<sub>22 </sub>is the observed frequency of the 9T/F508del haplotype, p<sub>2 </sub>is the frequency of the F508del allele in the general population and q<sub>2 </sub>is the population frequency of the 9T allele. The degree of linkage disequilibrium was expressed as D' = D/D<sub>max </sub>&#x000d7; 100%.</p><p>Statistical analysis was performed with SPSS; for power calculations, NCSS-PASS and StatMate were used. P &#x0003c; 0.05 on a two-sided test was considered significant. Pearson's &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>-test or analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used for overall comparisons between several genotypes; Pearson's or Fisher's Exact &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>-test were used for post-hoc two-genotype comparisons. The most common genotype combination in the population, 7T homozygosity without F508del, was used as reference group for statistical comparisons. We evaluated asthma and COPD prevalences between genotypes using unadjusted and adjusted logistic regression with Wald's test as a measure of significance; the adjusted model included gender, age at study entry (deciles), and packyears at study entry (never smokers and deciles). We evaluated asthma and COPD incidences between genotypes using the log-rank test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. Unadjusted and adjusted Cox regression with forced entry examined time to disease by using hazard ratios (relative risks) and 95% confidence intervals; the adjusted model included gender, age at study entry (deciles), tobacco use during follow-up (never smokers and deciles), and FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted at study entry (deciles). We tested possible interactions between the 5T/7T genotype and smoking habits, long-term occupational exposure to dust or welding fumes, familial predisposition to asthma, &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-antitrypsin MS genotype, &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-antitrypsin MZ genotype, or mannose-binding lectin deficiency in predicting FEV<sub>1 </sub>at study entry in ANCOVA models.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Characteristics of participants are given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>; genotypes are ordered according to predicted increased skipping of exon-9 of the <italic>cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator </italic>gene, stratified for presence or absence of F508del heterozygosity. Among the 9,131 participants selected randomly from the Danish general population, 352 (3.9%) were 5T heterozygotes and 249 (2.7%) were F508del heterozygotes. Expected numbers of 5T and F508del heterozygotes according to the Hardy Weinberg equilibrium were 349 and 246, respectively. Allele frequencies did not differ from those predicted by the Hardy Weinberg equilibrium (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>-test for 7T allele: P = 0.84; 9T allele: P = 0.60; 6T allele: P = 0.98; 5T allele: P = 0.42; F508del allele: P = 0.19). The novel intron-8 polythymidine tract variant, the 6T allele [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>], was identified in four individuals. The 9T and F508del alleles were in linkage disequilibrium with a degree of linkage of 98% (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>-test: P &#x0003c; 0.001).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of subjects by intron-8 polythymidine tract and F508del genotype</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Polythymidine</td><td align="center"><italic>9T/9T</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>7T/9T</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>7T/7T</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>6T/7T</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>5T/9T</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>5T/7T</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>5T/5T</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>9T/9T</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>7T/9T</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>7T/7T</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>5T/9T</italic></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Expected exon-9 skipping, %</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">&#x02265;18</td><td align="center">43</td><td align="center">48</td><td align="center">78</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">F508del heterozygosity</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">P-value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Women / Men</td><td align="center">44 / 39</td><td align="center">841 / 699</td><td align="center">3,818 / 3,087</td><td align="center">2 / 2</td><td align="center">22 / 18</td><td align="center">171 / 137</td><td align="center">1 / 1</td><td align="center">13 / 10</td><td align="center">127 / 90</td><td align="center">4 / 1</td><td align="center">2 / 2</td><td align="center">0.99</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Genotype frequency, %</td><td align="center">0.9</td><td align="center">16.9</td><td align="center">75.6</td><td align="center">0.0</td><td align="center">0.4</td><td align="center">3.4</td><td align="center">0.0</td><td align="center">0.3</td><td align="center">2.4</td><td align="center">0.1</td><td align="center">0.0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Smoking before study entry, packyears*</td><td align="center">16 &#x000b1; 2.1</td><td align="center">16 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td align="center">15 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="center">13 &#x000b1; 10</td><td align="center">18 &#x000b1; 3.0</td><td align="center">14 &#x000b1; 1.1</td><td align="center">8.4 &#x000b1; 12</td><td align="center">13 &#x000b1; 4.0</td><td align="center">14 &#x000b1; 1.3</td><td align="center">18 &#x000b1; 10</td><td align="center">14 &#x000b1; 10</td><td align="center">0.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age at study entry, years</td><td align="center">46 &#x000b1; 1.4</td><td align="center">47 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td align="center">47 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="center">46 &#x000b1; 6.3</td><td align="center">47 &#x000b1; 2.0</td><td align="center">46 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td align="center">39 &#x000b1; 8.9</td><td align="center">48 &#x000b1; 2.6</td><td align="center">48 &#x000b1; 0.9</td><td align="center">41 &#x000b1; 5.6</td><td align="center">46 &#x000b1; 6.3</td><td align="center">0.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FEV<sub>1 </sub>at study entry, %pred.</td><td align="center">87 &#x000b1; 1.9</td><td align="center">90 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td align="center">90 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="center">83 &#x000b1; 8.8</td><td align="center">96 &#x000b1; 2.8</td><td align="center">90 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td align="center">84 &#x000b1; 12</td><td align="center">94 &#x000b1; 3.7</td><td align="center">89 &#x000b1; 1.2</td><td align="center">84 &#x000b1; 7.9</td><td align="center">101 &#x000b1; 8.8</td><td align="center">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Smoking during follow-up, g/day<sup>&#x02020;</sup></td><td align="center">9.0 &#x000b1; 1.1</td><td align="center">8.8 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td align="center">8.9 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td align="center">11 &#x000b1; 5.0</td><td align="center">8.1 &#x000b1; 1.6</td><td align="center">7.5 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td align="center">6.3 &#x000b1; 7.1</td><td align="center">7.9 &#x000b1; 2.1</td><td align="center">7.1 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td align="center">8.0 &#x000b1; 4.5</td><td align="center">8.0 &#x000b1; 5.0</td><td align="center">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Follow-up, years</td><td align="center">23 &#x000b1; 0.14</td><td align="center">23 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="center">23 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="center">23 &#x000b1; 0.66</td><td align="center">23 &#x000b1; 0.21</td><td align="center">23 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="center">24 &#x000b1; 0.93</td><td align="center">23 &#x000b1; 0.27</td><td align="center">23 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td align="center">24 &#x000b1; 0.59</td><td align="center">24 &#x000b1; 0.66</td><td align="center">0.97</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are number of individuals, percentages, or mean &#x000b1; SD. P-values by Pearson's &#x003c7;<sup>2 </sup>test or analysis of variance. *Calculated as daily tobacco use (g/day) &#x000d7; duration of smoking (years) / 20 (g/pack). <sup>&#x02020;</sup>The average amount of tobacco used (in g/day) at the different examinations attended.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec><title>Annual decline in FEV<sub>1</sub></title><p>Annual decline in FEV<sub>1 </sub>did not differ between 5T heterozygotes or homozygotes vs. 7T homozygous controls (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). 7T/9T individuals had annual decline in FEV<sub>1 </sub>of 19 ml compared with 21 ml in 7T homozygous controls (t-test: P = 0.03; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). None of the other genotype combinations differed from 7T homozygous controls. The analysis had 90% power to detect differences in annual FEV<sub>1 </sub>decline of 14 ml in 9T/9T, 3.8 ml in 7T/9T, 61 ml in 6T/7T, 23 ml in 5T/9T, 8 ml in 5T/7T, 31 ml in 9T/9T F508del, 9 ml in 7T/9T F508del, 72 ml in 7T/7T F508del, and 72 ml in 5T/9T F508del individuals vs. 7T homozygous controls.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Annual FEV<sub>1 </sub>decline by intron-8 polythymidine tract and F508del genotype. </bold>Values are mean and SEM. *P = 0.03 compared with 7T homozygotes without F508del.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1465-9921-6-113-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Asthma</title><p>Prevalence of self-reported asthma did not differ between 5T heterozygotes or homozygotes vs. 7T homozygous controls (Ps &#x02265; 0.10; data not depicted). However, self-reported asthma differed between genotypes overall (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>: P = 0.02); eleven percent of 7T/9T individuals with F508del (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>: P = 0.01) and 40% of 7T homozygotes with F508del (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>: P = 0.04) had asthma vs. 6.7% of 7T homozygous controls (data not depicted). None of the other genotype combinations differed from 7T homozygous controls.</p><p>Unadjusted odds ratios for self-reported asthma were 1.7 (95%CI:1.1&#x02013;2.7) in 7T/9T individuals with F508del and 9.2 (1.5&#x02013;55) in 7T homozygotes with F508del vs. 7T homozygous controls (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, upper panel). After adjusting for gender, age at study entry, and packyears at study entry, equivalent odds ratios for self-reported asthma were 1.7 (1.0&#x02013;27) in 7T/9T individuals with F508del and 27 (2.2&#x02013;327) in 7T homozygotes with F508del (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, lower panel). The analysis had 90% power to detect an odds ratio for asthma of 3.0 for 9T/9T, 1.4 for 7T/9T, 23 for 6T/7T, 4.2 for 5T/9T, 1.9 for 5T/7T, 5.8 for 9T/9T F508del, 2.1 for 7T/9T F508del, 18 for 7T/7T F508del, and 23 for 5T/9T F508del individuals vs. 7T homozygous controls.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Odds ratios for self-reported asthma by intron-8 polythymidine tract and F508del genotype. </bold>7T homozygotes without F508del was used as reference group. The adjusted model included gender, age at study entry, and packyears at study entry. Error bars are 95% confidence intervals. Self-reported asthma = "Yes" at least once during the study period to the question "Do you suffer from asthma?".</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1465-9921-6-113-2"/></fig><p>Incidence of hospitalization from asthma during 24 years follow-up did not differ between 5T heterozygotes or homozygotes versus 7T homozygous controls (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). However, incidence of asthma hospitalization was increased in 7T homozygotes with F508del compared with 7T homozygous controls (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Unadjusted and after adjusting for gender, age at study entry, tobacco consumption, and FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted at study entry, the hazard ratio for asthma hospitalization was 11 (1.5&#x02013;78) and 6.3 (0.84&#x02013;47) in 7T homozygotes with F508del vs. 7T homozygous controls. None of the other genotype combinations differed from 7T homozygous controls (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The analysis had 90% power to detect a hazard ratio for asthma hospitalization of 2.7 for 9T/9T, 1.4 for 7T/9T, 15 for 6T/7T, 3.7 for 5T/9T, 1.8 for 5T/7T, 4.9 for 9T/9T F508del, 2.0 for 7T/9T F508del, 13 for 7T/7T F508del, and 15 for 5T/9T F508del individuals vs. 7T homozygous controls.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Incidences and hazard ratios for asthma hospitalisation by intron-8 polythymidine tract and F508del genotype during 24 years follow-up</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Poly-T</td><td align="center">Expected exon-9 skipping, %</td><td align="center">F508del heterozygosity</td><td align="center">n</td><td align="center">Incidence n/10000 person-years</td><td align="center">P-value*</td><td align="center">Unadjusted HR (95%CI)</td><td align="center">Adjusted<sup>&#x02020; </sup>HR (95%CI)</td><td align="center">90% power<sup>&#x02021; </sup>HR</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>9T/9T</italic></td><td align="center">7</td><td></td><td align="center">83</td><td align="center">9.8</td><td align="center">0.83</td><td align="center">1.2 (0.28&#x02013;4.7)</td><td align="center">1.1 (0.27&#x02013;4.4)</td><td align="center">2.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>7T/9T</italic></td><td align="center">13</td><td></td><td align="center">1540</td><td align="center">9.3</td><td align="center">0.60</td><td align="center">1.1 (0.76&#x02013;1.6)</td><td align="center">1.1 (0.77&#x02013;1.6)</td><td align="center">1.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>7T/7T</italic></td><td align="center">18</td><td></td><td align="center">6905</td><td align="center">8.4</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1.0</td><td align="center">1.0</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>6T/7T</italic></td><td align="center">&#x02265;18</td><td></td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0.77</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>5T/9T</italic></td><td align="center">43</td><td></td><td align="center">40</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">0.85</td><td align="center">1.2 (0.17&#x02013;8.6)</td><td align="center">1.2 (0.17&#x02013;8.9)</td><td align="center">3.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>5T/7T</italic></td><td align="center">48</td><td></td><td align="center">308</td><td align="center">5.3</td><td align="center">0.35</td><td align="center">0.63 (0.23&#x02013;1.7)</td><td align="center">0.53 (0.17&#x02013;1.7)</td><td align="center">1.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>5T/5T</italic></td><td align="center">78</td><td></td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0.84</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">25</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>9T/9T</italic></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">23</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0.49</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">4.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>7T/9T</italic></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">217</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">0.47</td><td align="center">1.3 (0.59&#x02013;3.1)</td><td align="center">1.3 (0.55&#x02013;2.9)</td><td align="center">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>7T/7T</italic></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">87</td><td align="center">0.003</td><td align="center">11 (1.5&#x02013;78)</td><td align="center">6.3 (0.84&#x02013;47)</td><td align="center">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>5T/9T</italic></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0.77</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">15</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*P-values are for the comparison with 7T/7T individuals without the F508del deletion by log-rank test. <sup>&#x02020;</sup>Cox regression adjusted for gender, age at study entry, tobacco use during follow-up, and FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted at study entry. <sup>&#x02021;</sup>90% power to detect a hazard ratio (HR) of asthma at 2-sided P &#x0003c; 0.05. 95%CI = 95% confidence interval. Hospitalizations from asthma (ICD8: 493; ICD10: J45&#x02013;46) were drawn from the Danish National Discharge Register from 1976 through 2000.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)</title><p>Prevalence of spirometry defined COPD did not differ between 5T heterozygotes or homozygotes vs. 7T homozygous controls (Ps &#x02265; 0.22) and did not differ between genotypes overall (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>: P = 0.51) (data not depicted). Unadjusted and adjusted odds ratios for spirometry defined COPD did not differ between genotypes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The analysis had 90% power to detect an odds ratio for COPD of 2.5 for 9T/9T, 1.3 for 7T/9T, 19 for 6T/7T, 3.4 for 5T/9T, 1.7 for 5T/7T, 4.6 for 9T/9T F508del, 1.8 for 7T/9T F508del, 15 for 7T/7T F508del, and 19 for 5T/9T F508del individuals vs. 7T homozygous controls.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Odds ratios for spirometry defined COPD by intron-8 polythymidine tract and F508del genotype. </bold>7T homozygotes without F508del was used as reference group. The adjusted model included gender, age at study entry, and packyears at study entry. Error bars are 95% confidence intervals. COPD = FEV<sub>1</sub>&#x0003c;80% predicted and FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC&#x0003c;0.7, excluding self-reported asthma.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1465-9921-6-113-3"/></fig><p>Incidence of hospitalization from COPD during 24 years follow-up was reduced in 5T/7T individuals vs. 7T homozygous controls (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Unadjusted and after adjusting for gender, age at study entry, tobacco consumption and FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted at study entry, the hazard ratio for COPD was 0.47 (0.23&#x02013;0.95) and 0.49 (0.23&#x02013;1.0) in 5T/7T individuals vs. 7T homozygous controls (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). There was a trend toward increased incidence of COPD hospitalization in 6T/7T individuals; unadjusted and adjusted hazard ratio for COPD hospitalization was 4.9 (0.69&#x02013;35) and 7.6 (1.0&#x02013;55) in 6T/7T individuals vs. 7T homozygous controls (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Other genotypes did not differ in COPD risk from 7T homozygous controls. The analysis had 90% power to detect a hazard ratio for COPD of 2.3 for 9T/9T, 1.3 for 7T/9T, 11 for 6T/7T, 3.0 for 5T/9T, 1.6 for 5T/7T, 3.8 for 9T/9T F508del, 1.7 for 7T/9T F508del, 9.7 for 7T/7T F508del, and 11 for 5T/9T F508del individuals vs. 7T homozygous controls.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Incidences and hazard ratios for COPD hospitalisation by intron-8 polythymidine tract and F508del genotype during 24 years follow-up</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Poly-T</td><td align="center">Expected exon-9 skipping, %</td><td align="center">F508del heterozygosity</td><td align="center">n</td><td align="center">Incidence n/10000 person-years</td><td align="center">P-value*</td><td align="center">Unadjusted HR (95%CI)</td><td align="center">Adjusted<sup>&#x02020; </sup>HR (95%CI)</td><td align="center">90% power<sup>&#x02021; </sup>HR</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>9T/9T</italic></td><td align="center">7</td><td></td><td align="center">83</td><td align="center">40</td><td align="center">0.10</td><td align="center">1.8 (0.89&#x02013;3.6)</td><td align="center">1.7 (0.85&#x02013;3.5)</td><td align="center">2.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>7T/9T</italic></td><td align="center">13</td><td></td><td align="center">1540</td><td align="center">21</td><td align="center">0.70</td><td align="center">0.95 (0.75&#x02013;1.2)</td><td align="center">0.99 (0.78&#x02013;1.3)</td><td align="center">1.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>7T/7T</italic></td><td align="center">18</td><td></td><td align="center">6905</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1.0</td><td align="center">1.0</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>6T/7T</italic></td><td align="center">&#x02265;18</td><td></td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">105</td><td align="center">0.08</td><td align="center">4.9 (0.69&#x02013;35)</td><td align="center">7.6 (1.0&#x02013;55)</td><td align="center">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>5T/9T</italic></td><td align="center">43</td><td></td><td align="center">40</td><td align="center">21</td><td align="center">0.90</td><td align="center">0.92 (0.23&#x02013;3.7)</td><td align="center">0.75 (0.19&#x02013;3.0)</td><td align="center">3.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>5T/7T</italic></td><td align="center">48</td><td></td><td align="center">308</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">0.47 (0.23&#x02013;0.95)</td><td align="center">0.49 (0.23&#x02013;1.0)</td><td align="center">1.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>5T/5T</italic></td><td align="center">78</td><td></td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0.73</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>9T/9T</italic></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">23</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0.25</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">3.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>7T/9T</italic></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">217</td><td align="center">25</td><td align="center">0.73</td><td align="center">1.1 (0.63&#x02013;1.9)</td><td align="center">1.1 (0.62&#x02013;1.9)</td><td align="center">1.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>7T/7T</italic></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0.59</td><td></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">9.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>5T/9T</italic></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0.63</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">11</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*P-values are for the comparison with 7T/7T individuals without the F508del deletion by log-rank test. <sup>&#x02020;</sup>Cox regression adjusted for gender, age at study entry, tobacco use during follow-up, and FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted at study entry. <sup>&#x02021;</sup>90% power to detect a hazard ratio (HR) of COPD at 2-sided P &#x0003c; 0.05. 95%CI = 95% confidence interval. Hospitalizations from COPD (ICD8: 491&#x02013;492; ICD10: J41&#x02013;44) were drawn from the Danish National Discharge Register from 1976 through 2000.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>5T homozygotes and 5T/F508del compound heterozygotes</title><p>One of two 5T homozygous smokers reported having asthma and took daily medication for respiratory disease (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). The other homozygous individual showed evidence of airway obstruction with reversibility and was referred for further examination and treatment of asthma. None of four 5T/F508del compound heterozygotes had clinical signs of severe pulmonary disease (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Pulmonary status of 5T homozygotes and 5T/F508del compound heterozygotes sampled from the general population</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Poly-T*</td><td align="center">F508del heterozygosity</td><td align="center">Age</td><td align="center">Gender</td><td align="center">Smoking status</td><td align="center" colspan="2">FEV<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">Self-reported asthma<sup>&#x02021;</sup></td><td align="center">Medication for asthma / bronchitis<sup>&#x000b6;</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="2">Hospitalization</td><td align="center" colspan="3">Often bothered by</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td><td colspan="2"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td><td colspan="2"><hr></hr></td><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="center">years</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">%predicted</td><td align="center">reversibility<sup>&#x02020;</sup></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">asthma**</td><td align="center">COPD**</td><td align="center">dyspnoea</td><td align="center">wheezing</td><td align="center">phlegm</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>TG12-5T/TG12-5T</italic></td><td></td><td align="center">32</td><td align="center">M</td><td align="center">current smoker</td><td align="center">92</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">no</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>TG11-5T/TG11-5T</italic></td><td></td><td align="center">62</td><td align="center">F</td><td align="center">current smoker</td><td align="center">67</td><td align="center">30%</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>TG11-5T</italic></td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">33</td><td align="center">F</td><td align="center">current smoker</td><td align="center">115</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>TG11-5T</italic></td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">62</td><td align="center">M</td><td align="center">never smoker</td><td align="center">121</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>TG12-5T</italic></td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">65</td><td align="center">F</td><td align="center">ex-smoker</td><td align="center">79</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>TG11-5T</italic></td><td align="center">yes</td><td align="center">70</td><td align="center">M</td><td align="center">current smoker</td><td align="center">128</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td><td align="center">no</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Number of TG repeats adjacent to the polythymidine tract included. <sup>&#x02020;</sup>FEV<sub>1 </sub>30 minutes after inhalation of 0.5 mg terbutaline minus FEV<sub>1 </sub>at 0 minutes divided by FEV<sub>1 </sub>at 0 minutes times 100%; only individuals with FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC&#x0003c;0.7 were tested for FEV<sub>1 </sub>reversibility. <sup>&#x02021;</sup>"Yes" to "Do you suffer from asthma?" <sup>&#x000b6;</sup>"Yes" to "Do you daily take medication for asthma / bronchitis?" **Hospitalizations from asthma (ICD8: 493; ICD10: J45&#x02013;46) and COPD (ICD8: 491&#x02013;492; ICD10: J41&#x02013;J44) were drawn from the Danish National Discharge Register from 1976 through 2000.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Context-dependent associations for 5T/7T genotype</title><p>There was no interaction between 5T/7T genotype and smoking status (P = 0.78), occupational exposure to dust or welding fumes (P = 0.10), familial asthma (P = 0.37), &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-antitrypsin MS genotype (P = 0.64), &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-antitrypsin MZ genotype (P = 0.47), or mannose-binding lectin deficiency (P = 0.73) in predicting FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted at study entry.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>This study shows that polythymidine 5T heterozygosity is not associated with increased annual decline in FEV<sub>1 </sub>or risk of asthma or COPD in the adult Caucasian population; these results are independent of age, gender, tobacco smoking, and other potential confounders. Interestingly, however, both 5T homozygotes showed evidence of asthma. Furthermore, our results support that F508del heterozygosity is associated with increased asthma risk independently of the 5T allele.</p><p>Because 1 in 26 carries a 5T allele in this population, it is indeed important that 5T heterozygosity does not increase risk of obstructive lung disease in the population at-large. It appears that the 5T allele causes lung disease only in very rare circumstances [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], leaving the average heterozygous individual unaffected by obstructive lung disease. Previous results suggest that penetrance of pulmonary manifestations in 5T carriers might depend on the length of an adjacent TG repeat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. This could be particularly relevant for 5T homozygotes and compound heterozygotes. In 5T heterozygotes, however, longer TG repeats seem less likely to affect risk of pulmonary disease. This is because 5T heterozygosity was not associated with risk of lung disease in this study although predicted TG12 and TG13 allele frequency in 5T carriers in our population was 31% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. Other additional genetic variations have also been shown to influence exon-9 skipping in 5T carriers, but to a lesser degree than the TG repeat.</p><p>Because all 5T/F508del compound heterozygotes were free from severe pulmonary disease, the 5T allele did not appear to explain our previous results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] suggesting that F508del heterozygosity may be overrepresented among asthmatics. A few recent studies also support this observation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], while others have found no [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] or negative associations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. In the present analyses, 7T/9T and 7T/7T individuals with F508del heterozygosity had higher prevalences of self-reported asthma, and 7T/7T individuals with F508del heterozygosity also had higher incidence of hospitalization from asthma. F508del heterozygosity was only associated with increased asthma risk in individuals without the 5T allele, indicating that our previous observations are independent of influence from this allele. In addition, both 5T homozygotes showed evidence of asthma supporting the hypothesis that CFTR variations may be associated with asthma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p><p>To identify factors in the population that significantly add to risk of lung disease in 5T heterozygotes, we tested for interactions between 5T/7T genotype and potential risk factors for lung disease, but found no significant interactions. Garred [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] and coworkers found a worse prognosis in cystic fibrosis patients with MBL deficiency. We were not able to extend this finding, since lung function in 5T or F508del heterozygotes was not reduced by MBL deficiency. Previous studies by Mahadeva [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] and Frangolias [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>] showed that pulmonary disease severity in cystic fibrosis patients were unaffected by &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-antitrypsin S and Z alleles. In line with this, we also observed no increased risk for pulmonary dysfunction in 5T carriers with &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-antitrypsin MS or MZ genotypes.</p><p>In the present study, bias caused by investigators' knowledge of disease or risk-factor status seems unlikely, because we selected from a general population and genotyped our sample without knowledge of disease status or lung function test results. Selection bias is possible if severe lung disease in some individuals with 5T genotypes prevented them from participating in our study; however, expected and observed numbers of these genotypes according to the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium were similar. The 2.7% frequency of F508del heterozygosity found in this study is in accordance with the 2.9% frequency of F508del heterozygosity observed in another previous study of the Danish population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. Annual decline in FEV<sub>1 </sub>was reduced in 7T/9T individuals and incidence of COPD hospitalization was reduced in 5T/7T individuals. If correction for multiple comparisons was performed, these significant findings become nonsignificant. Therefore, and because reduced COPD risk in 5T/7T individuals is less biologically plausible, the findings are likely due to chance alone rather than representing real phenomena. Misclassification of genotypes is unlikely, because diagnoses were confirmed by sequencing a subsample of different poly-T variants.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Polythymidine 5T heterozygosity was not associated with increased annual decline in FEV<sub>1 </sub>or risk of asthma or COPD in adults in this population-based study; however, both 5T homozygotes showed evidence of asthma. Furthermore, our results also support that F508del heterozygosity may be associated with increased asthma risk independently of the 5T allele.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>Morten Dahl, Anne Tybj&#x000e6;rg-Hansen, and B&#x000f8;rge G. Nordestgaard carried out the genotyping and statistical analysis. Peter Lange helped collect the data and was involved in the statistical analysis. All investigators participated in designing the study and in writing the paper, and all authors read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Birgit Hertz, Hanne Damm and Nina D. Kjersgaard for expert technical assistance. The Danish Heart Foundation and the Danish Lung Association supported this study.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tybj&#x000e6;rg-Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordestgaard</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x00394;F508 heterozygosity in cystic fibrosis and susceptibility to asthma</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1998</year><volume>351</volume><fpage>1911</fpage><lpage>1913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9654257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(97)11419-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzetis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Efthymiadou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Strofalis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Psychou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimakou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pouliou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>CFTR gene mutations &#x02013; including three novel nucleotide substitutions &#x02013; and haplotype background in patients with asthma, disseminated brochiectasis and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Hum Genet</source><year>2001</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11354633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004390100467</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffjan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolae</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ober</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association studies for asthma and atopic diseases: a comprehensive review of the literature</article-title><source>Resp Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1465-9921-4-14</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New concepts of the pathogenesis of cystic fibrosis lung disease</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2004</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14738247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.03.00057003</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The Cystic Fibrosis Genetic Analysis Consortium</collab></person-group><article-title>Worldwide survey of the &#x00394;F508 mutation &#x02013; report from the cystic fibrosis genetic analysis consortium</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>1990</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2378364</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordestgaard</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tybj&#x000e6;rg-Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fifteen-year follow-up of pulmonary function in individuals heterozygous for the cystic fibrosis phenylalanine-508 deletion</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2001</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>818</fpage><lpage>823</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11344348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mai.2001.114117</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griesenbach</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Geddes</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alton</surname><given-names>EWFW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pathogenic consequences of a single mutated CFTR gene</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>1999</year><volume>54</volume><issue>suppl 2</issue><fpage>S19</fpage><lpage>S23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10451687</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chill&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Casals</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lissens</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Silber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Mutations in the cystic fibrosis gene in patients with congenital absence of the vas deferens</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>332</volume><fpage>1475</fpage><lpage>1480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7739684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199506013322204</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pignatti</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bombieri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Benetazzo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Casartelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trabetti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>CFTR gene variant IVS8-5T in disseminated bronchiectasis</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>889</fpage><lpage>892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8644755</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rave-Harel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Augarten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Madgar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nissim-Rafinia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahav</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>A cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator splice variant with partial penetrance associated with variable cystic fibrosis presentations</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>1997</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>1914</fpage><lpage>1920</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9196095</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bombieri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Benetazzo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saccomani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Belpinati</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Luisetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Complete mutational screening of the CFTR gene in 120 patients with pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Hum Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>718</fpage><lpage>722</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9921909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004390050897</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castellani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonizzato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pradal</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Filicori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Foresta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>La Sala</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Evidence of mild respiratory disease in men with congenital absence of the vas deferens</article-title><source>Respir Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10653048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0954-6111(99)90052-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noone</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pue</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakeling</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganeshananthan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Lung disease associated with the IVS8 5T allele of the CFTR gene</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>1919</fpage><lpage>1924</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11069835</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noone</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>'CFTR-opathies': disease phenotypes associated with cystic fibrosis transmembrane regulator gene mutations</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11737931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/rr82</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrieux</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Audr&#x000e9;zet</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Frachon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Roge</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Scotet</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Quantification of CFTR splice variants in adults with disseminated bronchiectasis, using the TaqMan flourogenic detection system</article-title><source>Clin Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12123489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1399-0004.2002.620108.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Namkung</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanrahan</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>A haplotype-based molecular analysis of CFTR mutations associated with respiratory and pancreatic diseases</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2321</fpage><lpage>2332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12952861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddg243</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casals</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>De-Gracia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallego</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorca</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Sanch&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Bronchiectasis in adult patients: an expression of heterozygosity for CFTR gene mutations?</article-title><source>Clin Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>490</fpage><lpage>495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15151509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0009-9163.2004.00265.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Freezer</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Holdsworth</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Forshaw</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sart</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of CFTR mutations in adult bronchiectasis</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2004</year><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15047968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2003.020263</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e1;zaro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>de Cid</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Missense mutations in the cystic fibrosis gene in adult patients with asthma</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><year>1999</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10571949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1098-1004(199912)14:6&#x0003c;510::AID-HUMU10&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-O</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Cid</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chomel</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazaro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baudis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Casals</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>CFTR and asthma in the French EGEA study</article-title><source>Eur J Hum Genet</source><year>2001</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11175304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.ejhg.5200578</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castellani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinzii</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Altieri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mastella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Assael</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A pilot survey of cystic fibrosis clinical manifestations in CFTR mutation heterozygotes</article-title><source>Genet Test</source><year>2001</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11788092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/10906570152742317</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Verellen-Dumoulin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mairesse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Delaunois</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Brancaleone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahier</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Frequency of cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator gene mutations and 5T allele in patients with allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2001</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>762</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11243954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.119.3.762</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cutting</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator gene mutations: do they play a role in the aetiology of allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis?</article-title><source>Clin Exp Allergy</source><year>2002</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>756</fpage><lpage>761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11994102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2222.2002.01361.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid characterization of the variable length polythymidine tract in the cystic fibrosis (CFTR) gene: association of the 5T allele with selected CFTR mutations and its incidence in atypical sinopulmonary disease</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><year>1997</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9259194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1098-1004(1997)10:2&#x0003c;108::AID-HUMU3&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-G</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiesewetter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Macek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Curristin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>A mutation in CFTR produces different phenotypes depending on chromosomal background</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1993</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7506096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1193-274</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuppens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Raeymaekers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>De Boeck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassiman</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CFTR haplotype backgrounds on normal and mutant CFTR genes</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>1994</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7520797</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Curristin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cutting</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Crystal</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic basis of variable exon 9 skipping in cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator mRNA</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1993</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7684646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng0293-151</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorissen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Poppel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Legius</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassiman</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuppens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased proportion of exon 9 alternatively spliced CFTR transcripts in vas deferens compared with nasal epithelial cells</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9002674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/6.1.85</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larriba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Testicular CFTR splice variants in patients with congenital absence of the vas deferens</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1739</fpage><lpage>1744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9736775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/7.11.1739</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvi</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zielenski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Durie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Higher proportion of intact exon 9 CFTR mRNA in nasal epithelium compared with vas deferens</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2099</fpage><lpage>2107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9328474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/6.12.2099</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rave-Havel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nissim-Rafinia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Madjar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Goshen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Augarten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>The molecular basis of partial penetrance of splicing mutations in cystic fibrosis</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8981951</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Huxley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Skipping of exon 9 of human CFTR in YAC-transgenic mice</article-title><source>Genomics</source><year>2001</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11597137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/geno.2001.6630</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hargrave</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovelock</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator splice variants are not conserved and fail to produce chloride channels</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1993</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7691356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng0893-426</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansoura</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Devor</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Henze</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Expression of an abundant alternatively spliced form of the cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR) gene is not associated with a cAMP-activated chloride conductance</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>1993</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7684641</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garred</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pressler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name><surname>Frederiksen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Svejgaard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f8;iby</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Association of mannose-binding lectin gene heterogeneity with severity of lung disease and survival in cystic fibrosis</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>1999</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10449435</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahadeva</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Westerbeek</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovegrove</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehouse</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Alpha1-antitrypsin deficiency alleles and the TaqI GA allele in cystic fibrosis lung disease</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>1998</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>873</fpage><lpage>879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9623690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.98.11040873</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frangolias</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>LTK</given-names></name><name><surname>Berthiaume</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Alpha1-antitrypsin deficiency alleles in cystic fibrosis lung disease</article-title><source>Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12689922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1165/rcmb.2002-0271OC</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnohr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Scharling</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Appleyard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Copenhagen City Heart Study &#x02013; &#x000d8;sterbrounders&#x000f8;gelsen. Tables with data from the third examination 1991&#x02013;1994</article-title><source>Eur Heart J Suppl</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><issue>H</issue><fpage>H1</fpage><lpage>H83</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of chest pain and angina pectoris, with special reference to treatment needs</article-title><source>Acta Med Scand Suppl</source><year>1984</year><volume>682</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6587759</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyboe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnohr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Appleyard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ventilatory function impairment and risk of cardiovascular death and of fatal or non-fatal myocardial infarction</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>1991</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1080</fpage><lpage>1087</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1756841</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><article-title>British Thoracic Society guidelines for the management of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>1997</year><volume>52</volume><issue>suppl 5</issue><fpage>S1</fpage><lpage>S28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9474238</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tybj&#x000e6;rg-Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vestbo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordestgaard</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Change in lung function and morbidity from chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-antitrypsin MZ heterozygotes: a longitudinal study of the general population</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11848724</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tybj&#x000e6;rg-Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnohr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordestgaard</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A population-based study of morbidity and mortality in mannose-binding lectin deficiency</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>199</volume><fpage>1391</fpage><lpage>1399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15148337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20040111</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bojesen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tybj&#x000e6;rg-Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordestgaard</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrin &#x003b2;<sub>3 </sub>Leu33Pro homozygosity and risk of cancer</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2003</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1150</fpage><lpage>1157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12902444</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Georges</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Claustres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bienvenu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel length variant of the polypyrimidine tract within the splice acceptor site in intron 8 of the CFTR gene: consequences for genetic testing using standard assays</article-title><source>Eur J Hum Genet</source><year>2004</year><comment></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15340362</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuppens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaspers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Costes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vankeerberghen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Polyvariant mutant cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator genes. The polymorphic (Tg)m locus explains the partial penetrance of the T5 polymorphism as a disease mutation</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>1998</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9435322</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hefferon</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Casals</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Estivill</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Georges</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Variation in a repeat sequence determines whether a common variant of the cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator gene is pathogenic or benign</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14685937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/381001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aznarez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Zielenski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Siminovitch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased frequency of CFTR mutations and variants among asthma patients</article-title><source>Pediatr Pulmonol</source><year>1999</year><issue>suppl 19</issue><fpage>208</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10213261</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mennie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilfillan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>DJH</given-names></name><name><surname>Liston</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heterozygotes for the delta F508 cystic fibrosis allelele are not protected against bronchial asthma</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>978</fpage><lpage>979</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7489375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm1095-978b</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaughan</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Swift</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protection against brochial asthma by CFTR delta F508 mutation: a heterozygote advantage in cystic fibrosis</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7585155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm0795-703</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schi&#x000f8;tz</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of cystic fibrosis in Denmark. Implications for genetic counseling, carrier diagnosis and prenatal diagnosis</article-title><source>Acta Paediatr</source><year>1992</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>522</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1392366</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


