<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7505104</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1968653</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A randomised trial of three or six courses of etoposide cyclophosphamide methotrexate and vincristine or six courses of etoposide and ifosfamide in small cell lung cancer (SCLC). II: Quality of life. Medical Research Council Lung Cancer Working Party.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bleehen</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Girling</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Machin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>1993</year></pub-date><volume>68</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1157</fpage><lpage>1166</lpage><abstract><p>A total of 458 eligible patients, from 21 centres, with microscopically confirmed SCLC were allocated at random to three chemotherapy regimens, each given at 3-week intervals. In two regimens, etoposide, cyclophosphamide, methotrexate and vincristine were given for a total of either three courses (ECMV3) or six courses (ECMV6). In the third regimen, etoposide and ifosfamide were given for six courses (E16). Patients with limited disease also received radiotherapy to the primary site after the third course of chemotherapy in all three groups. As reported by clinicians, 59% of the ECMV3, 67% of the ECMV6 and 63% of the EI6 patients experienced moderate or severe adverse reactions to their chemotherapy. The major symptoms of disease, cough, haemoptysis, chest pain, anorexia, and dysphagia, were palliated in 63% or more of patients and the median duration of palliation was 63% or more of survival, the results being similar in the three groups. Among patients with poor overall condition, physical activity and breathlessness on admission, the proportions who improved were higher in the EI6 group but the differences were small. In all three groups, levels of anxiety fell substantially during treatment. Levels of depression were lower and showed little change. As assessed by patients using a daily diary card, the patterns of nausea, vomiting, activity and mood, associated with courses of chemotherapy were very similar in the three groups. In the EI6 group there was less dysphagia and better overall condition between courses, but these advantages need to be weighed against the inconvenience of the 24-h infusions required, compared with the 30-min infusions of the other two regimens. As reported in the companion paper (MRC Lung Cancer Working Party, 1993a) there was no statistically significant survival advantage to any of the three regimens, although the results do not exclude the possibility of a minor survival advantage with the two six-course regimens. In conclusion, there was no major clinical gain from continuing chemotherapy beyond three courses or from using the ifosfamide regimen.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0113.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1157" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0114.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1158" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0115.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1159" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0116.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1160" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0117.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1161" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0118.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1162" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0119.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1163" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0120.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1164" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0121.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1165" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00202-0122.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1166" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

