<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Dis Obstet Gynecol</journal-id><journal-title>Infectious Diseases in Obstetrics and Gynecology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1064-7449</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1098-0997</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9894177</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1784814</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1098-0997(1998)6:5&#x0003c;220::AID-IDOG6&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-G</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Incidence of postpartum endomyometritis following single-dose antibiotic prophylaxis with either ampicillin/sulbactam, cefazolin, or cefotetan in high-risk cesarean section patients.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Noyes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berkeley</surname><given-names>A S</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ledger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>New York University Medical Center, New York 10016, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><abstract><p>OBJECTIVE: To assess the efficacy of single-dose antibiotic prophylaxis against postpartum endomyometritis in high-risk cesarean section patients. DESIGN: Patients were administered one of three single-dose antibiotic regimens following umbilical cord clamping after cesarean section delivery. SETTING: Prospective randomized trial at a university-based hospital. PATIENTS: The study evaluated 293 consenting women undergoing cesarean section who had either experienced labor for a duration of &#x0003e; or = 6 hr or rupture of amniotic membranes. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES: Development of postpartum endomyometritis. RESULTS: The incidence of postpartum endomyometritis was 7/95 (7.4%) following the ampicillin/sulbactam regimen, 14/98 (14.3%) after the cefazolin regimen, and 11/99 (11.1%) after the cefotetan regimen. There was no significant difference in postpartum infection among the three study arms. In addition, the incidence of endomyometritis in the three single-dose study arms was not higher than previously noted in studies where three doses of antibiotic were administered. CONCLUSION: Single-dose antibiotic prophylaxis should replace the standard triple-dose therapy for uninfected women undergoing cesarean section who are at risk for postoperative endomyometritis. Ampicillin/sulbactam, cefazolin, and cefotetan are all reasonable antibiotic choices for single-dose therapy.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

