<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10339452</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1566563</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">sc271_5_1835</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cytogenetic effects from exposure to mixed pesticides and the influence from genetic susceptibility.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Au</surname><given-names>W W</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sierra-Torres</surname><given-names>C H</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cajas-Salazar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shipp</surname><given-names>B K</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Legator</surname><given-names>M S</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Preventive Medicine and Community Health, The University of Texas Medical Branch, Galveston, Texas 77555-1110, USA. william.au@utmb.edu</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>1999</year></pub-date><volume>107</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><abstract><p>Exposure to pesticides remains a major environmental health problem. Health risk from such exposure needs to be more precisely understood. We conducted three different cytogenetic assays to elucidate the biological effects of exposure to mixed pesticides in 20 Costa Rica farmers (all nonsmokers) compared with 20 matched controls. The farmers were also exposed to dibromochloropropane during the early employment years, and most of them experienced sterility/fertility problems. Our data show that the farmers had consistently higher frequencies of chromosome aberrations, as determined by the standard chromosome aberration assay, and significantly abnormal DNA repair responses (p &#x0003c; 0.05), as determined by the challenge assay, but no statistically significant differences in the tandem-probe fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) assay (p &#x0003e; 0.05). Genotype analysis indicates that farmers with certain "unfavorable" versions of polymorphic metabolizing genes (cytochrome P4502E1, the glutathione S-transferases mu and theta, and the paraoxonase genes) had significantly more biological effects, as determined by all three cytogenetic assays, than both the farmers with the "favorable" alleles and the matched controls. A unique observation is that, in individuals who had inherited any of the mentioned "unfavorable" alleles, farmers were consistently underrepresented. In conclusion, the Costa Rican farmers were exposed to genotoxic agents, most likely pesticides, which expressed the induction of biological and adverse health effects. The farmers who had inherited "unfavorable" metabolizing alleles were more susceptible to genotoxic effects than those with "favorable" alleles. Our genotype data suggest that the well-recognized "healthy worker effect" may be influenced by unrecognized occupational selection pressure against genetically susceptible individuals.</p><sec sec-type="scanned-figures"><title>Images</title><fig id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><graphic xlink:href="envhper00511-0120-a" xlink:role="504"/></fig></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="envhper00511-0117.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="501" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00511-0118.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="502" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00511-0119.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="503" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00511-0120.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="504" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00511-0121.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="505" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

