<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9432970</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1533009</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessment of water use for estimating exposure to tap water contaminants.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shimokura</surname><given-names>G H</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Savitz</surname><given-names>D A</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Symanski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Epidemiology, School of Public Health, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, NC 27599, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>106</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><abstract><p>Epidemiological studies examining the association between exposure to tap water contaminants (such as chlorination by-products) and disease outcomes (such as cancer and adverse reproductive outcomes) have been limited by inaccurate exposure assessment. Failure to take into account the variation in beverage and tap water consumption and exposure to volatile contaminants through inhalation and dermal absorption can introduce misclassification in assessing the association between exposure to tap water contaminants and health. To refine exposure assessment of tap water contaminants, we describe in detail the tap water consumption, showering, and bathing habits of pregnant women and their male partners as assessed by a questionnaire and a 3-day water diary. We found good agreement between questionnaire and 3-day water diary values for drinking water intake (Pearson's r = 0.78) and for time spent showering(r = 0.68) and bathing (r = 0.78). Half of the participants consumed tap water on a regular basis with an overall mean +/- 1 standard deviation (SD) of 0. 78 +/- 0.51 l/day. Our results further suggest that full-time employees, compared to women working part-time or less, have more heterogeneous consumption patterns over time. Seventy-nine percent of women and 94% of men took showers for an average of 11.6 +/-4.0 min and 10.4 +/- 4.8 min, respectively. Baths were taken more frequently by women than men (21% vs. 3%) for an average of 22.9 +/-10.1 min and 21.3 +/- 12.4 min, respectively. Thus, these patterns of tap water use should be considered in the design and interpretation of environmental epidemiology studies.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0045.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="55" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0046.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="56" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0047.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="57" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0048.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="58" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00525-0049.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="59" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

