<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8431368</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1968159</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Phase I trial with pharmacokinetics of CB10-277 given by 24 hours continuous infusion.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gumbrell</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jenns</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Calvert</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Institute of Cancer Research, Sutton, Surrey, UK.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>1993</year></pub-date><volume>67</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><abstract><p>The dose limiting toxicities of the short infusion trial of the dacarbazine analog, CB10-277, were nausea and vomiting which appeared to be related to the peak plasma level of the parent drug. In addition, based on mouse studies, these dose limiting toxicities occurred at a less than optimal level of the monomethyl metabolite, the presumed species required for antitumour activity. An alternative schedule that would avoid the parent drug peak plasma levels of short infusion, while possibly allowing an increase in the amount of monomethyl metabolite produced was considered. Thus, a 24 h continuous infusion schedule, repeated every 21 days was explored. Twenty-two patients received 42 courses with a dose range of 4,700-15,000 mg m-2. The dose limiting toxicity was myelosuppression (leucopenia and thrombocytopenia). Although nausea and vomiting also occurred, it was manageable with routine antiemetic therapy. Other toxicities included diarrhoea, hallucinations, malaise, muscle ache, headache and flushing and all were &#x0003c; or = WHO grade 2. Pharmacokinetic studies were performed with 13 courses which included all dose levels. The mean t1/2 of the parent drug was 178 min. Area under the concentration x time curve (AUC) at the highest dose for the parent drug and the monomethyl metabolite were 2,350 and 9 mM x minutes, respectively. This monomethyl metabolite AUC and the associated myelosuppression showed a more favourable comparison to the preclinical data determined in mice than the results from the short infusion trial of CB10-277. Therefore, the recommended Phase II dose and schedule of this drug was 12,000 mg m-2 given by 24 h continuous infusion.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00204-0167.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="369" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00204-0168.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="370" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00204-0169.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="371" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00204-0170.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="372" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00204-0171.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="373" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

