<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9417767</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1532938</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of chronic exposure to low doses of trichloroethylene on steroid hormone and insulin levels in normal men.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>V H</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>S E</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>C N</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Family Medicine, National University of Singapore, Singapore, Republic of Singapore.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>106</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><abstract><p>The aim of this study was to examine the serum levels of insulin and some adrenal steroid hormones in men chronically exposed to low doses of trichloroethylene (TCE). A total of 85 workers participated in this study. Each worker had urine collected and analyzed for trichloroacetic acids (UTCA) on the same day that a blood sample was taken for analyses of serum testosterone, sex hormone-binding globulin (SHBG), androstenedione, cortisol, aldosterone, and insulin. The mean concentration of environmental TCE was 29.6 ppm and the mean UTCA was 22.4 mg/g creatinine (range 0.8-136.4). TCE exposure did not cause any significant changes to the adrenal steroid hormone productions. The results showed that UTCA was significantly correlated to serum insulin levels. Insulin and SHBG responded in tandem, with the highest levels found in workers exposed to TCE for less than 2 years; levels of both parameters were significantly lowered in those exposed for more than 2 years. A triphasic response in insulin levels to TCE, which depended on the duration of exposure, was noted. Initial exposure caused an acute rise in insulin levels. This was followed by a fall to normal levels in those exposed 2-4 years and then a slight rise in those exposed for more than 6 years. The mechanism for this pattern of response to TCE exposure is yet unknown.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="envhper00524-0067.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="41" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00524-0068.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="42" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00524-0069.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="43" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00524-0070.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="44" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

