<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Dis Obstet Gynecol</journal-id><journal-title>Infectious Diseases in Obstetrics and Gynecology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1064-7449</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1098-0997</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10968597</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1784682</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Use of methergine for the prevention of postoperative endometritis in non-elective cesarean section patients.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dweck</surname><given-names>M F</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>C M</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Spellacy</surname><given-names>W N</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of South Florida College of Medicine, Tampa 33606, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2000</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>3-4</issue><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><abstract><p>OBJECTIVE: Methergine increases constriction of uterine musculature which may facilitate sloughing of endometrial debris, close uterine vessels, and prevent post-cesarean endometritis. The objective of this study was to evaluate the efficacy of methergine in preventing endometritis in patients undergoing non-elective cesarean section delivery. METHODS: Eighty patients undergoing non-elective cesarean section were enrolled in a prospective randomized clinical trial of methergine (41) versus no methergine (39) administration during the postpartum period. The hospital records were abstracted after discharge to compare the postpartum course. RESULTS: There were no significant demographic differences between the two groups. The women receiving methergine had a significant reduction in the rate of postoperative endometritis (10% vs. 36%, P &#x0003c; 0.005). In addition, the mean postoperative hemoglobin was significantly higher in the methergine treated group (P &#x0003c; 0.001). CONCLUSIONS: The use of methergine postpartum in women undergoing non-elective cesarean sections significantly reduces the incidence of postoperative endometritis and blood loss.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

