<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mediators Inflamm</journal-id><journal-title>Mediators of Inflammation</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0962-9351</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">14760933</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1781624</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Influence of ionic and non-ionic radiographic contrast media on leukocyte adhesion molecules.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vermeiren</surname><given-names>Guy L J</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>Roel</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Claeys</surname><given-names>Marc J</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vrints</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Slegers</surname><given-names>Herman</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jorens</surname><given-names>Philippe G</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Intensive Care, University Hospital of Antwerp, Wilrijkstraat 10, B 2650 Edegem, Belgium.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><abstract><p>BACKGROUND: Many papers have focused on the importance of granulocytes in the process of reperfusion and ischemia. Most of the clinical studies measured several parameters of this process during and after coronary angiography, without taking into account the effect of the radiographic contrast media (RCM) used during this procedure. MATERIALS AND METHODS: We performed a randomized patient study (n = 37) to evaluate the effect of ionic and non-ionic RCM on granulocyte adhesion during coronary angiography. We also evaluated the influence of the ionicity and osmolarity of the different substances on granulocyte adhesion molecules in in vitro experiments. RESULTS: The osmolarity of patient serum samples increased from 302 +/- 1 to 309 +/- 1 mOsm/kg (p &#x0003c; 0.05) after infusion of RCM. The CD11b expression in the samples of the non-ionic RCM treated group increased from 221 +/- 21 MFI to 377 +/- 30 MFI (p &#x0003c; 0.05) measured as the absolute mean fluorescence intensity (MFI), yet did not alter significantly in the ionic RCM group. In contrast, the in vitro experiments showed a reduction of the CD11b expression from 360 +/- 70 MFI to 149 +/- 30 MFI (p &#x0003c; 0.05) in the ionic RCM group. CONCLUSIONS: The upregulation of adhesion molecules was significantly reduced in vivo with ionic RCM, while ionic substances caused opposite effects in vitro. This effect should be taken into account when performing leukocyte functional analysis of samples taken during angiography.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

