<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><!-- Original-type: oa--><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">12966414</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2376956</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6601214</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjc.6601214</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Irinotecan plus leucovorin-modulated 5-fluorouracil I.V. bolus every other week may be a suitable therapeutic option also for elderly patients with metastatic colorectal carcinoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Comella</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Farris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lorusso</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Palmeri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maiorino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lucia</surname><given-names>L De</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buzzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mancarella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vita</surname><given-names>F De</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gambardella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">10</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><sup>1</sup>Division of Medical Oncology, National Tumour Institute, Via M. Semmola, 80131 Naples, Italy</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><sup>2</sup>Chair of Medical Oncology, University School of Medicine, Viale S. Pietro 8, 07100 Sassari, Italy</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><sup>3</sup>Department of Medical Oncology, Oncology Institute, Via G. Amendola 209, 70126 Bari, Italy</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><sup>4</sup>Chair of Medical Oncology, University School of Medicine, P.za delle Cliniche 2, 90127&#x02009;Palermo, Italy</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><sup>5</sup>Medical Oncology, San Gennaro Hospital, Via S. Gennaro dei Poveri 5, 80131 Naples, Italy</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><sup>6</sup>Medical Oncology, City Hospital, Via G. Tescione 81, 81100 Caserta, Italy</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><sup>7</sup>Medical Oncology, City Hospital, Via T. Joannuccio, 05100 Terni, Italy</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label><sup>8</sup>Medical Oncology, City Hospital, Via Taranto, 73021 Campi Salentino (Lecce), Italy</aff><aff id="aff9"><label>9</label><sup>9</sup>Chair of Medical Oncology, Second University School of Medicine, Via S. Pansini, 80131 Naples, Italy</aff><aff id="aff10"><label>10</label><sup>10</sup>Chair of Geriatrics, Second University School of Medicine, Via S. Pansini, 80131 Naples, Italy</aff><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>Author for correspondence: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:pasqualecomella@libero.it">pasqualecomella@libero.it</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>09</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>09</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><volume>89</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>992</fpage><lpage>996</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2002</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>03</day><month>06</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>06</month><year>2003</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright 2003, Cancer Research UK</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2003</copyright-year><permissions><copyright-holder>Cancer Research UK</copyright-holder></permissions><kwd-group><kwd>colorectal carcinoma</kwd><kwd>elderly patients</kwd><kwd>combination chemotherapy</kwd><kwd>Irinotecan</kwd><kwd>5-fluorouracil</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Colorectal carcinoma is among the most common cancers in western countries. In Italy, about 40 new cases per 100&#x02009;000 males, and 20 new cases per 100&#x02009;000 females are diagnosed each year (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib31">Zanetti <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>). Most of these cases are discovered in patients aged 65 years or more.</p><p>In recent years, the postsurgical administration of 5-fluorouracil (FU)-based chemotherapy in high-risk (Dukes' stage C) colon cancer patients has been proven to reduce the recurrence and death rate (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib32">Wolmark <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>). On the contrary, there is still no agreement about the absolute benefit that could be obtained in patients with more limited (Dukes' stage B) extension (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib14">International Multicenter Pooled Analysis of B2 Colon Cancer Trials, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib18">Mamounas <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>). Anyway, recently published retrospective studies and meta-analyses have reported no interaction between age of patients and effect of adjuvant chemotherapy, suggesting that elderly patients should also be offered such treatments (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib26">Sargent <italic>et al</italic>, 2001a</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib28">Sundararajan <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>).</p><p>Until recently, the usual management for the recurrent or metastatic disease included leucovorin (LV)-modulated FU chemotherapy (LV-FU), given in a 5-day monthly or in a once-a-week schedule (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib2">Buroker <italic>et al</italic>, 1994</xref>). These two regimens produced equivalent results, and a meta-analysis has shown that this palliative treatment was associated with a 35&#x00025; reduction in the risk of death as compared with supportive care alone, which translated in an improvement in median survival of 3.7 months (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib4">Colorectal Cancer Collaborative Group, 2000</xref>). Also in this case, no age-related difference was found as to the effectiveness of chemotherapy (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib3">Chiara <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib21">Popescu <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>).</p><p>Despite this observation, the number of elderly patients receiving palliative chemotherapy for colorectal carcinoma is still limited (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib13">Hutchins <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>). Indeed, there is still a diffuse concern about the compliance and tolerability of chemotherapy in such patients (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib8">Daniele <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>). On the other hand, some investigators have already stressed that performance status, and associated morbidities, more than age of patients, may adversely affect their outcome (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib11">Extermann <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib29">Yancik <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>).</p><p>Recently, novel drugs such as irinotecan or oxaliplatin have shown activity in this disease when used either alone or in combination with FU. Addition of irinotecan to LV-FU has been proven to increase significantly the response rate, the time to progression, and the median survival of patients, in comparison with LV-FU alone (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib10">Douillard <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">Saltz <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>). Also, oxaliplatin combined with LV-FU has demonstrated to increase significantly the response rate and the time to progression, but not the survival, in comparison with the same regimen without oxaliplatin (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib9">de Gramont <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>). Therefore, irinotecan plus LV and FU is now considered the gold standard of treatment for metastatic patients. However, because no prospective analysis has been carried out on the tolerability of these new combinations in aged people, a special care has been recommended, in consideration of the early and unpredictable adverse events that may occur in older individuals (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib24">Rothemberg <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib27">Sargent <italic>et al</italic>, 2001b</xref>).</p><p>In recent years, the Southern Italy Cooperative Oncology Group (SICOG) has devised an original biweekly regimen, including irinotecan plus LV-modulated FU given as i.v. bolus (IRIFAFU) for metastatic colon cancer patients (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib5">Comella <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>). The IRIFAFU combination has been compared in a randomised multicentre study (SICOG trial 9801) with FU modulated by methotrexate and LV. In that trial, the IRIFAFU regimen produced a greater response rate, and a longer time to progression, than the control treatment (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib6">Comella <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>). Here we report the results of a retrospective analysis we have carried out on the patients randomly allocated to receive the combination regimen, with the aim of having a deeper insight on the interaction between age of patients, their tolerability to chemotherapy, and outcome.</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>PATIENTS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Patient population</title><p>Patients affected by metastatic colorectal cancer, enrolled into the SICOG trial 9801, and randomly allocated to receive the IRIFAFU regimen (experimental arm), were the object of this retrospective analysis. Briefly, eligibility criteria for SICOG trial 9801 were: histologically proven adenocarcinoma of the colon or rectum; presence of bidimensionally measurable lesion(s); age &#x02a7e;18 years; performance status &#x02a7d;2 of the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) scale; adequate liver, renal, and bone marrow reserve. Patients previously treated with FU-based adjuvant chemotherapy were also included, provided that at least 6 months had elapsed from treatment discontinuation.</p></sec><sec><title>Treatment</title><p>Patients in the experimental arm received the IRIFAFU regimen: irinotecan 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> given i.v. over 1-h on day 1, and <sc>L</sc>-leucovorin 250&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> given as 1-h i.v. infusion, followed by FU 850&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> as i.v. bolus, on day 2. Cycles were repeated every other week until progression, or for a maximum of 6 months. Attending physicians were required to specify the reason for an earlier treatment discontinuation. Disease status was checked every 2 months, and classified according to the World Health Organization (WHO) criteria (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib19">Miller <italic>et al</italic>, 1981</xref>). Adverse events of each treatment cycle were scored according to WHO scale (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib19">Miller <italic>et al</italic>, 1981</xref>), and the worst grade for each patient during treatment was recorded. Haematological toxicity was checked weekly. The actual dose intensity of cytotoxic drugs over 4 and 8 cycles (DI<sub>4</sub> and DI<sub>8</sub>, respectively) was calculated as previously reported. Patients were followed every 2 months for assessing tumour progression and survival, and the cause of death (disease- or treatment-related, or due to other reasons) was recorded.</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of safety and activity</title><p>According to their age, patients were divided into three groups: younger (&#x02a7d;54 years), middle-aged (55&#x02013;69 years), and elderly (&#x02a7e;70 years). Differences in distribution of pretreatment characteristics among the three groups were assessed by the <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> test. Comparison of treatment in the three age groups (i.e., number of cycles, duration of therapy, and dose intensities) was made by the Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis test. The difference in reasons for going off-study was assessed for significance by the Pearson <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup>-test. For exploring the interaction between pretreatment characteristics and treatment activity, patients achieving a complete or partial response were classified as &#x02018;responders&#x02019;, while patients showing a stable or progressive disease, as well as those not assessed for response, were classified as &#x02018;failures&#x02019; according to intent-to-treat analysis. The following characteristics were explored for correlation with activity: age, sex, primary site, previous radical surgery, previous adjuvant chemotherapy, time to occurrence of metastatic disease, performance status, presence of symptoms, significant loss of body weight, number of disease sites, and basal carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) serum level. For statistical analysis, the following variables were coded as dichotomous: primary site (colon or rectum), performance status (0 or &#x02a7e;1), timing of metastasis (synchronous or metachronous), number of disease sites (1 or &#x02a7e;2), and CEA basal value (&#x0003c;100 or &#x02a7e;100&#x02009;ng&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>).</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of outcome</title><p>Progression-free survival (PFS) was calculated for each patient from the date of registration to the date of documented tumour progression, or death. Patients who discontinued the treatment early because of toxicity, refusal, or reason other than progression, were considered as censored at that time interval. Overall survival (OS) time was calculated for all patients from the date of registration to the date of death for any cause, or to patients last follow-up. Survival curves were generated by actuarial method (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib15">Kaplan and Meier, 1958</xref>), and compared by the log-rank test (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib20">Peto <italic>et al</italic>, 1977</xref>).</p><p>A logistic regression analysis was performed to identify the interaction between probability of response and pretreatment characteristics, while the Cox multivariate analysis (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib7">Cox, 1972</xref>) was carried out to assess their effect on time to progression and survival.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Patients and treatment</title><p>Patient main characteristics are listed in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Main patient characteristics according to age grouping</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="4" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Age groups (years)</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Characteristics</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>&#x02a7d;54 <italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;37</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>55&#x02013;69 <italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;64</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>&#x02a7e;70 <italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;17</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Total <italic>N</italic>&#x0003d;118</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Median age in years (range)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">48 (28&#x02013;54)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">64 (55&#x02013;69)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">68 (65&#x02013;79)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">62 (28&#x02013;79)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Males</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">41</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Females</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">23</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">23</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">49</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Primary</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colon or recto&#x02013;sigmoid</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">27</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">48</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">88</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Rectum</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">16</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">30</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Previous surgery</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">17</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">32</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">53</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">16</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">101</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Previous adjuvant CT</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">26</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">89</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">29</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Synchronous metastasis</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">28</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">19</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">36</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">63</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Performance status</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;0</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">38</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">70</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">24</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">44</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Presence of symptoms</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">43</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">76</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">17</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">21</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">42</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Weight loss &#x02a7e;5</italic>&#x00025;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">28</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">53</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">93</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">25</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>No. disease sites</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">36</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">66</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;&#x0003e;1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">17</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">28</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">52</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Liver involvement</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">34</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">84</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Single</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">16</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;&#x0003c;25&#x00025;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">23</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">39</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;&#x0003e;25&#x00025;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">29</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Lung involvement</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">31</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">49</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">93</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">25</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>CEA basal value</italic> &#x02a7e;100</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">24</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">42</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">85a</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">22</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">20a</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote1"><label/><p><sup>a</sup>No available basal values in 13 patients.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>, according to age grouping. An imbalance in gender distribution was observed, given that elderly patients were more likely to be male (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.004). Other baseline characteristics were well matched across the three groups.</p><p>Younger patients stayed somewhat longer on treatment, while a similar length of treatment (and number of cycles) was administered to middle-aged or elderly patients (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Duration of treatment, number of delivered cycles, and reason for discontinuation of therapy according to age grouping</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Age groups (years)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>&#x02a7d;54 <italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;37</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>55&#x02013;69 <italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;64</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>&#x02a7e;70 <italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;17</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Stay on treatment (weeks)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Median</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">24</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>P</italic><sup>a</sup>&#x0003d;0.091</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Range</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x02013;42</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x02013;45</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x02013;35</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Administered cycles</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Median</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>P</italic><sup>a</sup>&#x0003d;0.045</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Range</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x02013;16</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1&#x02013;20</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1&#x02013;12</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Reasons for treatment discontinuation:</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;As for protocol</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">32</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">40</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Toxicity</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Refusal</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>P</italic><sup>b</sup>&#x0003d;0.016</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Disease complications</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Death</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Physician's decision</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote2"><label>a</label><p>Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis test.</p></fn><fn id="tbfnote3"><label>b</label><p>Pearson's <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>). Analysis of reasons for treatment discontinuation revealed that younger patients were less likely to refuse chemotherapy as compared to the middle-aged or elderly ones (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.016), while other causes were evenly distributed among the three groups.</p><p>A greater (although not statistically significant) proportion of elderly patients (35&#x00025;) had a dose reduction along the first four cycles, in comparison with the middle-aged (25&#x00025;), and younger patients (19&#x00025;). In addition, a &#x0003e;2-week delay during the administration of the first four cycles was applied in 40&#x00025; of elderly, in 25&#x00025; of middle-aged, and in 26&#x00025; of younger patients. During the four subsequent cycles, such a delay was applied in 62&#x00025; of elderly, in 64&#x00025; of middle-aged, and in 65&#x00025; of younger patients. As a consequence, the median DI<sub>4</sub> of cytotoxic drugs was slightly lower for elderly patients, but DI<sub>8</sub> was substantially comparable in all groups (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Absolute dose intensity (mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>&#x02009;week<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) over the first four (DI4) and eight (DI<sub>8</sub>) cycles according to age grouping</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="4" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Age&#x02013;groups (years)</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Dose intensity</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>&#x02a7d;54 <italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;37</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>55&#x02013;69 <italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;64</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>&#x02a7e;70 <italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;17</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold><italic>P</italic><sup>a</sup></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">DI<sub>4</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;IRI</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;&#x02003;Median</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">86</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">82</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">66</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.230</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;&#x02003;Range</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">55&#x02013;100</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">52&#x02013;100</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">41&#x02013;100</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">5FU</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;&#x02003;Median</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">366</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">361</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">270</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.131</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;&#x02003;Range</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">231&#x02013;425</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">249&#x02013;458</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">175&#x02013;426</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">DI<sub>8</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;IRI</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;&#x02003;Median</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">85</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">75</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">81</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.532</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;&#x02003;Range</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">58&#x02013;98</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">50&#x02013;100</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">50&#x02013;100</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">5FU</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;&#x02003;Median</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">366</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">322</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">345</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.449</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;&#x02003;Range</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">230&#x02013;410</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">230&#x02013;41</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">209&#x02013;425</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote4"><label>a</label><p>Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>).</p><p>After discontinuation of study treatment, 55 patients (47&#x00025; of the whole series) received second-line therapy: 19 (51&#x00025;) younger patients, 28 (44&#x00025;) middle-aged patients, and 7 (41&#x00025;) elderly patients (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> for trend not significant).</p></sec><sec><title>Safety</title><p>Main severe haematological toxicity of this regimen was neutropenia, which occurred in 46 patients on the whole: grade &#x02a7e;3 neutropenia was detected in 43&#x00025; of younger, in 41&#x00025; of middle-aged, and in 31&#x00025; of elderly group. Only four patients suffered from neutropenic fever or infection: their age ranged between 45 and 64 years. Among nonhaematological side effects, grade &#x02a7e;3 diarrhoea was reported in 11&#x00025; of younger, 18&#x00025; of aged, and 6&#x00025; of elderly patients (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup>-test not significant). Severe stomatitis occurred in three patients on the whole: one patient in each age-group. Occurrence of other adverse events was not different in the three age groups (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Severe (WHO grade &#x02a7e;3) toxicity according to age grouping</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="3" align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>Age&#x02013;groups (years)</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Toxicity WHO grade &#x02a7e;3</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>&#x02a7d;54 <italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;37</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>55&#x02013;69 <italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;64</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>&#x02a7e;70 <italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;17</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Neutropenia</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">43</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">41</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Anaemia</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Thrombocytopenia</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Neutropenic fever&#x0002f;infection</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Diarrhoea</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Stomatitis</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Nausea&#x0002f;vomiting</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alopecia</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">51</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">36</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Hepatic</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Cholinergic syndrome</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Any type (except for alopecia)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">68</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">70</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">50</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote5"><label/><p>Numbers are percent of patients.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>). Interestingly, a lower proportion of elderly patients suffered from at least one episode of grade &#x02a7e;3 toxicity of any type (excluding alopecia) in comparison with aged or younger patients. However, seven patients, all belonging to the <italic>middle-aged group</italic>, went off-study for toxicity (diarrhoea, six cases; severe bone marrow suppression, one case). Treatment-induced or treatment-exacerbated early death (as defined by <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib24">Rothemberg <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>) occurred in three of 118 (2.5&#x00025;) patients: a 62-year-old woman, completely asymptomatic at study entry), died of severe diarrhoea and dehydration after two courses; another woman, aged 63 years, and with initial PS&#x0003d;1, suffered from deep phlebitis with subsequent pulmonary embolism and acute cardiac failure after three cycles; and a 69-year-old man, entered into the study in good PS and no cardiac contraindications, had a fatal myocardial infarction after three cycles.</p></sec><sec><title>Activity</title><p>As already reported, the IRIFAFU regimen produced nine complete plus 33 partial responses, for an overall response rate (RR) of 36&#x00025; (95&#x00025; confidence interval, 28&#x02013;44&#x00025;), according to intent-to-treat analysis. In addition, 12 patients showed a tumour shrinkage that did not qualify for a major response. RR was comparable in all age groups: it was 38&#x00025; in the younger, 34&#x00025; in the middle-aged, and 35&#x00025; in the elderly patients. Similarly, no statistically significant difference in RR was observed according to gender (males, 36&#x00025;; females, 35&#x00025;); primary site (colon, 37&#x00025;; rectum, 30&#x00025;); previous adjuvant chemotherapy (yes, 41&#x00025;; no, 34&#x00025;); onset of metastasis (synchronous, 35&#x00025;, metachronous, 36&#x00025;); basal CEA serum level (&#x0003c;100&#x02009;ng&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 36&#x00025;; &#x02a7e;100&#x02009;ng&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 40&#x00025;). Some baseline characteristics, although not reaching a significant <italic>P</italic>-value, seemed affecting more the probability of response. This holds true for number of disease sites (single, 42&#x00025;; multiple, 27&#x00025;), performance status (0, 41&#x00025;; &#x02a7e;1, 27&#x00025;), disease symptoms (absent, 41&#x00025;; present, 26&#x00025;), previous loss of body weight (absent, 39&#x00025;; present, 24&#x00025;), previous radical surgery (yes, 38&#x00025;; no, 23&#x00025;). Keeping these last variables together with the age grouping into a logistic regression analysis, no significant interaction was reported with the activity rate.</p></sec><sec><title>Long-term outcome</title><p>After a median follow-up of 30 months, 91 (77&#x00025;) patients had progressed, and 75 (64&#x00025;) had died. Besides the already mentioned three early deaths, two other patients died for a disease- and treatment-unrelated reason: a 66-year-old man committed suicide after 4 months from initial treatment, and a 36-year-old patient affected by insulin-dependent diabetes died of uncontrolled metabolic coma after 3 months from the start of therapy. Median PFS was 7.4, 8.0, and 5.3 months, for younger, middle-aged and elderly patients (log-rank test not significant also when adjusted by gender). In the multivariate analysis, taking into account all pretreatment characteristics, the presence of disease-related symptoms was the only variable significantly associated with a shorter PFS (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.053), while age group was of borderline significance (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.099). Survival, which at the Cox analysis resulted significantly affected by number of disease sites and previous loss of body weight, was unrelated to the age of patients: indeed, median OS was 13.4, 15.3, and 13.9 months, respectively, for the three age groups.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this paper, we have retrospectively reported on a series of patients affected by advanced colorectal carcinoma, randomly allocated to receive the IRIFAFU regimen, with the aim to ascertain whether the safety and activity of this regimen could have been affected by the age of patients. For this purpose, patients were divided in three age groups. Apart from sex, other baseline characteristics were evenly distributed across the three groups.</p><p>Considering the occurrence of treatment-related adverse events, as registered by the investigators, it appeared that severe toxicity was not greater in elderly as compared with other patients. An usually uncomplicated neutropenia affected a similar proportion of patients, regardless of age. Occurrence of severe diarrhoea was even lower among elderly patients. On the whole, a smaller proportion of elderly patients suffered from any type of severe toxicity. However, delays or dose reductions were applied during the initial treatment more frequently for elderly than for remaining patients. This apparent discrepancy may be explained by an earlier onset of side effects in elderly patients. Indeed, dose intensity over eight cycles was not different across the age groups, which is an indirect evidence that, with a cautious and tailored approach, our regimen was feasible also in elderly patients.</p><p>As for treatment discontinuation, it is worth noting that no young patient refused the study treatment, in contrast with four patients each in the two other groups. This observation may suggest that, despite toxicity was not more pronounced among these patients, the subjective perception of treatment-related physical and&#x0002f;or psychological distress was in these cases no longer tolerable. At this proposal, we would remember that a mental depression, which is a common psychiatric syndrome in elderly subjects, may be even more frequent in cancer patients. The presence and severity of this syndrome, when not sought and properly managed by the attending physicians, may adversely affect the compliance of patients to the anticancer treatment.</p><p>Although the results reported here were generated by a retrospective analysis, which was not powered to reveal significant differences according to age of patients, we believe meaningful that the proportion of responders was similar in all age groups. In addition, while a slightly poorer median PFS was registered for elderly, no difference at all in OS was noted for these patients as compared to middle-aged and younger ones. In this respect, a careful check for the presence of disease-related symptoms, or for a recent loss of body weight, together with an appropriate assessment of disease extent, showed a greater prognostic significance than the ECOG PS score.</p><p>Of course, this basically descriptive analysis cannot permit to draw firm conclusions, but it could help in generating hypotheses for future studies, in which the clinical benefit for elderly patients should be prospectively outweighed against the occurrence of side effects. Indeed, we have to admit that patients aged &#x02a7e;70 years were under-represented also in our trial. Although we may confirm that all eligible patients were offered to entry into this study, we cannot exclude a systematic selection bias, due to some reluctance of attending caregivers in referring elderly patients to cancer centres, or because of a poor willingness of patients themselves to take part in a randomised trial, or to undergo chemotherapy at all.</p><p>Moreover, in our case series no information was collected about the number and types of associated diseases, which may adversely affect the long-term outcome of patients (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib11">Extermann <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib30">Yancik <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>). This was mainly due to the lack of a standard scoring system for co-morbidities in cancer patients (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib23">Repetto <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>). Furthermore, a comprehensive geriatric assessment, including an evaluation of functional, cognitive and psychological status, has been strongly recommended for aged patients, in order to anticipate the acceptance and tolerability of a cytotoxic treatment (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib1">Balducci and Yates, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib16">Kearney <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib17">K&#x000f6;hne <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, we suggest that geriatrics and medical oncologists should tightly cooperate in carefully evaluating elderly colon cancer patients, in order to identify those who may benefit from irinotecan plus FU combinations, and excluding patients with medical contraindications, or with an impairment of their physical, cognitive and&#x0002f;or psychological status. Furthermore, we strongly recommend the implementation of prospective trials to assess properly the quality of life of elderly patients undergoing chemotherapy. In this way, it could be possible to counteract an unjustified &#x02018;ageism&#x02019;, a prejudice that denies opportunities of treatment or even cure for patients that, as far as we know, may have the same chance as younger people (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib22">Potosky <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>). Apart from the obvious ethical and juridical implications of such a negative attitude, we would remember that a recent economic evaluation of healthcare intervention has quantified an additional yearly cost of about &#x00024;1200 for elderly cancer patients receiving specific treatments (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib12">Hayman <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). In our opinion, this extra expense is by far included in the costs that a developed country can effort to manage these individuals.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dr Maurizio Montella and Dr Anna Crispo (Unit of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, National Tumour Institute, Naples, Italy) for their assistance in data management and statistical analysis of this study.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balducci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>General guidelines for the management of older patients with cancer</article-title><source>Oncology (Huntington)</source><year>2000</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Oncology (Huntington)||14|221||bib1|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buroker</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connel</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieand</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Krook</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerstner</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mailliard</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Levitt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kardinal</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gesme</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Randomized comparison of two schedules of fluorouracil and leucovorin in the treatment of advanced colorectal cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1994</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||12|14||bib2|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7677801</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nobile</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincenti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lionetto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gozza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barzacchi</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanguineti</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Repetto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advanced colorectal cancer in the elderly: results of consecutive trials with 5-fluorouracil-based chemotherapy</article-title><source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source><year>1998</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Chemother Pharmacol||42|336||bib3|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9744780</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Colorectal Cancer Collaborative Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Palliative chemotherapy for advanced colorectal cancer: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2000</year><volume>321</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'BMJ||321|531||bib4|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Comella</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vita</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancarella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>De Lucia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Biglietto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Casaretti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Farris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ianniello</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorusso</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Avallone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carten&#x000ec;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Leo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>De Lena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Comella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biweekly irinotecan or raltitrexed plus 6S-leucovorin and bolus 5-fluorouracil in advanced colorectal carcinoma. A Southern Italy Cooperative Oncology Group phase II&#x0002f;III randomized trial</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2000</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1323</fpage><lpage>1333</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Ann Oncol||11|1323||bib5|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11106123</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Comella</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Crucitta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vita</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>De Lucia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Farris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Gaizo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmeri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Iannelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancarella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tafuto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Maiorino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Buzzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>De Cataldis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Addition of either irinotecan or methotrexate to bolus fluorouracil and high-dose leucovorin every two weeks in advanced colorectal carcinoma: a randomized study of the Southern Italy Cooperative Oncology Group</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>866</fpage><lpage>873</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Ann Oncol||13|866||bib6|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12123331</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regression models and life tables</article-title><source>J Roy Stat Assoc</source><year>1972</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Roy Stat Assoc||34|187||bib7|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daniele</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Should chemotherapy be used as a treatment of advanced colorectal carcinoma (ACC) in patients over 70 years of age</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>1999</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1640</fpage><lpage>1649</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Eur J Cancer||35|1640||bib8|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10674007</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Gramont</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Figer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Homerin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hmissi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassidy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortes-Funes</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cervantes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Freyer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Papamichael</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Bail</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Louvet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>de Braud</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Morvan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leucovorin and fluorouracil with or without oxaliplatin as first-line treatment in advanced colorectal cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2000</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>2938</fpage><lpage>2947</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||18|2938||bib9|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10944126</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Douillard</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Karasek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jandik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Iveson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alakl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rougier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Irinotecan combined with fluorouracil compared with fluorouracil alone as first-line treatment for metastatic colorectal cancer</article-title><source>A multicentre randomised trial. Lancet</source><year>2000</year><volume>355</volume><fpage>1041</fpage><lpage>1047</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'A multicentre randomised trial. Lancet||355|1041||bib10|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Extermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Overcash</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyman</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Parr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Balducci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comorbidity and functional status are independent in older cancer patients</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1998</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1582</fpage><lpage>1587</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||16|1582||bib11|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9552069</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Langa</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabeto</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>DeMonner</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernew</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Slavin</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fendrick</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating the cost of informal caregiving for elderly patients with cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3219</fpage><lpage>3225</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||19|3219||bib12|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11432889</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hutchins</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Unger</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coltman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Albain</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Underrepresentation of patients 64 years of age or older in cancer-treatment trials</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>341</volume><fpage>2061</fpage><lpage>2067</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'N Engl J Med||341|2061||bib13|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10615079</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>International Multicenter Pooled Analysis of B2 Colon Cancer Trials</collab></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of adjuvant fluorouracil and folinic acid in B2 colon cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1999</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1356</fpage><lpage>1363</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||17|1356||bib14|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10334519</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-parametric estimation from incomplete observations</article-title><source>J Am Stat Assoc</source><year>1958</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Am Stat Assoc||53|457||bib15|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oncology healthcare professionals' attitude towards elderly people</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2000</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Ann Oncol||11|599||bib16|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10907955</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000f6;hne</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Grothey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokemeyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bontke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Aapro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemotherapy in elderly patients with colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2001</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Ann Oncol||12|435||bib17|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11398873</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mamounas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolmark</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bear</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rockette</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative efficacy of adjuvant chemotherapy in patients with Dukes' B versus Dukes' C colon cancer: results from four National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project adjuvant studies (C-01, C-02, C-03, and C-04)</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1999</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1355</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||17|1349||bib18|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10334518</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoogstraten</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Staquet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reporting results of cancer treatment</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>1981</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer||47|207||bib19|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7459811</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Breslow</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Peto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design and analysis of randomised clinical trials requiring prolonged observation on each patient</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1977</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||35|1||bib20|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">831755</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popescu</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adjuvant or palliative chemotherapy for colorectal cancer in patients 70 years or older</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1999</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2412</fpage><lpage>2418</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||17|2412||bib21|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10561304</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Potosky</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Harlan</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age, sex, and racial differences in the use of standard adjuvant therapy for colorectal cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2002</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1192</fpage><lpage>1202</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||20|1192||bib22|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11870160</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Repetto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fratino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Audisio</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Venturino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gianni</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Vercelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parodi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dal Lago</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gioia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Monfardini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aapro</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Serraino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zagonel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive geriatric assessment adds information to Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status in elderly cancer patients: an Italian Group for Geriatric Oncology study</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2002</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||20|494||bib23|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11786579</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rothemberg</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Meropol</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Poplin</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Cutsem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wadler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mortality associated with irinotecan plus bolus fluorouracil&#x0002f;leucovorin: summary findings of an independent panel</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3801</fpage><lpage>3807</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||19|3801||bib24|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11559717</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saltz</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fehrenbacher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maroun</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackland</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Locker</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirotta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Elfring</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Irinotecan plus fluorouracil and leucovorin for metastatic colorectal cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>905</fpage><lpage>914</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'N Engl J Med||343|905||bib25|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11006366</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sargent</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname></name><name><surname>JC</surname></name><name><surname>Labianca</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Seitz</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Francini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A pooled analysis of adjuvant chemotherapy for resected colon cancer in elderly patients</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2001a</year><volume>345</volume><fpage>1091</fpage><lpage>1097</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'N Engl J Med||345|1091||bib26|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11596588</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sargent</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Niedzwiecki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connel</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilsky</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recommendation for caution with irinotecan, fluorouracil, and leucovorin for colorectal cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2001b</year><volume>345</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'N Engl J Med||345|144||bib27|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11450666</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundararajan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Grann</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitjan</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Neugut</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival associated with 5-fluorouracil-based adjuvant chemotherapy among elderly patients with node-positive colon cancer</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Ann Intern Med||136|349||bib28|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11874307</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolmark</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rockette</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamounas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickerham</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bear</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical trial to assess the relative efficacy of fluorouracil and leucovorin, fluorouracil and levamisole, and fluorouracil, leucovorin, and levamisole in patients with Dukes' B and C carcinoma of the colon: results from National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project C-04</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1999</year><volume>17(11)</volume><fpage>3553</fpage><lpage>3559</lpage>Nov<!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||17(11)|3553||bib32|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10550154</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yancik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganz</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Varricchio</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Conley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspectives on comorbidity and cancer in older patients: Approaches to expand the knowledge base</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1147</fpage><lpage>1151</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||19|1147||bib29|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11181680</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yancik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wesley</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ries</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Havlik</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comorbidity and age as predictors of risk for early mortality of male and female colon carcinoma patients: A population-based study</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>1998</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>2123</fpage><lpage>2134</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer||82|2123||bib30|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9610691</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zanetti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Crosignani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vigane</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title/><source>Cancer in Italy: Incidence data from Cancer Registries. Vol. 2, 1988&#x02013;1992</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>Roma: II Pensiero Scientifico Editore</publisher-name></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


