<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><!-- Original-type: oa--><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">12865915</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2394273</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6601060</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjc.6601060</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Molecular and Cellular Pathology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor in node-positive breast cancer patients treated with adjuvant tamoxifen</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coradini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Biganzoli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pellizzaro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Veneroni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oriana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ambrogi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Erdas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boracchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Daidone</surname><given-names>M G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marubini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><sup>1</sup>Unit&#x000e0; Operativa Determinanti Biomolecolari nella Prognosi e Terapia, Istituto Nazionale per lo Studio e la Cura dei Tumori, Via Venezian, 1, 20133 Milan, Italy</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><sup>2</sup>Unit&#x000e0; di Statistica Medica e Biometria, Istituto Nazionale per lo Studio e la Cura dei Tumori, Via Venezian, 1, 20133 Milan, Italy</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><sup>3</sup>Unit&#x000e0; di Chirurgia Senologica, Istituto Nazionale per lo Studio e la Cura dei Tumori, Via Venezian, 1, 20133 Milan, Italy</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><sup>4</sup>Istituto di Statistica Medica e Biometria, Universit&#x000e0; degli Studi di Milano, 20133 Milan, Italy</aff><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>Author for correspondence: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:danila.coradini@istitutotumori.mi.it">danila.coradini@istitutotumori.mi.it</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>07</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>21</day><month>07</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><volume>89</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2002</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>07</day><month>04</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>04</month><year>2003</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright 2003, Cancer Research UK</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2003</copyright-year><permissions><copyright-holder>Cancer Research UK</copyright-holder></permissions><kwd-group><kwd>vascular endothelial growth factor</kwd><kwd>steroid receptors</kwd><kwd>node-positive breast cancer</kwd><kwd>tamoxifen</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Breast tissue is highly responsive to changes in ovarian hormone concentrations that induce a cyclic remodelling process involving epithelial, stromal and vascular components during each menstrual cycle (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib17">Vogel <italic>et al</italic>, 1981</xref>). In particular, the angiogenic turnover is regulated by oestrogens and progesterone, which modulate the expression of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) in the epithelial cells of the terminal ductal&#x02013;lobular units (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib14">Nakamura <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>).</p><p>Although the VEGF gene promoter lacks a perfect palindromic oestrogen-responsive element, an analogue of the consensus element that functions as a classical enhancer for oestrogen receptor (ER) has been identified in the 3&#x02032;-untranslated region (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib12">Hyder <italic>et al</italic>, 2000b</xref>).</p><p>Angiogenesis is known to represent a fundamental step in tumour progression (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib8">Hanahan and Folkman, 1996</xref>) and clinical evidence has shown that node-negative (N&#x02212;) as well as node-positive (N&#x0002b;) breast cancer patients with high intratumoral VEGF concentrations have a significantly shorter relapse-free survival (RFS) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib4">Gasparini <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib5">1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib13">Linderholm <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>).</p><p>Preclinical studies on breast cancer cell lines demonstrated that, as expected, oestrogens rapidly induce VEGF expression, which is blocked by pure oestrogen antagonists (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib16">Ruohola <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib11">Hyder <italic>et al</italic>, 2000a</xref>).</p><p>In a series of N&#x0002b; ER-positive (ER&#x0002b;, by ligand-binding assay, LBA) postmenopausal women with resectable breast cancer who received adjuvant tamoxifen, we investigated the comprehensive effect on RFS of VEGF content and steroid receptor profile, evaluated in the same cytosolic fraction.</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>PATIENTS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Patients</title><p>The study included postmenopausal patients with primary resectable invasive breast cancer, histologically classified as N&#x0002b;, who underwent surgery at the Istituto Nazionale Tumori in Milan between March 1991 and December 1995 and received only adjuvant tamoxifen (20&#x02009;mg&#x02009;day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) for at least 2 years (median duration time, 4 years) because of their positive ER status (ER tumour concentration higher than 10&#x02009;fmol&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of protein). From a total of 859 N&#x0002b;, ER&#x0002b; postmenopausal patients, consecutive with respect to steroid receptor determination at the time of diagnosis, 289 were selected on the basis of treatment, histology (pure or mixed ductal or lobular invasive tumours) and follow-up (i.e. a minimum potential of 6 years from the date of surgery to the date of last updating of patient records).</p><p>Of the 289 eligible patients, 212 (73&#x00025;) were available for VEGF evaluation. Their median age was 64 years (range, 50&#x02013;85); 88 patients (42&#x00025;) were treated by mastectomy and 124 (58&#x00025;) by breast-conserving surgery plus radiotherapy. All of them underwent complete axillary lymph node dissection (median number of examined nodes, 18). Most patients had one to three metastatic axillary lymph nodes (139, 66&#x00025;). Small (&#x02a7d;2&#x02009;cm) and large (&#x0003e;2&#x02009;cm) tumours were equally represented (93, 48&#x00025; and 99, 52&#x00025;, respectively). After surgery, the patients were followed at 6-month intervals during the first 5 years and at 12-month intervals thereafter; disease status was assessed by means of physical examination, chest X-ray, bone scan and abdominal sonography. Treatment failure was defined as the first documented evidence of new disease manifestations in locoregional areas (seven cases), distant sites (40 cases), or in the contralateral breast (five cases). Relapse-free survival was calculated as the time elapsed from diagnosis to the date of first recurrence or to the last clinical examination for patients without documented disease manifestation. Median follow-up for the whole series was 68 months (interquartile range, 52&#x02013;82 months).</p></sec><sec><title>Steroid receptor determination by LBA</title><p>Steroid receptor content was determined according to the EORTC recommendations and within national (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib15">Piffanelli <italic>et al</italic>, 1991</xref>) and international (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib3">EORTC Breast cancer co-operative group, 1980</xref>) quality control programmes by a double-labelling assay (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib2">Coradini <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>), and expressed as fmol&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of protein. Tumours with an ER<sub>LBA</sub> concentration higher than 10&#x02009;fmol&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of protein were defined as ER&#x0002b;.</p></sec><sec><title>Vascular endothelial growth factor determination</title><p>The predominant VEGF isoform, VEGF<sub>65</sub> (henceforward referred to as VEGF), was measured by a quantitative enzyme immunoassay technique (Quantikine, human VEGF; R&#x00026;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA) as described elsewhere (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib1">Coradini <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). Concentrations were expressed as pg of VEGF protein per mg of total protein.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The overall association of VEGF level with patient age, tumour size, number of metastatic lymph nodes, ER<sub>LBA</sub> and PgR<sub>LBA</sub> content was evaluated by Spearman's rank correlation coefficient.</p><p>The effect of VEGF, ER<sub>LBA</sub> and PgR<sub>LBA</sub> content on RFS was investigated by multivariate analysis using a Cox regression model in which also the number of metastatic lymph nodes was included. All variables were considered on a continuous scale after logarithmic transformation. Null values for PgR<sub>LBA</sub> content were arbitrarily set at 1, taking a sensitivity threshold value of 2&#x02009;fmol&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of protein. According to a previous finding (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib1">Coradini <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>), linear terms for log(ER<sub>LBA</sub>), log(PgR<sub>LBA</sub>) and log(VEGF) and the interaction between ER<sub>LBA</sub> and VEGF were included in the model.</p><p>The proportional hazard assumption of the Cox model was evaluated and the effect of model terms was tested as previously reported (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib1">Coradini <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>).</p><p>The library written by <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib9">Harrell <italic>et al</italic> (1996)</xref> was applied in some steps of the model building procedure and the SAS macro programme RELIMPCR designed by <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib10">Heinze and Schemper (2001)</xref> was adopted for evaluation of the relative prognostic contribution of the covariates.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>In this series of ER<sub>LBA</sub>-positive tumours from postmenopausal patients, the VEGF content ranged from 7 to 2186&#x02009;pg&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of protein with 52, 95 and 200 as the 25th, 50th and 75th percentiles, respectively; the PgR<sub>LBA</sub> concentration ranged from 1 to 2563&#x02009;fmol&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of protein with 40, 111 and 355 as the 25th, 50th and 75th percentiles, respectively. Vascular endothelial growth factor content did not show any significant correlation with any of the other variables considered; estimated correlation coefficients were all in the range &#x000b1;0.08.</p><p>In the multivariate model, the number of metastatic lymph nodes, VEGF, ER<sub>LBA</sub> and the interaction between ER<sub>LBA</sub> and VEGF were significantly related to prognosis (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Final Cox regression model results for RFS</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Effect</bold><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Wald statistics</bold><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>d.f.</bold><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>b</bold><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic><bold>P</bold></italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Metastatic nodes</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">19.76</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.6054</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">VEGF</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">7.70<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.7562</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0213</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ER<sub>LBA</sub></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">5.59<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.5317</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0610</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">PgR<sub>LBA</sub></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.26</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;0.0696</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.2617</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ER<sub>LBA</sub>&#x02013;VEGF</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4.73</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;0.3405</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0297</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Total</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">30.78</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote1"><label>a</label><p>Estimated regression coefficient.</p></fn><fn id="tbfnote2"><label>b</label><p>Factor &#x0002b;interaction.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>), whereas no significant contribution was observed for PgR<sub>LBA</sub>. As for ER<sub>LBA</sub>, VEGF and the ER<sub>LBA</sub>&#x02013;VEGF interaction, the results were similar to those previously obtained in patients with N&#x02013; breast cancer who did not receive systemic treatment (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib1">Coradini <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). This finding further supports the role of ER<sub>LBA</sub> in modulating the prognostic effect of VEGF and the negative interaction term indicates a decrease in the unfavourable effect of VEGF for increasing values of ER<sub>LBA</sub>.</p><p>To provide a description of the combined effect of VEGF and ER<sub>LBA</sub>, the relative hazard (RH) for increasing VEGF concentrations was plotted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Plots of the logarithm of the relative hazard of disease recurrence as a function of VEGF level for different ER<sub>LBA</sub> values (fixed approximately at the first and third quartiles of the distribution). The solid line corresponds to an ER<sub>LBA</sub>&#x0003d;70&#x02009;fmol&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> protein, whereas the dashed line corresponds to an ER<sub>LBA</sub>&#x0003d;220&#x02009;fmol&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> protein. Dotted lines indicate 95&#x00025; pointwise confidence limits (upper: UCL; lower: LCL).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="89-6601060f1"/></fig>) for selected values of ER<sub>LBA</sub> (70 and 220&#x02009;fmol&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of protein) that were approximately equal to the 1st and third quartiles of ER<sub>LBA</sub> distribution. Owing to the interaction between ER<sub>LBA</sub> and VEGF, when the ER<sub>LBA</sub> content was set at 70&#x02009;fmol&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> protein, the increase in the risk of disease recurrence for high VEGF values associated with low ER<sub>LBA</sub> values was evident. In fact, the estimated RH for patients with a VEGF content of 200 <italic>vs</italic> those with a VEGF content of 50&#x02009;pg&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> protein was 1.54 (95&#x00025; CI, 1.07&#x02013;2.20). Conversely, when the ER<sub>LBA</sub> content was set at 220&#x02009;fmol&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> protein, VEGF did not show any prognostic effect and the estimated RH for the two selected values (200 and 50&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was 0.89 (95&#x00025; CI, 0.54&#x02013;1.47).</p><p>Analysis of the prognostic contribution of the covariates showed that the model explained only 13.2&#x00025; of the total heterogeneity of the relapse times of our case series and that, considering the relative importance of prognostic factors, 8.2&#x00025; was attributable to the number of metastatic lymph nodes, whereas VEGF and ER<sub>LBA</sub> together contributed with 3.3&#x00025;, and PgR only with 0.8&#x00025;.</p></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>According to the recently revised treatment guidelines for early breast cancer (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib6">Goldhirsch <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>), postmenopausal women with ER&#x0002b; primary breast cancer should receive adjuvant hormone therapy with tamoxifen. However, a recent clinical study (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib13">Linderholm <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>) provided evidence that also the intratumoral VEGF content could predict outcome following adjuvant endocrine treatment: patients with ER&#x0002b; tumours, but a high VEGF expression, had a significantly shorter RFS and overall survival. In agreement with these findings, our results showed that, due to the presence of a negative interaction between ER<sub>LBA</sub> and VEGF, already observed in a series of N&#x02212; cancers (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib1">Coradini <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>), patients whose tumours had a low&#x0002f;intermediate ER<sub>LBA</sub> content exhibited an increased risk of disease recurrence with increasing values of intratumoral VEGF. Conversely, the VEGF level did not show prognostic effect in patients whose tumours had a high ER<sub>LBA</sub> content. These findings suggest that in tumours characterised by a high ER<sub>LBA</sub> concentration and therefore more likely to be hormonally regulated, tumour progression, activated or sustained by VEGF, may be counteracted by the protective effect of endocrine therapy. Conversely, when a patient has a high level of VEGF and a low ER<sub>LBA</sub> concentration, tamoxifen could fail to contrast the tumour's metastatic potential and more tailored adjuvant treatment would be required including, for example, an antiangiogenic agent.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This study was supported by a grant from the Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche (CNR) and the Italian Association for Cancer Research (AIRC), Italy.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coradini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Boracchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Daidone</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellizzaro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Miodini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ammatuna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomasic</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Biganzoli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of vascular endothelial growth factor to the Nottingham prognostic index in node-negative breast cancer</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2001</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>795</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||85|795||bib1|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556826</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coradini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Daidone</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Boracchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Biganzoli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Oriana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bresciani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellizzaro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomasic</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Fronzo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Marubini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Time-dependent relevance of steroid receptors in breast cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2000</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>2702</fpage><lpage>2709</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||18|2702||bib2|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10894869</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>EORTC Breast Cancer Co-operative Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Revision of the standards for the assessment of hormone receptors in human breast cancer. Report of the second EORTC Workshop, held on 16&#x02013;17 March 1979, in the Netherlands Cancer Institute</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>1980</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1513</fpage><lpage>1515</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Eur J Cancer||16|1513||bib3|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6262087</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasparini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Toi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Verderio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dittadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanatani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinante</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonoldi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Boracchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prognostic significance of vascular endothelial growth factor protein in node-negative breast carcinoma</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>1997</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Natl Cancer Inst||89|139||bib4|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8998183</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasparini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Toi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miceli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermeulen</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dittadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Biganzoli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Morabito</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dirix</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical relevance of vascular endothelial growth factor and thymidine phosphorylase in patients with node-positive breast cancer treated with either adjuvant chemotherapy or hormone therapy</article-title><source>Cancer J Sci Am</source><year>1999</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer J Sci Am||5|101||bib5|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10198732</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldhirsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Glick</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelber</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Senn</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Meeting highlights: International Consensus Panel on the treatment of primary breast cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3817</fpage><lpage>3827</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||19|3817||bib6|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11559719</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grambsch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Therneau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proportional hazards tests and diagnostics based on weighted residuals</article-title><source>Biometrika</source><year>1994</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Biometrika||81|515||bib7|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanahan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Folkman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns and emerging mechanisms of the angiogenic switch during tumorigenesis</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cell||86|353||bib8|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8756718</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrell</surname><given-names>FE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multivariable prognostic models: issues in developing models, evaluating assumptions and adequacy, and measuring and reducing errors</article-title><source>Stat Med</source><year>1996</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Stat Med||15|361||bib9|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8668867</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schemper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title/><source>RELIMPCR, and RELIMPLR SAS-macros for the analysis of relative importance of prognostic factors in Cox and logistic regression</source><year>2001</year><publisher-name>Vienna: University of Vienna. Department of Medical Computer Sciences, Section of Clinical Biometrics</publisher-name>Technical Report 3&#x0002f;2001</citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hyder</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Boettger-Tong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Makela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiappetta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stancel</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of vascular endothelial growth factor expression by estrogens and progestins</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>2000a</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>785</fpage><lpage>790</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Environ Health Perspect||108|785||bib11|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hyder</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiappetta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stancel</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of functional response elements in the gene coding for the potent angiogenic factor vascular endothelial growth factor</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2000b</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>3183</fpage><lpage>3190</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||60|3183||bib12|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10866309</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linderholm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Grankvist</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilking</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavelin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Heriksson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation of vascular endothelial growth factor content with recurrences, survival and first relapse site in primary node-positive breast carcinoma after adjuvant treatment</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2000</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1423</fpage><lpage>1431</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||18|1423||bib13|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10735889</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Aberdeen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of estrogen on aromatase and vascular endothelial growth factor messenger ribonucleic acid in the normal nonhuman primate mammary gland</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1999</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1432</fpage><lpage>1437</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Endocrinol Metab||84|1432||bib14|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10199791</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piffanelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelizzola</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>De Bortoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Catozzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Giganti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Steroid receptor assays: an Italian quality assessment program</article-title><source>Ann Ist Super Sanit&#x000e0;</source><year>1991</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Ann Ist Super Sanit&#x000e0;||27|523||bib15|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruohola</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Valve</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Karkkainen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Joukov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Alitalo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Harkonen</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factors are differentially regulated by steroid hormones and antiestrogens in breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Mol Cell Endocrinol</source><year>1999</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Mol Cell Endocrinol||25|29||bib16|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgiade</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetter</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mc Carty</surname><given-names>KS</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>The correlation of histologic changes in human breast with the menstrual cycle</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>1981</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Am J Pathol||104|23||bib17|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7258295</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


