<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8855989</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2077108</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Phase I study of simultaneous dose escalation and schedule acceleration of cyclophosphamide-doxorubicin-etoposide using granulocyte colony-stimulating factor with or without antimicrobial prophylaxis in patients with small-cell lung cancer.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ardizzoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pennucci</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Danova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Viscoli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Giorgi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Venturini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mereu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scolaro</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rosso</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Division of Medical Oncology I, Istituto Nazionale per la Ricerca sul Cancro, Genoa, Italy.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>74</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1141</fpage><lpage>1147</lpage><abstract><p>A phase I study was designed to assess whether dose intensity of an 'accelerated' cyclophosphamide-doxorubicin-etoposide (CDE) regimen plus granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF) could be increased further, in an outpatient setting, by escalating the dose of each single drug of the regimen. Patients with previously untreated small-cell lung cancer (SCLC) received escalating doses of cyclophosphamide (C) 1100-1300 mg m-2 intravenously (i.v.) on day 1, doxorubicin (D) 50-60 mg m-2 i.v. on day 1, etoposide (E) 110-130 mg m-2 i.v. on days 1, 2, 3 and every 14 days for at least three courses. Along with chemotherapy, G-CSF (filgastrim) 5 micrograms kg-1 from day 5 to day 11 was administered subcutaneously (s.c.) to all patients. Twenty-five patients were enrolled into the study. All patients at the first dose level (C 1100, D 50, E 110 x 3) completed three or more cycles at the dose and schedule planned by the protocol and no 'dose-limiting toxicity' (DLT) was seen. At the second dose level (C 1200, D 55, E 120 x 3) three out of five patients had a DLT consisting of 'granulocytopenic fever' (GCPF). Another six patients were treated at this dose level with the addition of ciprofloxacin 500 mg twice a day and only two patients had a DLT [one episode of documented oral candidiasis and one of 'fever of unknown origin' (FUO) with generalised mucositis]. Accrual of patients proceeded to the third dose level (C 1300, D 60, E 130 x 3) with the prophylactic use of ciprofloxacin. Four out of six patients experienced a DLT consisting of GCPF or documented non-bacterial infection. Accrual of patients at the third dose level was then resumed adding to ciprofloxacin anti-fungal prophylaxis (fluconazole 100 mg daily) and anti-viral prophylaxis (acyclovir 800 mg twice a day) from day 5 to 11. Out of five patients treated three experienced a DLT consisting of severe leucopenia and fever or infection. With a simultaneous dose escalation and schedule acceleration it is indeed possible to take maximum advantage of G-CSF activity and to increase CDE dose intensity by a factor 1.65-1.80 for a maximum of 3-4 courses. The role of antimicrobial prophylaxis in this setting deserves to be investigated further.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00023-0147.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1141" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00023-0148.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1142" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00023-0149.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1143" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00023-0150.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1144" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00023-0151.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1145" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00023-0152.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1146" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00023-0153.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1147" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

