<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ViewNLM-v2.3.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608400</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2816285</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2004.19.6.870</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Quantitative Analysis of <italic>SMN1</italic> Gene and Estimation of <italic>SMN1</italic> Deletion Carrier Frequency in Korean Population based on Real-Time PCR</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Tae-Mi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Sang-Wun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Kwang-Soo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Hyun-Seok</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>Soo Kyung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>Inho</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Seongman</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Sung-Chul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">&#x02021;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>*</label>Division of Genetic Disease, Department of Biomedical Sciences, National Institute of Health, Seoul, Korea.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>&#x02020;</label>Graduate School of Life Sciences and Biotechnology, Korea University, Seoul, Korea.</aff><aff id="A3"><label>&#x02021;</label>Department of Biochemistry, Ewha Womans University, Seoul, Korea.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Address for correspondence: Sung-Chul Jung, M.D. Department of Biochemistry, College of Medicine, Ewha Womans University, 911-1 Mok-dong, Yangcheon-gu, Seoul 158-710, Korea. Tel: +82.2-2650-5724, Fax: +82.2-2652-7846, <email>jungsc@ewha.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>870</fpage><lpage>873</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Spinal muscular atrophy (SMA) is an autosomal recessive disorder, caused by homozygous absence of the survival motor neuron gene (<italic>SMN1</italic>) in approximately 94% of patients. Since most carriers have only one <italic>SMN1</italic> gene copy, several <italic>SMN1</italic> quantitative analyses have been used for the SMA carrier detection. We developed a reliable quantitative real-time PCR with SYBR Green I dye and studied 13 patients with SMA and their 24 parents, as well as 326 healthy normal individuals. The copy number of the <italic>SMN1</italic> gene was determined by the comparative threshold cycle (Ct) method and albumin was used as a reference gene. The homozygous <italic>SMN1</italic> deletion ratio of patients was 0.00 and the hemizygous <italic>SMN1</italic> deletion ratio of parents ranged from 0.39 to 0.59. The &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct ratios of 7 persons among 326 normal individuals were within the carrier range, 0.41-0.57. According to these data, we estimated the carrier and disease prevalence of SMA at 1/47 and 1/8,496 in Korean population, respectively. These data indicated that there would be no much difference in disease prevalence of SMA compared with western countries. Since the prevalence of SMA is higher than other autosomal recessive disorders, the carrier detection method using real-time PCR could be a useful tool for genetic counseling.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Muscular Atrophy, Spinal</kwd><kwd>SMN Protein</kwd><kwd>Gene Deletion</kwd><kwd>Heterozygote</kwd><kwd>Polymerase Chain Reaction</kwd><kwd>PCR, Real-time</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Spinal muscular atrophy (SMA) is one of the most common autosomal recessive disorders characterized by progressive muscle weakness caused by degeneration of the spinal anterior horn cells. SMA has a prevalence of 1/6,000 to 1/10,000 births and a carrier frequency of 1/40 to 1/50 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). According to age of onset and severity of symptoms, patients with SMA are subdivided into three clinical types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). Type I (Werdnig-Hoffmann disease; OMIM 253300) is the most severe form with the onset at birth to the first few month and death by 2 yr of life. Type II (OMIM 253550), intermediate form, is characterized by the onset before 18 months of age and survival beyond 4 yr-old age. Type III (Kugelberg-Welander disease; OMIM 253400) is the mildest form with the onset after the age of 2 yr and survival into adulthood.</p><p>All types of SMA are associated with homozygous deletion in the survival motor neuron 1 gene (<italic>SMN1</italic>; OMIM 600354) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). <italic>SMN1</italic> and its homologous gene, <italic>SMN2</italic> (OMIM 601627), are located on 5q13. The two SMN genes are different at only five nucleotide exchanges within their 3' ends (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). In contrast to <italic>SMN1</italic>, the expression of SMN2 protein is truncated from skipping of exon 7 by a single nucleotide exchange (840C&#x02192;T) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Approximately 94% of SMA patients lack both copies of <italic>SMN1</italic> exon 7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>), which can be detected by the commonly used molecular analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>).</p><p>As the carrier frequency in population is high, the carrier test for SMA is important issue in genetic counseling. Until now, several quantitative PCR methods for <italic>SMN1</italic> analysis have been developed for carrier detection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). However, these methods were intricate and easily submitted to errors. Recently reported quantitative real-time PCR assays (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>) allow the specific amplification of only <italic>SMN1</italic> gene, and become powerful tools to avoid these problems. However, these tests include still several limitations in relation to the specificity, and cost-effectiveness.</p><p>In consideration of these defects, we developed a reliable quantitative real-time PCR method using <italic>SMN1</italic> gene specific primers and SYBR Green I dye for the carrier detection of SMA. The comparative Ct (threshold cycle) method was used to quantify the copy numbers of <italic>SMN1</italic> gene. This test allowed us to analyze a large number of samples efficiently. Here, we report the results of quantitative analysis of <italic>SMN1</italic> gene in SMA patients and parents, and the estimated carrier frequency in Korean population.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Subjects</title><p>Quantitative analysis of <italic>SMN1</italic> gene was done in 13 patients with SMA and their 24 parents. Clinical diagnosis was fulfilled on all patients and homozygous absence of <italic>SMN1</italic> exon 7 was confirmed with polymerase chain reaction-restriction fragment length polymorphism (PCR-RFLP) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>).</p><p>To estimate the carrier frequency in Korean population, we selected 326 unrelated healthy individuals aged 19-81 yr who participated in a comprehensive health screening in Ansan Health Center (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). Informed consents for DNA analysis were obtained from the patients and normal individuals.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA extraction</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted from peripheral blood samples by the QIAamp DNA blood kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) and was measured by an Ultrospec&#x000ae;2100 (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech, Piscataway, NJ, U.S.A.). Samples that had purity in the range of 1.5-1.8 (260 nm/280 nm ratio) were used for highly efficient amplification. DNAs were diluted to a final concentration of 2.5 ng/&#x000b5;L.</p></sec><sec><title>Quantitative real-time PCR of <italic>SMN1</italic></title><p>The quantitative real-time PCR assay was based on primers that specifically amplify <italic>SMN1</italic> gene. To distinguish <italic>SMN1</italic> from <italic>SMN2</italic> (GenBank AH006635) in the amplication reactions, 3' ends of the primers were designed to end on the <italic>SMN1</italic> specific sequence in exon 7 at position 6 and intron 7 at position +2: forward primer is 5'-CCTTTTATTTTCCTTACAGGGTTT<italic>C</italic>-3'; reverse primer is 5'-GATTGTTTTACATTAACCTTTCAACTTT<italic>T</italic>-3'. Specificity of the <italic>SMN1</italic> primers was confirmed by multiplex PCR with <italic>COL1A1</italic> gene (forward primer, 5'-GGGGGAACAAGGCTGTCT-3'; reverse primer, 5'-TCCTGGGGTTCAGACCAA-3') in patient samples and a normal individual's. As a reference gene, we used exon 12 of human serum albumin: forward primer is 5'-AGCTATCCGTGGTCCTGAAC-3; reverse primer is 5'-TTCTCAGAAAGTGTGCATATATCTG-3'. Using the ABI PRISM&#x000ae;7700 Sequence Detection System (PE Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, U.S.A.), the PCR was performed in a total volume of 20 &#x000b5;L in each well, containing 10 &#x000b5;L of SYBR Green&#x000ae; PCR Master Mix (PE Applied Biosystems), 20 ng of genomic DNA (8 &#x000b5;L), and 0.1 &#x000b5;M and 0.5 &#x000b5;M of <italic>SMN1</italic> and albumin primers, which was determined after the analysis of the optimal concentrations of each primer. Each sample was run in triplicates in separate tubes to permit quantification of the <italic>SMN1</italic> gene normalized to albumin. The PCR condition consisted of initial denaturation step of 95&#x02103; for 10 min, followed by 40 cycles of 95&#x02103; for 15 sec and 60&#x02103; for 1 min.</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><p>All data were calculated by the comparative Ct method, to detect the relative gene copy numbers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). By using a calibrator sample of a normal control DNA, the gene copy numbers of unknown samples were estimated. Patients, carrier, and unrelated normal samples were analyzed together with the calibrator sample on every assay plate. &#x00394;Ct represents the mean Ct value of each sample and was calculated for <italic>SMN1</italic> and albumin. The gene copy numbers of the samples were determined by the following formula: &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct=[&#x00394;Ct albumin (calibrator sample)-&#x00394;Ct SMN1 (calibrator sample)]-[&#x00394;Ct albumin (unknown sample)-&#x00394;Ct <italic>SMN1</italic> (unknown sample)]. The relative gene copy numbers were calculated by the expression 2<sup>-&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup>. Using this method, a &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct ratio, [2<sup>-&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup>], was expected to be about 1 in normal controls, about 0.5 in carriers and 0 in patients with SMA.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>The Ct values of <italic>SMN1</italic> and albumin triplicates showed almost identical at the amplification plots of a normal control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). The standard deviations of triplicate Ct values for all samples were very low (mean, 0.10; range, 0.00-0.32). In parents of SMA patients, carrying only one <italic>SMN1</italic> gene copy, the Ct values of <italic>SMN1</italic> increased about 1.32 compared with albumin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). In the SMA patients, the albumin gene was amplified as in normal controls, but the <italic>SMN1</italic> gene was not amplified as expected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Their &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct ratios were 0.00 showing homozygous absence of <italic>SMN1</italic> gene. In accordance with this result, there were no visible products of the <italic>SMN1</italic> genes in SMA patients by multiplex PCR with <italic>COL1A1</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The range of measured &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct ratios in 24 parents was between 0.39 and 0.59 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). To estimate the frequency of carrier in general population, we tested 326 healthy individuals. Among them, &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct ratios of 7 persons were within the carrier range, 0.41-0.57, indicating that the carrier prevalence was about 1/47 in Korean population (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). The others were detected between 0.84 and 2.19. This result was classified into three groups according to the expected copy numbers of <italic>SMN1</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>SMA carrier test based on direct quantitative analysis of <italic>SMN1</italic> gene is one of the most important issues, since homozygous deletion of <italic>SMN1</italic> exon 7 is a common variant. However, the reports of SMA carrier frequency have been concentrated in western countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). Therefore, we tried to calculate the SMA carrier frequency in Korea and developed the reliable quantitative test of <italic>SMN1</italic> based on real-time PCR with the SYBR Green I dye using the comparative Ct method. We used primers ending on to the nucleotide exchanges between the <italic>SMN1</italic> and <italic>SMN2</italic> genes in exon 7 to distinguish the <italic>SMN1</italic> and <italic>SMN2</italic> genes. The specificity and sensitivity of the test are 100%, although the presence of two <italic>SMN1</italic> copies per chromosome or intragenic point mutations in some of the SMA chromosomes (approximately 5%) slightly decreases the sensitivity of the test.</p><p>We determined the range of carrier gene dosage in 24 parents (0.39-0.59) of SMA patients, in which homozygous deletion of <italic>SMN1</italic> gene were identified previously by PCR-RFLP (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), and then screened 326 healthy normal individuals. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, there is no overlap between the range of &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct ratio measured <italic>SMN1</italic> copy numbers in carriers and normal individuals. The prevalence of carrier was 1/47 in Korean population (95% confidence interval: 1/175-1/27), within the similar ranges reported in western countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). In 65 individuals, the <italic>SMN1</italic> copy numbers were three or four copies like as in other countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>).</p><p>Since SMA is a fatal disease, coefficient of selection of <italic>SMN1</italic> deleted homozygotes is almost one. Therefore, extrapolation of Hardy-Weinberg equation to calculate the prevalence of <italic>SMN1</italic> deleted homozygotes in a population seems to be unreasonable. Nevertheless, if ignoring this potential bias, the disease prevalence of <italic>SMN1</italic> deleted homozygotes calculated by Hardy-Weinberg equation was 1/8,496 in Koreans. The estimated prevalence was also not much different from those of other European countries. Since there was no available information of SMA prevalence in East Asian countries including Korea, estimated prevalence presented in this study would be valuable for pursuing SMA pathogenesis and genetic counseling.</p><p>The <italic>SMN2</italic>, highly homologous gene of <italic>SMN1</italic>, is a well-established disease-modifying gene for SMA and has been shown to decrease the severity of type I-III SMA in gene dosage analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). The copy number of <italic>SMN2</italic> also correlates with longer survival of individuals affected with type I SMA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). Thus, the quantitative analysis of <italic>SMN2</italic> gene enables it possible to predict that an infant with homozygous deletion of <italic>SMN1</italic> develop type I, II or III SMA. Although we did not carry out the assay of <italic>SMN2</italic> gene in the present study, our real-time quantitative PCR analysis could produce sufficient results.</p><p>In conclusion, we detected <italic>SMN1</italic> deletion carriers in a general population and calculated the prevalence as the advantages of real-time PCR with SYBR Green I. With relatively high frequency of SMA compared with other autosomal recessive disorders, the carrier detection method using real-time PCR could be a useful tool for genetic counseling.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of spinal muscular atrophies</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1980</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>919</fpage><lpage>922</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6103267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gnetic testing and risk assessment for spinal muscular atrophy (SMA)</article-title><source>Hum Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12436240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cusin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Clermont</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000e9;rard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chantereau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Elion</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of SMN1 deletion and duplication in carrier and normal populations: implication for genetic counseling</article-title><source>J Med Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>e39</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12676912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munsat</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Meeting report: International SMA Consortium meeting</article-title><source>Neuromuscul Disord</source><year>1992</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1300191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Burglen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Reboullet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Clermont</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Burlet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Viollet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Benichou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Millasseau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeviani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Paslier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Frezal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissenbach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Munnich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Melki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of a spinal muscular atrophy-determining gene</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7813012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000fc;rglen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Clermont</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Burlet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Viollet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Munnich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Melki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and organization of the human survival motor neurone (SMN) gene</article-title><source>Genomics</source><year>1996</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8838816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahnen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Androphy</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single nucleotide in the SMN gene regulates splicing and is responsible for spinal muscular atrophy</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>6307</fpage><lpage>6311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10339583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monani</surname><given-names>UR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Androphy</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Burghes</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single nucleotide difference that alters splicing patterns distinguishes the SMA gene SMN1 from the copy gene SMN2</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>1999</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1177</fpage><lpage>1183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10369862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An Update of the mutation spectrum of the survival motor neuron gene (SMN1) in autosomal recessive spinal muscular atrophy (SMA)</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><year>2000</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10679938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deletion of SMN and NAIP genes in Korean patients with spinal muscular atrophy</article-title><source>J Korean Med Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10719817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McAndrew</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Simard</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rochette</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Burghes</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of proximal spinal muscular atrophy carriers and patients by analyses of SMNT and SMNC copy number</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>1411</fpage><lpage>1422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9199562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000e9;rard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthijs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Evrard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerard-Blanluet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandchamp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Elion</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genotype determination at the survival motor neuron locus in a normal population and SMA carriers using competitive PCR and primer extension</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><year>2000</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10980532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheffer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobben</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mensink</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Stulp</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Steege</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Buys</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SMA carrier testing-validation of hemizygous SMN exon 7 deletion test for the identification of proximal spinal muscular atrophy carriers and patients with a single allele deletion</article-title><source>Eur J Hum Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10757638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Valero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>del Castillo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Chico</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic study of SMA patients without homozygous SMN1 deletions: identification of compound heterozygotes and characterisation of novel intragenic SMN1 deletions</article-title><source>Hum Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11935338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feldk&#x000f6;tter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarzer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wienker</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative analyses of SMN1 and SMN2 based on real-time LightCycler PCR: fast and highly reliable carrier testing and prediction of severity of spinal muscular atrophy</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11791208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anhuf</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Eggermann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudnik-Sch&#x000f6;neborn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zerres</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of SMN1 and SMN2 copy number using TaqMan&#x02122;, Technology</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12815596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lack of evidence for contribution of Glu298Asp (G894T) polymorphism of endothelial nitric oxide synthase gene to plasma nitric oxide levels</article-title><source>Thromb Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12431478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aarskog</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vedeler</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction. A new method that detects both the peripheral myelin protein22 duplication in Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 1A disease and the peripheral myelin protein 22 deletion in hereditary neuropathy with liability to pressure palsies</article-title><source>Hum Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11140948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Herz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wetter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moskau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahnen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudnik-Sch&#x000f6;neborn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wienker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zerres</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative analysis of survival motor neuron copies: identification of subtle SMN1 mutations in patients with spinal muscular atrophy, genotype-phenotype correlation, and implications for genetic counseling</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>1999</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1340</fpage><lpage>1356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10205265</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Real-time amplification plots of triplicate <italic>SMN1</italic> and albumin of: (<bold>A</bold>) healthy normal control (&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct ratio 1.04, SD <italic>SMN1</italic> 0.09, SD albumin 0.01); (<bold>B</bold>) carrier with one <italic>SMN1</italic> copy (&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct ratio 0.5, SD <italic>SMN1</italic> 0.01, SD albumin 0.14); (<bold>C</bold>) patients with SMA of homozygous absence of <italic>SMN1</italic> (&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct ratio 0.00, SD albumin 0.14, no amplification of <italic>SMN1</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-19-870-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Identification of specificity of <italic>SMN1</italic> primers in three SMA families and a normal individual by multiplex PCR with <italic>COL1A1</italic>. P, patient; F, father; M, Mother.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-19-870-g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Real-time quantitative analysis of <italic>SMN1</italic> gene copy number using a comparative Ct method (&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct ratio) in patients, carriers, and normal individuals</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-19-870-i001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>SD, standard deviation; CV, coefficient of variation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><italic>SMN1</italic> gene copy numbers in Korean population</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-19-870-i002"/></table-wrap></floats-group></article>
