<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8688345</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2074572</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetic profile and clinical efficacy of a once-daily ondansetron suppository in cyclophosphamide-induced emesis: a double blind comparative study with ondansetron tablets.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beijnen</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Tellingen</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schellens</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Boer-Dennert</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Verweij</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Medical Oncology, Rotterdam Cancer Institute, The Netherlands.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>74</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><abstract><p>We investigated the pharmacokinetic profile and the efficacy of ondansetron (day 1) given as 16 mg suppository once a day, as compared with ondansetron 8 mg tablets twice daily, in patients receiving moderately emetogenic chemotherapy. The study was primarily aimed at investigating the pharmacokinetics and was part of a large multinational, randomised, double-blind, double-dummy efficacy trial. Pharmacokinetic data were obtained in a total of 20 patients, 11 of whom had received a suppository containing ondansetron, and nine patients had received the oral formulation. The median area under the plasma concentration curve (AUC) obtained with the oral formulation was 226 ng ml-1h-1 (range 91-750), and the median maximum plasma level (Cmax) was 50.5 ng ml-1 (range 24.7-199.6) after a dose of 8 mg. For the ondansetron suppository the median AUC was 140 ng ml-1h-1 range (77-405) and the median Cmax was 17.1 ng ml-1 (range 13-48.3) after a dose of 16 mg. The systemic exposure after correction for the dose difference after the suppository was on average 70% lower than after the tablet. The median time to reach the maximum level (Tmax) was 60 min (range 28-120) with the oral formulation and 209 min (range 90-420) with the suppository. For both the tablet and suppository, there was no apparent relationship between either Cmax or AUC, and efficacy. Although the patient numbers were too small for a formal exposure-response relationship to be derived, the slightly poorer pharmacokinetic performance of the suppository did not appear to be associated with a lessening of control of emesis following chemotherapy. The study demonstrates that the pharmacokinetic analysis of a once-daily 16 mg ondansetron suppository results in appropriate plasma concentrations and AUC, and that this rectal formulation is effective in the protection against nausea and vomiting associated with cyclophosphamide chemotherapy. This formulation will provide a useful alternative to the currently available oral formulation.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00018-0163.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="323" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00018-0164.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="324" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00018-0165.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="325" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00018-0166.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="326" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

