<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7964515</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2191778</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">95053780</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>CD30 expression by CD8+ T cells producing type 2 helper cytokines. Evidence for large numbers of CD8+CD30+ T cell clones in human immunodeficiency virus infection</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>1994</year></pub-date><volume>180</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2407</fpage><lpage>2411</lpage><permissions></permissions><abstract><p>A large panel of CD8+ T cell clones generated from peripheral blood lymphocytes (PBL) of healthy donors or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-infected individuals were assessed for both cytokine secretion profile and CD30 expression and release. The great majority of CD8+ T cell clones generated from healthy individuals showed the ability to produce interferon gamma (IFN-gamma), but not interleukin 4 (IL-4), and none of them either expressed membrane CD30 or released substantial amounts of soluble CD30 (sCD30) in their supernatant. In contrast, high numbers of CD8+ T cell clones generated from HIV-infected individuals, which produced IL-4 (and IL-5) in addition to IFN-gamma or IL-4 (and IL- 5) alone, expressed membrane CD30 and released detectable amounts of sCD30 in their supernatants. Indeed, CD30 expression appeared to be positively correlated with the ability of CD8+ T cell clones to produce IL-4 and IL-5 and inversely correlated with their ability to produce IFN-gamma, whereas no correlation between CD30 expression and production of IL-10 was observed. These data suggest that CD30 is a marker for CD8+ T cells that have switched to the production of type 2 helper cytokines.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>


