<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">brjcancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9231927</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2223923</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Physical and psychosocial outcomes in cancer patients: a comparison of different age groups.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Greimel</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Padilla</surname><given-names>G. V.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>University of Gatz, Austria.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>1997</year></pub-date><volume>76</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><abstract><p>In a cross-sectional study, we investigated the relationship between age, physical health, social and economic resources, functional status, activities of daily living (ADL) and disease-related variables of 227 patients with cancer. Using multidimensional outcome measures we examined age differences in three age groups (&#x0003c; 45, 46-65, &#x0003e; 65 years) and identified predictors of performing ADL. The results indicated that older patients have outcomes similar to those of younger patients. There were no significant differences in quality of life, performance status and physical health among the three age groups. The only areas where age-related differences were found were co-morbidity and cancer-related impairments. Patients aged 45-65 years and patients 65 years and older reported a higher level of co-morbidity and more cancer-related impairments than those aged 45 and younger. Although older patients had higher co-morbidity, they showed similar Karnofsky Performance Status (KPS) scores to those of their younger counterparts. The regression analysis revealed social resources, self-reported health, performance status and complexity of care as significant predictors of patients' ADL, but not age, co-morbidity or severity of treatment. The findings support the conclusion that differences in performing ADL between younger and older patients with cancer are minimal and tend to be due to co-morbidity. Thus, treatment should be decided by a patient's physical health rather than by age.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00166-0115.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="251" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00166-0116.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="252" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00166-0117.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="253" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00166-0118.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="254" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00166-0119.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="255" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

