<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8883420</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2075933</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A randomised phase II study of sialyl-Tn and DETOX-B adjuvant with or without cyclophosphamide pretreatment for the active specific immunotherapy of breast cancer.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Towlson</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reddish</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Longenecker</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor-Papadimitriou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rubens</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>ICRF Clinical Oncology Unit, Guy's Hospital, London.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>74</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1292</fpage><lpage>1296</lpage><abstract><p>Studies in animal models of mouse mammary carcinoma have shown that ovine submaxillary mucin, which carries multiple sialyl-Tn (STn) epitopes, is effective in stimulating an immune response and inhibiting tumour growth. In similar studies using carbohydrate antigens, pretreatment with low-dose cyclophosphamide has been shown to be important in modulating the immune response to antigen possibly by inhibiting suppresser T-cell activity. In a clinical trial assessing the efficacy and toxicity of synthetic STn, patients with metastatic breast cancer were randomised to receive 100 micrograms STn linked to keyhole limpet haemocyanin (KLH) with DETOX-B adjuvant given by subcutaneous injection at weeks 0, 2, 5 and 9 with or without low-dose cyclophosphamide (CTX, 300 mg m-2) pretreatment, 3 days before the start of immunotherapy. Patients with responding or stable disease after the first four injections were eligible to receive STn-KLH at 4 week intervals. The main toxicity noted was the development of subcutaneous granulomata at injection sites. Of 23 patients randomised, 18 received four injections, 5 patients having developed progressive disease during the initial 12 week period. Two minor responses were noted in the 18 patients who received four active specific immunotherapy (ASI) injections and a further five patients had stable disease. Six patients continued ASI at 4 week intervals and a partial response was noted in a patient who had previously had stable disease. All patients developed IgG and IgM responses to sialyl-Tn and levels of IgM antibodies were significantly higher in those patients who were pretreated with CTX. Measurable tumour responses have been recorded following ASI with STn-KLH plus DETOX and the immunomodulatory properties of low-dose CTX have been confirmed.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00024-0140.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1292" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00024-0141.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1293" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00024-0142.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1294" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00024-0143.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1295" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00024-0144.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1296" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

