<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">2871860</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2001430</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A trial of chemotherapy in patients with osteosarcoma (a report to the Medical Research Council by their Working Party on Bone Sarcoma.</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>1986</year></pub-date><volume>53</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><abstract><p>Two hundred and thirty five patients with osteosarcoma, aged less than 40 years, and treated by amputation or radiotherapy, were entered in a randomised trial of two forms of adjuvant chemotherapy. A two drug regimen, namely vincristine 2 mg m-2 (maximum 2mg) followed by methotrexate 200 mgm-2, given every three weeks, was compared with a three drug regimen, comprising the same vincristine-methotrexate treatment, alternating every three weeks with doxorubicin 60 mg m-2. Both regimens were continued for 54 weeks. Forty-one patients were excluded, most because of inadequate histology, leaving 194 patients for analysis. One hundred and seventy of these had immediate amputation, 14 were treated by a policy of radiotherapy, with surgery delayed for 9 months, provided no distant metastases had appeared, and 10 by a policy of radiotherapy only. Patients have been followed-up for between 26 and 94 months after entry to the trial. The 2- and 5-year survival rates were 48% and 27%. No significant difference in survival was observed between the two regimens, but toxicity was less with the two drug regimen.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00528-0059.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="513" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00528-0060.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="514" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00528-0061.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="515" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00528-0062.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="516" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00528-0063.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="517" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00528-0064.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="518" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

