<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7981071</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2033669</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Methylprednisolone enhances the efficacy of ondansetron in acute and delayed cisplatin-induced emesis over at least three cycles. Ondansetron Study Group.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chevallier</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Paillarse</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Centre Anti-Canc&#x000e9;reux Henri Becquerel, Rouen, France.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>1994</year></pub-date><volume>70</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1171</fpage><lpage>1175</lpage><abstract><p>This double-blind multicentre study has been carried out in order to confirm the improvement of ondansetron's antiemetic efficacy when combined with a corticosteroid and to determine whether this increased efficacy is maintained over three chemotherapy courses. One hundred and two patients receiving their first course of cisplatin (50-120 mg m-2)-containing chemotherapy were randomised to receive one of the two following treatments: 8 mg OND i.v. injection and 120 mg MPD i.v. injection before chemotherapy, followed 8-12 h later by an 8 mg OND tablet and a 16 mg MPD tablet (oral treatment administered twice daily for 3-5 days): or 8 mg OND plus placebo i.v. injection before chemotherapy, followed by 8-12 h later by an 8 mg OND tablet and placebo p.o. (oral treatment administered twice daily for 3-5 days). The number of emetic episodes (EEs = vomits + retches) and the grade of nausea were recorded. Of the 101 patients studied (efficacy analysis), complete or major control (0-2 EEs) was experienced in 90.4% of patients in the first 24 h in the OND/MPD group compared with 71.4% of patients in the OND group during the first course. This difference in favour of OND/MPD was noted over the three courses and is statistically significant. In the control of delayed emesis (worst day between days 2 and 6) there is a trend in favour of the OND/MDP group during the first course [56.2% vs 43.2% for complete response (no emetic episodes)] which was statistically significant on courses 2 and 3. The global antiemetic control over the course was always in favour of OND/MPD, which leads to a better efficacy maintained over the three courses. Both treatments were well tolerated. The results of this study confirm the increased antimetic efficacy of ondansetron and methylprednisolone in combination in cisplatin-induced acute and delayed emesis which led to a better maintained efficacy over three repeated chemotherapy courses.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00058-0139.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1171" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00058-0140.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1172" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00058-0141.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1173" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00058-0142.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1174" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00058-0143.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1175" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

