<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8519676</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2034079</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Carboplatin combined with amifostine, a bone marrow protectant, in the treatment of non-small-cell lung cancer: a randomised phase II study.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Betticher</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ranson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meely</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oster</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thatcher</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>CRC Department of Medical Oncology, Christie and Wythenshawe Hospitals, Manchester, UK.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>1995</year></pub-date><volume>72</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1551</fpage><lpage>1555</lpage><abstract><p>Amifostine (WR-2721), a thiol compound, has been shown to protect normal tissue from alkylating agents and cisplatin-induced toxicity without loss of anti-tumour effects. To confirm this result, we conducted a phase II randomised trial to determine if the addition of amifostine reduces the toxicity of carboplatin without loss of anti-tumour activity in patients with inoperable non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC). After the first course of carboplatin (600 mg m-2 i.v. infusion), 21 patients were randomised to receive three cycles of carboplatin alone (C arm) or three infusions of amifostine at 910 mg m-2 (CA arm) at 28 day intervals. The amifostine was given 20 min before and at 2 and 4 h after carboplatin. Since the 910 mg m-2 amifostine infusion led to hypotension in six patients, the dosage was reduced by 25%, to 683 mg m-2 t.i.d., in the other four patients. Amifostine was well tolerated at this dose level. Five patients in the CA arm and three in the C arm had their planned treatment discontinued owing to progressive disease (n = 3), amifostine side-effects (hypotension, sneezing and sickness, n = 4), and carboplatin-induced thrombocytopenia (n = 1). Bone marrow and renal function at study entry and after the first course of carboplatin before randomisation were similar in both treatment arms. Twenty courses of carboplatin+amifostine have been compared with 25 courses of carboplatin alone. Although there was no statistically significant difference with respect to haematological values comparing both arms, the median time to platelet recovery (&#x0003e; 100 x 10(9) l-1) (13.5 days vs 21 days; P = 0.04) and the need for hospitalisation for i.v. antibiotic and other supportive treatment tended to be reduced in the CA arm (0/20 vs 6/25 patient courses; P = 0.06). Response rates and median survival (14 vs 9 months) were no different, excluding tumour protection activity by amifostine. These results with a small number of patients suggest that amifostine given with carboplatin may reduce the duration of thrombocytopenia and hospitalisation.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00046-0217.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1551" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00046-0218.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1552" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00046-0219.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1553" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00046-0220.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1554" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00046-0221.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1555" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

