<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">brjcancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9649150</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2150390</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>High-dose cyclosporin with etoposide--toxicity and pharmacokinetic interaction in children with solid tumours.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bisogno</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cowie</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>H. D.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pinkerton</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Children's Department, Royal Marsden NHS Trust/Institute of Cancer Research, Sutton, Surrey, UK.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>77</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2304</fpage><lpage>2309</lpage><abstract><p>The tolerability, anti-tumour activity and pharmacokinetic interaction of high-dose intravenous cyclosporin combined with intravenous etoposide was evaluated in children. Eighteen patients with recurrent or refractory tumours, all of whom had previously received etoposide, were treated with a combination of high-dose cyclosporin and etoposide. In 13, cyclosporin was given as a continuous infusion (15 mg kg(-1) per 24 h for 60 h) and in five a short 3-hour infusion of 30 mg kg(-1) day(-1) on three consecutive days. Pharmacokinetic profiles of etoposide were determined with and without cyclosporin. Cyclosporin levels ranged from 1359 to 4835 ng ml(-1) and cyclosporin increased the median area under the concentration time for etoposide curve from 7.2 to 12.5 mg ml(-1) min. The major toxicity was acute with varying forms of hypersensitivity reactions. In four cases this was severe. Hyperbilirubinaemia was present in 25 of 32 courses but was of short duration. In 14 courses, creatinine and/or urea was elevated, but was also transient. Significant hypertension was seen in six courses. Four of 17 patients evaluable for response obtained a partial response and one showed stable disease. It is concluded that in children given the combination of high-dose cyclosporin and etoposide, the etoposide dose should be halved in order to achieve an area under the drug concentration-time curve similar to that with etoposide alone. A continuous infusion schedule of cyclosporin is better tolerated during the period of administration but is associated with similar hepatic and renal dysfunction to a short schedule. The 24% response rate in children who had previously received etoposide suggests that this may be an effective method of enhancing drug sensitivity and further phase II evaluation is justified.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00088-0250.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="2304" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00088-0251.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="2305" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00088-0252.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="2306" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00088-0253.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="2307" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00088-0254.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="2308" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00088-0255.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="2309" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

