<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7964484</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2191805</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">95053741</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The T helper cell response in Lyme arthritis: differential recognition of Borrelia burgdorferi outer surface protein A in patients with treatment-resistant or treatment-responsive Lyme arthritis</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>1994</year></pub-date><volume>180</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2069</fpage><lpage>2078</lpage><permissions></permissions><abstract><p>The host response to Borrelia burgdorferi is likely to play a role in the pathogenesis of Lyme arthritis. Whereas most patients with Lyme arthritis can be cured with antibiotic therapy, approximately 10% of the patients have persistent arthritis for months or even several years after antibiotic treatment. In this study, we tested the hypothesis that the T cell response to one or more antigens of B. burgdorferi is different in patients with treatment-responsive or treatment-resistant Lyme arthritis. For this purpose, 313 B. burgdorferi-specific T cell lines were derived from the synovial fluid or peripheral blood of four patients with treatment-responsive Lyme arthritis and five patients with treatment-resistant arthritis. 87 T cell lines from treatment- responsive Lyme arthritis and 112 lines from the treatment-resistant group were examined for the recognition of five recombinant. B. burgdorferi proteins: outer surface proteins A (OspA), B, C, p39, and p93. In both groups of patients, the T cell lines frequently recognized OspB, and only occasionally recognized OspC, p39, and p93. In contrast, OspA was preferentially recognized by T cell lines from patients with treatment-resistant arthritis, but only rarely recognized by T cell lines from patients with treatment-responsive arthritis (odds ratio 28.4, 95% confidence interval 9.2-87.8, p &#x0003c; 0.005). These results are compatible with the hypothesis that the T cell response to B. burgdorferi OspA is involved in the pathogenesis of treatment-resistant Lyme arthritis.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>


