<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7819058</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2033463</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A randomised trial of octreotide vs best supportive care only in advanced gastrointestinal cancer patients refractory to chemotherapy.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cascinu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Del Ferro</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Servizio di Oncologia, Ospedali Riuniti, Pesaro, Italy.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>1995</year></pub-date><volume>71</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><abstract><p>Octreotide, a somatostatin analogue, has been shown to inhibit the growth of gastrointestinal cancers in vitro and in vivo. To assess the anti-tumour effect of octreotide, we performed a randomised trial comparing octreotide with best supportive care in advanced gastrointestinal cancer patients refractory to chemotherapy. A total of 107 patients with advanced gastrointestinal cancer refractory to chemotherapy were randomised to receive octreotide at the dose of 200 micrograms three times a day for 5 days a week, or the best supportive care only. The primary outcome variable was the survival duration. Response rate was an outcome variable of secondary importance. Fifty-five patients (15 stomach, 16 pancreas, 24 colon-rectum) received octreotide, while 52 (14 stomach, 16 pancreas, 22 colon-rectum) received the best supportive care. Patients treated with octreotide had a significant advantage in duration of survival with a median survival time of 20 weeks vs 11 in the control group (P &#x0003c; 0.0001). This advantage was present also considering the survival data for each tumour group. Twenty-five patients (45%) given octreotide showed stable disease vs only eight (15%) in the control group (P &#x0003c; 0.001). In conclusion, octreotide therapy seems to confer a survival benefit in advanced gastrointestinal cancer patients refractory to chemotherapy. Additional studies will be needed to confirm these results and to clarify other questions about dose and schedule of octreotide.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00047-0099.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="97" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00047-0100.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="98" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00047-0101.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="99" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00047-0102.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="100" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00047-0103.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="101" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

