<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8912549</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2074776</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A phase I clinical trial of imiquimod, an oral interferon inducer, administered daily.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Witt</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Medicine, Royal Marsden Hospital, London, UK.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>74</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1482</fpage><lpage>1486</lpage><abstract><p>Imiquimod is an orally active interferon inducer with anti-tumour activity in experimental animals. In this study the tolerability, toxicity and biological effects of daily oral imiquimod administration were investigated in 21 patients with refractory cancer. Patients were treated with doses of 25 mg, 50 mg, 100 mg or 200 mg on a projected 112 day course. Only three patients completed the course, all at the 50 mg dose. Treatment toxicities were dose related and mainly comprised flu-like symptoms, nausea and lymphopenia. Of the 21 patients, five received dose reductions and in five treatment was discontinued because of treatment-related toxicity. The biological activity of imiquimod was confirmed by significant and sustained rises in peripheral blood mononuclear cell (PBMC) 2-5A synthetase (2-5AS) levels at all doses. At 100 mg and 200 mg these occurred within the first 24 h of administration. Levels of neopterin and beta 2-microglobulin (beta 2M) were also significantly elevated when assessed after three weeks' treatment. Interferon production was not demonstrated within the first 24 h of the initial dose but, following repeated doses, ten of the patients developed detectable serum interferon concentrations with a maximum value of 5600 IU ml-1 recorded. Administration of imiquimod did not have any significant effect on serum levels of tumour necrosis factor (TNF) or interleukin 1 (IL-1), nor did it lead to development of detectable levels of antibodies to interferon. One mixed clinical response was observed after 4 weeks' treatment at 100 mg in a patient with renal cell cancer. Daily administration of imiquimod causes activation of the interferon production system but at higher doses results in unacceptable toxicity. Further investigation of imiquimod as an interferon-inducing agent in cancer patients is suggested at either the lower dose levels or employing alternative dosing schedules.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00025-0158.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1482" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00025-0159.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1483" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00025-0160.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1484" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00025-0161.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1485" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00025-0162.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1486" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

