<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><!-- Original-type: ra--><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11720429</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2363931</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6692070</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1054/bjoc.2001.2070</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Regular Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Somatostatin-receptor scintigraphy for staging and follow-up of patients with extraintestinal marginal zone B-cell lymphoma of the mucosa associated lymphoid tissue (MALT)-type</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raderer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Traub</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Formanek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Virgolini</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d6;sterreicher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fiebiger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Penz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000e4;ger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pont</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kurtaran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Departments of Internal Medicine I, <label>4</label>Departments of Internal Medicine IV, <label>2</label>Nuclear Medicine, <label>3</label>Otorhinolaryngology, <label>5</label>Clinical Pathology, University of Vienna</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Internal Medicine V, Kaiser Franz Josef Spital</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>Nuclear Medicine, KH Lainz, Vienna, Austria</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>85</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1462</fpage><lpage>1466</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>03</month><year>2001</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>07</month><year>2001</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>07</month><year>2001</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright 2001, Cancer Research Campaign</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2001</copyright-year><permissions><copyright-holder>Cancer Research Campaign</copyright-holder></permissions><abstract><p>The majority of lymphomas of the mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue (MALT)-type arise in the stomach, but extragastric locations are also frequently encountered. Due to previous results indicating that somatostatin receptor (SSTR)-expression distinguishes between gastric and extragastric MALT-type lymphoma, we have initiated a study to evaluate the role of SSTR-scintigraphy for staging and follow-up of patients with extragastric manifestations of MALT-type lymphoma. A total of 30 consecutive patients, including 24 with primary extragastric MALT-type lymphoma, 5 patients with dissemination to extragastric sites (including colon, lung, parotid, ocular adnexa and breast) following an initial gastric MALT-lymphoma and one patient with spread to stomach, lung and lymph nodes following parotid lymphoma were prospectively studied. All patients had histologically verified MALT-type lymphoma: 2 patients had lymphoma presenting in the lung, 9 in the ocular adnexa, 7 had lymphomas in the parotid, 2 patients had disease located in the breast, 3 patients had lymph-node relapse following MALT-type lymphoma of the parotid, the lacrimal gland and the thyroid, and 1 had primary MALT-lymphoma of the liver. All patients underwent SSTR-scintigraphy using <sup>111</sup>In-DTPA-D-Phe<sup>1</sup>-Octreotide (<sup>111</sup>In-OCT) before initiation of therapy, while 13 also had a second scan after treatment. The results of gamma camera imaging were compared to conventional staging. No positive scans could be obtained in patients with dissemination following gastric lymphoma, while all patients with primary extragastric lymphoma had positive scans at the site of histologically documented involvement before initiation of therapy. In addition, also the patient with secondary spread to stomach, lung and lymph nodes was positive in all documented lymphoma sites. In one patient, focal tracer uptake in projection to the maxillary sinus was documented, which was bioptically verified as inflammation. In the scans performed after therapy, focal tracer accumulation in the left orbit indicated persistance of disease following irradiation in one patient with otherwise negative work-up, which was verified by MRI and biopsy 6 months later. In another patient, a positive scan indicated disease relapse in the lacrimal gland 9 months before clinical verification by means of ultrasound. In one patient, a focus not present in the pretherapeutic scan was found in the ethmoidal sinus, corresponding to a hyperplastic polyp. Both SST-scan as well as CT indicated disease persistance in one case, while negative scans corresponding to complete remission as judged by conventional staging were obtained following therapy in the remaining patients, and absence of relapse has been confirmed for a median follow-up of 2 years. These results indicate that <sup>111</sup>In-OCT is an excellent tool for staging and non-invasive therapy-monitoring in extragastric MALT-type lymphomas. These data further confirm our initial finding that gastric MALT-type lymphomas do not express relevant amounts of respective SSTR, and that SSTR-scanning is able to distinguish between gastric vs extragastric origin of MALT-type lymphoma irrespective of the site of presentation.&#x000a9; 2001 Cancer Research Campaign&#x02002;&#x02002;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.bjcancer.com">http://www.bjcancer.com</ext-link></p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>somatostatin</kwd><kwd>extraintestinal MALT-lymphoma</kwd><kwd>scintigraphy</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front></article>


