<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><!-- Original-type: ra--><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11720428</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2363962</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6692013</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1054/bjoc.2001.2013</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Regular Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Accelerated cisplatin and high-dose epirubicin with G-CSF support in patients with relapsed non-small-cell lung cancer: feasibility and efficacy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huisman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Biesma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Postmus</surname><given-names>P E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Giaccone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schramel</surname><given-names>F M N H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>E F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Pulmonary Diseases, University Hospital Vrije Universiteit, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Pulmonary Diseases, Bosch Medisch Centrum, Den Bosch, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Medical Oncology, University Hospital Vrije Universiteit, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Pulmonary Diseases, St Antonius Hospital, Nieuwegein, The Netherlands</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>85</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1456</fpage><lpage>1461</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>03</month><year>2001</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>03</day><month>06</month><year>2001</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>07</month><year>2001</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright 2001, Cancer Research Campaign</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2001</copyright-year><permissions><copyright-holder>Cancer Research Campaign</copyright-holder></permissions><abstract><p>The purpose of this study is to determine whether it is feasible to administer high-dose epirubicin (135&#x02008;mg m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) combined with a fixed dose of cisplatin every 2 weeks with G-CSF support in patients with metastatic non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC). Subsequently, the efficacy of the recommended dose of this regimen was tested in a phase II study in patients with relapsed NSCLC. In the initial feasibility study at least 6 patients were entered at each of the 4 dose levels tested. A fixed dose of cisplatin 60&#x02008;mg m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>was given. Epirubicin was administered at 120&#x02008;mg&#x02008;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>on dose level 1, 135&#x02008;mg&#x02008;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>on dose level 2 and 3 and 135&#x02008;mg m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>on dose level 4. Patients treated at dose level 3 and 4 received G-CSF support on days 3&#x02013;12. Cycles were repeated every 3 weeks on the first 3 dose levels and every 2 weeks on the fourth dose level. A total of 27 patients were then treated on dose level 4, which appeared to be feasible in the initial study. In the initial study, a total of 86 courses were administered. Haematological toxicity was the principal side effect. None of the patients encountered dose-limiting toxicity in the first course, which confirmed that epirubicin 135&#x02008;mg m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>could be combined with cisplatin 60&#x02008;mg m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>and accelerated by G-CSF support to a 14-day-schedule. In the subsequent phase II study with this schedule, 89 courses were administered. The relative dose intensity of cisplatin and epirubicin was 0.90 and 0.91, respectively. Myelosuppression was frequent with 70&#x00025; and 63&#x00025; of patients experiencing WHO grade III or IV leukocytopenia and thrombocytopenia, respectively. 6 cases of febrile neutropenia were observed, with 2 treatment-related deaths. Non-haematological toxicity consisted mainly of nausea and vomiting, which was grade III in 22&#x00025; of patients. Renal toxicity grade I and II occurred in 37&#x00025; and 4&#x00025; of patients, respectively. 55&#x00025; of these patients had received prior cisplatin-containing chemotherapy. On an intention-to-treat basis 9 partial responses were recorded in 27 patients (33&#x00025;; 95&#x00025; confidence interval, 15&#x00025;&#x02013;51&#x00025;). Accelerated cisplatin and high-dose epirubicin with G-CSF support is a feasible and promising regimen in relapsed NSCLC. Myelosuppression limits the use of this regimen in the second-line setting to a selected group of patients with a good performance status. Since the activity of this regimen is encouraging, it is probably best studied in untreated patients.&#x000a9; 2001 Cancer Research Campaign&#x02002;&#x02002;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.bjcancer.com">http://www.bjcancer.com</ext-link></p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>non-small-cell lung cancer</kwd><kwd>chemotherapy</kwd><kwd>second-line</kwd><kwd>cisplatin</kwd><kwd>epirubicin</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front></article>


