<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Clin Pract</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijcp</journal-id><journal-title>International Journal of Clinical Practice</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1368-5031</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1742-1241</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17877652</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2040191</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-1241.2007.01500.x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Once-daily OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone for the management of chronic nonmalignant pain: a dose-conversion and titration study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rauck</surname><given-names>R L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moulin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thipphawong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tudor</surname><given-names>I C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>San Diego Medical Center, University of California</institution><addr-line>La Jolla, CA, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Wake Forest University School of Medicine, The Center for Clinical Research, Carolinas Pain Institute</institution><addr-line>Winston-Salem, NC, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>London Regional Cancer Program</institution><addr-line>London, ON, Canada</addr-line></aff><aff id="au4"><label>4</label><institution>ALZA Corporation</institution><addr-line>Mountain View, CA, USA</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> John Thipphawong, ALZA Corporation, 1900 Charleston Road, Mountain View, CA 94039, USA Tel.: + 650 564 5196 Fax: + 650 564 3506 Email: <email>jthippha@alzus.jnj.com</email></corresp><fn><p><bold>Disclosures</bold> Mark Wallace was a paid consultant for the sponsor of this study. Richard Rauck was a paid consultant for the sponsor of this study. Dwight Moulin has received research grant funding from Pfizer, Purdue Pharma and Janssen-Ortho. He has received honoraria for consultations and speaker fees for educational presentations from Pfizer, Purdue Pharma, Merck-Frosst, Janssen-Ortho and Bayer. John Thipphawong, Sarita Khanna and Iulia Cristina Tudor are employees of ALZA Corporation.</p><p>Clinical Trial Registration Identifier: NCT00410644.</p><p>Re-use of this article is permitted in accordance with the Creative Commons Deed, Attribution 2.5, which does not permit commercial exploitation.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>61</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1671</fpage><lpage>1676</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><month>5</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="received"><month>6</month><year>2007</year></date></history><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 ALZA Corporation Journal compilation 2007 Blackwell Publishing Ltd</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><abstract><sec><title>Summary</title></sec><sec><title>Background:</title><p>The use of opioid analgesics for patients with chronic nonmalignant pain is becoming more widely accepted, and long-acting formulations are an important treatment option.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>To assess conversion to extended-release OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone from previous stable opioid agonist therapy in patients with chronic nonmalignant pain of moderate-to-severe intensity.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>In this open-label multicentre trial, patients were stabilised on their previous opioid therapy before being switched to OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone at a ratio of 5 : 1 (morphine sulphate equivalent to hydromorphone hydrochloride). The OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone dose was titrated over 3&#x02013;16 days to achieve effective analgesia, and maintenance treatment continued for 14 days.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Study medication was received by 336 patients; 66% completed all study phases. Stabilisation of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone was achieved by 94.6% of patients, the majority in two or fewer titration steps (mean time, 4.2 days). Mean pain intensity scores, as determined by the Brief Pain Inventory, decreased during OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone treatment (p &#x02264; 0.001). The percentage of patients rating their pain relief as &#x02018;good&#x02019; or &#x02018;complete&#x02019; increased, and the use of rescue analgesics for breakthrough pain decreased. The interference of pain with everyday activities (e.g. walking or work), and the effects on mood and enjoyment of life, also improved during the study (all p &#x0003c; 0.001). OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone was well tolerated, and adverse events were those expected for opioid agonist therapy.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Patients with chronic nonmalignant pain who had been receiving opioid therapy easily underwent conversion to OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone, with no loss of efficacy or increase in adverse events.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text position="float"><sec><title>What's known</title><p>In contrast to immediate-release hydromorphone, OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone produces relatively constant steady-state concentrations for 24 h. Conversion from previous opioid therapy can be easily achieved without loss of pain control or increase in adverse events using a morphine equivalents : OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone conversion ratio of 5 : 1 (based on preliminary results from a pooled analysis of two open-label, repeated-dose studies; one in subjects with malignant pain and one in subjects with nonmalignant pain).</p></sec><sec><title>What's new</title><p>The current report presents final results of the individual study conducted in patients with nonmalignant pain. It demonstrates that conversion can be achieved without loss of pain control or increase in adverse events, and provides additional evidence of the safety and efficacy for the proposed 5 : 1 morphine equivalents : OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone conversion ratio.</p></sec></boxed-text><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Although the treatment of chronic pain with opioid agonists in cancer patients is widely accepted, the use of opioid analgesics for patients with nonmalignant pain has become widespread only in recent years, and remains controversial (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>). However, numerous studies have shown that opioid agonists can safely and effectively control chronic pain of moderate-to-severe intensity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>).</p><p>Hydromorphone is a hydrogenated semi-synthetic ketone of morphine that has been used for many years to treat moderate-to-severe cancer pain, for which it is regarded as an effective alternative to morphine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>). Hydromorphone is available as an oral formulation, but the short elimination half-life of this drug (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>) necessitates repeated dosing every 4&#x02013;6 h for effective around-the-clock pain control. This need for frequent dosing could lead to reductions in compliance, which in turn could negatively impact treatment outcomes and quality of life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). The introduction of long-acting opioid agonist formulations has provided an important treatment option for patients with chronic pain, and studies have shown that long-acting opioids can improve pain management and reduce opioid-related side effects in comparison to immediate-release (IR) formulations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>).</p><p>An OROS&#x000ae; formulation of hydromorphone was developed recently. It utilises OROS&#x000ae; Push-Pull&#x02122; osmotic pump technology (ALZA Corporation, Mountain View, CA) to release hydromorphone at a controlled rate for up to 24 h. Clinical pharmacokinetic analysis has shown that, in contrast to IR hydromorphone, OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone produces relatively constant steady-state concentrations for 24 h with much less peak-to-trough variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>).</p><p>The conversion of patients to OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone from previous opioid agonist treatment was evaluated in an open-label, repeated-dose study. Preliminary results were presented as part of a pooled analysis, with a second study of identical design performed in patients with chronic cancer pain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>). The current report presents final results of the individual study in patients with nonmalignant pain.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Study design</title><p>The study was an open-label, repeated-dose, single-treatment, multicentre trial conducted at 35 sites throughout the USA and Canada. Its protocol was approved by an Institutional Review Board at each site, and all patients provided written informed consent.</p><p>Before the administration of study medication, patients were stabilised on their previous opioid therapy for at least 3 days. Stabilisation was defined as &#x02265; 3 consecutive days when the total daily baseline opioid dose remained unchanged, with &#x02264; 3 doses of rescue medication required for breakthrough pain. Patients were permitted to receive combinations of opioid drugs during this phase, and nonopioid and adjuvant analgesics also were allowed.</p><p>When stabilised, patients were switched to OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone hydrochloride using a 5 : 1 conversion ratio of morphine sulphate equivalent to hydromorphone hydrochloride (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>), with no washout or overlap of previous opioid therapy and study medication. Patients stabilised on transdermal fentanyl were converted on the basis of 8 mg/day hydromorphone for each 25 &#x003bc;g/h of fentanyl, which conservatively approximates the 5 : 1 conversion ratio (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>). For all patients, the minimum starting dose of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone was 8 mg/day.</p><p>After the switch, OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone was titrated over a period of 3&#x02013;16 days. Each dose of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone was given for at least 2 days to ensure that steady-state blood levels of hydromorphone were achieved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>). If more than two doses (or 7 mg) of rescue medication (IR hydromorphone) were required in a 24-h period, the dose of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone was increased by 25 to 100%. Patients who did not achieve stable OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone dosing after 21 days were discontinued from the study. After stabilisation on OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone, patients entered a 14-day maintenance phase. Those who withdrew from the study had their OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone dose tapered over several days (50% reduction every 2 days) until discontinuation.</p><p>Patients were treated on an outpatient basis, with five study visits over the treatment period. Stabilisation of prior opioid therapy began at visit 1 (baseline evaluation). OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone titration started at visit 2, and OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone maintenance therapy began at visit 3. Visits 4 and 5 occurred at the midpoint and end of the maintenance phase, respectively.</p><p>During the study, IR hydromorphone could be prescribed as rescue medication for breakthrough pain, with the recommended dose generally ranging from 10% to 15% of the basic daily OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone dose. No other opioid medication was permitted after conversion; however, patients were allowed to use nonopioid and adjuvant analgesics.</p></sec><sec><title>Patients</title><p>Study patients were adults (&#x02265; 18 years of age) with chronic nonmalignant pain and stable analgesic requirements (daily opioid requirement of &#x02265; 45 mg morphine equivalents). Exclusion criteria included hypersensitivity to hydromorphone or other opioid agonists; gastrointestinal disorders that could affect the intake, absorption or transit of study medication; significant disorders of the central nervous system; respiratory compromise; risk of serious decrease in blood pressure with an opioid analgesic; significant organ or metabolic dysfunction; a history of drug or alcohol abuse; requirement for radiation treatment; pregnancy or lactation; and use of any investigational drug within 30 days of study initiation.</p></sec><sec><title>Assessments</title><p>The efficacy of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone was assessed using the Short Form of the Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>). Pain intensity (worst, least and average) over the previous 24 h was rated by patients on a scale of 0 (no pain) to 10 (pain as bad as you can imagine). Pain relief was rated on a scale of 0% (no relief) to 100% (complete relief). The degree to which pain interfered with general activity, mood, walking ability, normal work, relationships with others, sleep and enjoyment of life was rated on a scale of 0 (no interference) to 10 (complete interference). In addition, both patients and physicians rated the general effectiveness of study medication on a five-point scale (1, poor; 2, fair; 3, good; 4, very good; 5, excellent). Safety monitoring was performed by recording adverse events and study discontinuations throughout the trial. Patients also underwent physical examination at baseline and end-point.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Changes in mean BPI pain intensity, pain relief and pain interference ratings from visit 2 to end-point (or the last observation carried forward from visit 3 or 4 for patients who withdrew) were assessed using the Wilcoxon signed rank test. To detect the smallest differences in BPI ratings, a type I (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>) error of 0.05 was assumed. Statistical significance was set at p &#x02264; 0.05. No adjustment for multiple testing was applied.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Patients</title><p>Overall, 366 patients with chronic nonmalignant pain were enrolled; 336 of these received study medication (30 withdrew during the prior opioid stabilisation phase). The study was completed by 222 patients (66%); 94 (28%) discontinued during the titration phase and 20 (8%) during the maintenance phase. Patient disposition is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Figure 1</xref>, and baseline characteristics of treated patients are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and baseline characteristics of treated patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone (<italic>n</italic>=336)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#x000b1; SD age, years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.2 &#x000b1; 11.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Sex, <italic>n</italic> (%)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (45)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185 (55)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#x000b1; SD height (cm)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170.6 &#x000b1; 11.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#x000b1; SD weight (kg)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.4 &#x000b1; 22.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Type of pain, <italic>n</italic> (%)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Sympathetic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Musculoskeletal</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174 (52)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Neuropathic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134 (40)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Location of pain, <italic>n</italic> (%)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Back</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (58)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Limbs</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179 (53)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Face/head/neck</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (19)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Torso</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (17)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Previous opioid medication, <italic>n</italic> (%)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Codeine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Fentanyl</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Hydrocodone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (14)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Hydromorphone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Meperidine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Methadone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Morphine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (22)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Oxycodone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (40)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Propoxyphene</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean daily opioid requirement (mg)*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*Morphine equivalent at end of stabilisation phase.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Patient disposition</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijcp0061-1671-f1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone dosing</title><p>The overall mean &#x000b1; SD duration of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone treatment was 24.2 &#x000b1; 12.2 days, with 306 patients (91%) receiving study medication for more than 7 days and 143 patients (43%) receiving it for more than 25 days.</p><p>Three hundred and eighteen of the 336 treated patients (94.6%) achieved a stable dose of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone during the titration phase. Overall, the mean time to dose stabilisation was 4.2 &#x000b1; 2.12 days. Stabilisation was achieved in two or fewer titration steps by 87% of patients [no titration, <italic>n</italic> = 209 (66%); one or two titration steps, <italic>n</italic> = 82 (26%); <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Figure 2</xref>]. The mean &#x000b1; SD dose of prior opioid therapy at the end of the prior opioid stabilisation phase was 154.5 &#x000b1; 172.6 mg morphine equivalents, and the mean starting daily dose of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone was 30.1 &#x000b1; 37.9 mg, resulting in a mean conversion ratio of 5.13 : 1. The mean daily dose of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone increased to 56.6 &#x000b1; 63.3 mg at the end of titration and to 70.1 &#x000b1; 146.1 mg at the end of the maintenance phase.</p><fig id="fig02" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Percentage of patients requiring titration steps to achieve stabilisation of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone dose (<italic>n</italic> = 318)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijcp0061-1671-f2"/></fig><p>At the start of the OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone titration period, mean rescue medication requirements were 4.8 &#x000b1; 4.4 doses per day and 15.7 &#x000b1; 20.5 mg per day. The frequency of rescue medication use, but not mean dose, declined during OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone therapy (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Rescue medication (IR hydromorphone) used by patients receiving daily OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. daily doses</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily dose (mg)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Start of titration</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 &#x000b1; 4.36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7 &#x000b1; 20.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>End of titration</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 &#x000b1; 6.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3 &#x000b1; 20.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Mean change</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>End of maintenance</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1 &#x000b1; 10.38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8 &#x000b1; 42.54</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Mean change</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Analgesic efficacy</title><p>Mean BPI pain intensity ratings for pain at its worst, pain at its least, average pain and pain right now all decreased with OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone treatment (from the end of previous opioid stabilisation to the end of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone treatment; all p &#x02264; 0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Figure 3</xref>). Patients&#x02019; assessment of pain relief (BPI) also improved during OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone treatment, from 52.7 &#x000b1; 22.5% at the end of previous opioid stabilisation to 60.1 &#x000b1; 23.9% at last postbaseline assessment.</p><fig id="fig03" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of BPI pain intensity ratings: end of previous opioid stabilisation phase vs. end of treatment. Scale: 0, no pain; 10, pain as bad as you can imagine (p &#x02264; 0.001 for all scores; no adjustment for multiple testing)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijcp0061-1671-f3"/></fig><p>In addition to the improvement in pain intensity, patients reported a decrease in the degree to which pain interfered with their lives, as assessed by BPI pain interference scores (all p &#x0003c; 0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Figure 4</xref>). Investigators rated the overall effectiveness of medication as very good or excellent for 9% of patients at baseline (visit 2) and for 27% at the last assessment. Similarly, more patients rated the overall effectiveness of medication as very good or excellent at the last assessment (26%) than at the beginning of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone titration (8%).</p><fig id="fig04" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of BPI pain interference ratings: end of previous opioid stabilisation phase vs. end of treatment. Scale: 0, no interference; 10, complete interference (p &#x0003c; 0.001 for all scores; no adjustment for multiple testing)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijcp0061-1671-f4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Safety and tolerability</title><p>During the study, adverse events were experienced by 79% of patients. The most common events were gastrointestinal symptoms (such as nausea, constipation and vomiting) as well as headache, dizziness and somnolence (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>). The majority of these events were mild or moderate in severity. Serious adverse events were reported by 13 patients (4%), three of whom experienced episodes of overdose related to patient noncompliance with therapy. Two of these three patients were withdrawn from the study, and all three recovered with no sequelae. No other serious adverse events were considered probably or definitely related to study treatment. One death occurred during the study, which resulted from a perforated ulcer in the caecum of a patient with a history of morbid obesity. This event was not considered related to the study treatment. No clinically significant changes in vital signs occurred during the trial.</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Adverse events occurring in &#x02265; 5% of treated patients (<italic>n</italic> = 336)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. patients (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any adverse event</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">264 (79)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (24)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Headache</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Constipation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Dizziness</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (16)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Vomiting</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (15)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Somnolence</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (15)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Pruritus</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Sweating</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Insomnia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Dry mouth</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Diarrhoea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Fatigue</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Peripheral oedema</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (5)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Results of the previous interim pooled analysis showed that patients with chronic malignant or nonmalignant pain could be switched easily from previous opioid therapy to OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>). This finding was confirmed by the final results of the present study in patients with chronic nonmalignant pain. The majority of treated patients (&#x0223c;95%) achieved a stable dose of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone, most of them (87%) in two or fewer titration steps (4 days).</p><p>The efficacy results of the present study indicate that conversion from previous opioid therapy to OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone can be achieved with no loss of pain control. Over the course of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone treatment, patients&#x02019; BPI pain intensity ratings (worst, least and average pain, and pain right now) improved significantly (p &#x02264; 0.001) in comparison to the ratings recorded for their previous opioid therapy. The improvement in pain interference was similar. At the end of the maintenance period, there were statistically significant (p &#x0003c; 0.001) decreases in the degree to which patients&#x02019; pain interfered with general activity, mood, ability to walk, normal work, relationships with other people, sleep and general enjoyment of life. Such improvement can be expected to positively impact quality of life, as has been demonstrated for extended-release formulations of opioid agonists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). A German study conducted with a sustained-release formulation of hydromorphone (Palladone) in 487 patients showed improvement in quality of life domains, such as sleep, vitality, mood, social contacts, activity, resilience and walking ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>), consistent with results of the present study.</p><p>As has been demonstrated previously with extended-release morphine and oxycodone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>), conversion to OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone was achieved without the need for an intermediate IR opioid phase. The conversion ratio used in the study protocol is based on the commonly used 5 : 1 ratio of morphine equivalents to hydromorphone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>). However, some investigators, including the American Pain Society, recommend a reduction in equivalent dose when introducing a new long-acting opioid into treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>). The results of the present study demonstrate that most patients can successfully undergo direct conversion from their previous opioid agonist therapy to OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone using the 5 : 1 ratio, with no loss of efficacy or increase in side effects. Moreover, in the majority of patients, conversion at this level requires little or no titration to achieve stabilisation of the OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone dose. Interestingly, even fewer patients required dose titration in the study of identical design in patients with chronic cancer pain (104 manuscript in preparation). In that study, 77% of patients achieved a stable OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone dose with no titration, and another 20% required only one to two titration steps. In an analysis of two studies in which an 8 : 1 ratio was used for conversion, 70% of patients achieved a stable dose of hydromorphone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>).</p><p>OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone was well tolerated throughout the study. The most common adverse events affected the gastrointestinal and central nervous systems, and were consistent with those expected to occur with opioid agonist therapy for chronic pain.</p><p>Limitations of the present study include the open-label design and the lack of a control group. However, this study does show that patients can be switched easily from stable opioid agonist therapy to OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone, and that titration of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone will enable achievement of a stable dose that maintains effective pain control. The 5 : 1 conversion ratio (morphine equivalents to hydromorphone) also was well tolerated, with adverse events typical of those expected for OROS&#x000ae; opioid agonist therapy. Based on these promising results, the role of OROS&#x000ae; hydromorphone in the treatment of chronic nonmalignant pain should be further assessed by prospective, randomised and controlled trials.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This study was supported by ALZA Corporation, Mountain View, CA, USA.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Passik</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Managing chronic nonmalignant pain: overcoming obstacles to the use of opioids</article-title><source>Adv Ther</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11010058</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breivik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opioids in chronic non-cancer pain, indications and controversies</article-title><source>Eur J Pain</source><year>2005</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15737800</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydromorphone for acute and chronic pain</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2002</year><volume>1</volume><comment>CD003447. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/14651858.CD003447">10.1002/14651858.CD003447</ext-link></comment></citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarhill</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydromorphone: pharmacology and clinical applications in cancer patients</article-title><source>Support Care Cancer</source><year>2001</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11305075</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vallner</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics and bioavailability of hydromorphone following intravenous and oral administration to human subjects</article-title><source>J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>1981</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6165742</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of controlled-released morphine on quality of life for cancer pain</article-title><source>Oncol Nurs Forum</source><year>1989</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2755859</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarberg</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-acting opioids for chronic pain: pharmacotherapeutic opportunities to enhance compliance, quality of life, and analgesia</article-title><source>Am J Ther</source><year>2001</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11344385</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drover</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Input characteristics and bioavailability after administration of immediate and a new extended-release formulation of hydromorphone in healthy volunteers</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>2002</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12357147</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palangio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dose conversion and titration with a novel, once-daily, OROS osmotic technology, extended-release hydromorphone formulation in the treatment of chronic malignant or nonmalignant pain</article-title><source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source><year>2002</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12007754</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Storey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Subcutaneous infusions for control of cancer symptoms</article-title><source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source><year>1990</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1969887</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruera</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Opioid rotation in patients with cancer pain. A retrospective comparison of dose ratios between methadone, hydromorphone, and morphine</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>1996</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>852</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8756381</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawlor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dose ratio between morphine and hydromorphone in patients with cancer pain: a retrospective study</article-title><source>Pain</source><year>1997</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9272790</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Storey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>More on the conversion of transdermal fentanyl to morphine</article-title><source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source><year>1995</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8594116</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiple dose pharmacokinetics of OROS and immediate release (IR) hydromorphone (HM) in healthy subjects [abstract]</article-title><source>Pharm Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>S617</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daut</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of the Wisconsin Brief Pain Questionnaire to assess pain in cancer and other diseases</article-title><source>Pain</source><year>1983</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6646795</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sittig</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pain reduced and quality of life improved by sustained-release hydromorphone. Results of an observational study</article-title><source>MMW Fortschr Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>146</volume><issue>Suppl. 3&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15662898</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The evaluation of analgesic effects in cancer patients as exemplified by a double-blind, crossover study of immediate-release versus controlled-release morphine</article-title><source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source><year>1992</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1484191</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salzman</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Can a controlled-release oral dose form of oxycodone be used as readily as an immediate-release form for the purpose of titrating to stable pain control</article-title><source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10534967</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="book"><article-title>American Pain Society</article-title><source>Principles of Analgesic Use in the Treatment of Acute Pain and Cancer Pain</source><year>2003</year><edition>5</edition><publisher-loc>Glenview, IL</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Pain Society</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multicenter, open-label, prospective evaluation of the conversion from previous opioid analgesics to extended-release hydromorphone hydrochloride administered every 24 hours to patients with persistent moderate to severe pain</article-title><source>Clin Ther</source><year>2006</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16490582</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>





