<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><!-- Original-type: cl--><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15545973</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2409769</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6602230</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjc.6602230</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Quantifying trade-offs: quality of life and quality-adjusted survival in a randomised trial of chemotherapy in postmenopausal patients with lymph node-negative breast cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zahrieh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>A S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gelber</surname><given-names>R D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Castiglione-Gertsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>J F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Perey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff12">12</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff13">13</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rudenstam</surname><given-names>C-M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff14">14</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Crivellari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff15">15</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Veronesi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff15">15</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Th&#x000fc;rlimann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff16">16</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fey</surname><given-names>M F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>K N</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goldhirsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff17">17</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff18">18</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000fc;rny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff19">19</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><sup>1</sup>IBCSG Coordinating Center, Bern, Switzerland</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><sup>2</sup>Institute of Medical Oncology, Inselspital, Bern, Switzerland</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><sup>3</sup>IBCSG Statistical Center, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, MA, USA</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><sup>4</sup>Frontier Science and Technology Research Foundation, Boston, MA, USA</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><sup>5</sup>The Cancer Council Australia, Australia</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><sup>6</sup>University of Sydney, Australia</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><sup>7</sup>Groote Schuur Hospital, South Africa</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label><sup>8</sup>University of Cape Town, South Africa</aff><aff id="aff9"><label>9</label><sup>9</sup>Australian New Zealand Breast Cancer Trials Group, Newcastle, Australia</aff><aff id="aff10"><label>10</label><sup>10</sup>Newcastle Mater Misericordiae Hospital, Newcastle, Australia</aff><aff id="aff11"><label>11</label><sup>11</sup>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois, Lausanne</aff><aff id="aff12"><label>12</label><sup>12</sup>Department of Surgery, The Royal Melbourne Hospital, Melbourne, Australia</aff><aff id="aff13"><label>13</label><sup>13</sup>Department of Oncology, St Vincent's Hospital, Melbourne, Australia</aff><aff id="aff14"><label>14</label><sup>14</sup>West Swedish Breast Cancer Study Group, Sahlgrenska University Hospital, G&#x000f6;teborg, Sweden</aff><aff id="aff15"><label>15</label><sup>15</sup>Centro di Riferimento Oncologico, Aviano, Italy</aff><aff id="aff16"><label>16</label><sup>16</sup>Kantonsspital, St Gallen, Switzerland</aff><aff id="aff17"><label>17</label><sup>17</sup>Oncology Institute of Southern Switzerland, Lugano, Switzerland</aff><aff id="aff18"><label>18</label><sup>18</sup>European Institute of Oncology, Milan, Italy</aff><aff id="aff19"><label>19</label><sup>19</sup>B&#x000fc;rgerspital, St Gallen, Switzerland</aff><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>Author for correspondence: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:juerg.bernhard@ibcsg.org">juerg.bernhard@ibcsg.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>91</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1893</fpage><lpage>1901</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>06</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>30</day><month>09</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>09</month><year>2004</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright 2004, Cancer Research UK</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><permissions><copyright-holder>Cancer Research UK</copyright-holder></permissions><kwd-group><kwd>breast cancer</kwd><kwd>adjuvant therapy</kwd><kwd>quality of life</kwd><kwd>quality-adjusted survival</kwd><kwd>Q-TWiST</kwd><kwd>utility</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The International Breast Cancer Study Group (IBCSG) recently presented first results of a randomised trial (Trial IX) testing the role of adjuvant chemotherapy preceding treatment with tamoxifen for postmenopausal patients with lymph node-negative breast cancer (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib27">International Breast Cancer Study Group, 2002</xref>). Patients showed substantially better disease-free survival (DFS) with adjuvant chemotherapy if their oestrogen receptor (ER) status was negative (i.e. endocrine nonresponsive). In contrast, if their cancer was ER-positive (i.e. endocrine-responsive), they obtained no benefit from the chemotherapy compared with tamoxifen alone. In this report, we extend the analysis to quantify trade-offs based on quality of life (QL) and quality-adjusted survival (QAS).</p><p>The objective of the QL analysis was an extension of our earlier findings on the impact of adjuvant therapy on QL (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1996b</xref>). Presence, duration, timing and anticipation of chemotherapy had a measurable effect on patients' QL, but patients' psychological adaptation was found to be more important for their QL than cytotoxic side effects. In this trial, we used additional QL indicators (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib3">Bernhard <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>).</p><p>The objective of the QAS analysis was an extension of the Q-TWiST model designed to evaluate &#x02018;trade-offs&#x02019; in clinical trials (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib21">Goldhirsch <italic>et al</italic>, 1989</xref>). This model divides the life-span from the beginning of adjuvant treatment until death into three time segments corresponding to distinct health states: Tox (time with toxicity), TWiST (time without symptoms and toxicity) and Rel (time after systemic relapse). In previous trials, Tox and Rel were weighted by arbitrary utilities and added to TWiST to reach an overall assessment of different treatment groups. In this trial, patients were asked to directly assess the relevant utilities during Tox, TWiST and Rel using a scale which asked them to imagine that they would have to live the rest of their life in their current condition and then to rate this condition between &#x02018;perfect health&#x02019; and &#x02018;worst health&#x02019;. This scale has been shown to correspond to utility values as measured by conventional time trade-off (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib26">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>).</p><p>QL and QAS are usually evaluated separately despite their complementary objectives: understanding the pattern of morbidity and adaptation (QL), and providing information for clinical policy and decision-making (QAS). In this analysis, we link these two concepts to provide a quantitative backing for the trade-offs inherent in the use of effective but toxic therapies.</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>PATIENTS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>The Trial</title><p>Between October 1988 and August 1999, 1715 postmenopausal patients were randomly assigned to receive either tamoxifen (20&#x02009;mg&#x02009;day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) for 60 months or three 28-day courses of CMF (cyclophosphamide at 100&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> orally on days 1&#x02013;14, methotrexate at 40&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> intravenously on days 1 and 8 and 5-fluorouracil at 600&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> intravenously on days 1 and 8, followed by tamoxifen (20&#x02009;mg&#x02009;day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) for 57 months. Tamoxifen following chemotherapy was to begin on day 15 of the final course of CMF. Of the 1715 patients randomly assigned, 1669 (97&#x00025;) were eligible and assessable. The details of the trial protocol and conduct are described elsewhere (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib27">International Breast Cancer Study Group, 2002</xref>). The median follow-up of this analysis was 71 months. Participating investigators are displayed in <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1">Appendix A</xref>.</p><p>Patients were asked to complete a QL form at beginning of treatment (baseline), 2 months later (i.e. day 1 of cycle 3 or 8 weeks after tamoxifen start), at each 3 months for the first year, at months 18 and 24, and 1 and 6 months after relapse. This schedule was expanded, with yearly assessments up to month 72 (June 1995) regardless of the disease status (December 1996), that is, the 1 and 6 month assessments following relapse were dropped.</p></sec><sec><title>Quality of life analysis</title><p>We predicted worse QL during chemotherapy (month 3) but no residual effects among treatment groups after completion of chemotherapy (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1996b</xref>). A clinically meaningful difference was defined based on our previous observations of the coping indicator in postmenopausal patients with lymph node-positive breast cancer (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1996b</xref>), as the ratio of the average change between baseline and month 3 in patients with Tam alone <italic>vs</italic> those with three initial cycles CMF followed by Tam (ratio&#x0003d;3.37; not shown in the original article). We chose to use the ratio instead of the absolute difference in scores because the baseline scores in the present trial were better than those of the earlier trial, which involved women with node-positive disease.</p><p>As a secondary hypothesis, we expected smaller adverse effect of CMF on QL at month 3 for patients with ER-negative than those with ER-positive tumours. We reasoned that patients with ER-negative tumours would be more likely to feel that chemotherapy was necessary and therefore find it more bearable than patients with ER-positive disease.</p><p>We report QL data for the first 24 months in patients without recurrence within this time. Of the 1669 eligible and assessable patients, 1398 patients were included in the QL analysis. Of these, 803 completed all of their assessments using the 1993 version of the IBCSG QL Core Form (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib3">Bernhard <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>). This form comprised indicators for physical well being, mood (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib24">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1996a</xref>), coping effort (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib22">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1993</xref>), appetite, tiredness, hot flushes, nausea&#x0002f;vomiting, perceived social support, restrictions in arm movement and subjective health estimation (SHE) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib26">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>) in the linear analogue self-assessment (LASA) format. The other 595 patients either filled out all of their assessments using the previous version of the form, which included four of these indicators (physical well being, mood, coping effort, appetite) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib10">Butow <italic>et al</italic>, 1991</xref>), or they filled out a combination of the two. For consistency, only data provided by the 803 patients mentioned above were used for the analyses of the additional indicators. All indicators were analysed separately.</p><p>To test for differences between treatments in QL scores at each time point, we used ANOVA adjusting for culture (country&#x0002f;language; see <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Description of patients excluded from the quality of life (QL) analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Total eligible cases</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1669</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Exclusions from analysis</italic></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Relapse within first 24 months of randomisation</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">136</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Completed no QL forms</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Completed QL forms in multiple languages</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Undefined culture<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Assessable cases</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1398<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote1"><label>a</label><p>Culture is defined by the following language&#x0002f;country combinations: English&#x0002f;Australia; New Zealand; English&#x0002f;South Africa; French&#x0002f;Switzerland; German&#x0002f;Switzerland; Italian&#x0002f;Switzerland; Italian&#x0002f;Italy; Slovenian&#x0002f;Slovenia; Spanish&#x0002f;Spain; Swedish&#x0002f;Sweden.</p></fn><fn id="tbfnote2"><label>b</label><p>Of the 1398 patients, 803 completed all of their assessments using the 1993 version of the QL form. These 803 patients were used for the analyses of indicators included alone on this version of the form (tiredness, hot flushes, nausea&#x0002f;vomiting, social support, arm movement and SHE). All 1398 patients were used for the analyses of indicators included on both versions of the QL form (physical well being, mood, appetite and PACIS).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap> for definitions). For baseline analysis and tests for heterogeneity among treatment groups at each time point, we used the square roots of the scores (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1996b</xref>) because this transformation approximated a normal distribution and was effective in stabilising the variances for all indicators. The figures however show the results in the original scores from 0 to 100.</p><p>We also tested for differences in QL scores between baseline and month 3 and 6, respectively, of the within-patient changes in an ANOVA model that included assigned treatment and culture. The intrapatient differences were normally distributed for all QL scores.</p></sec><sec><title>Quality-adjusted survival analysis</title><p>For this analysis, we used the SHE indicator as designed for QAS (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib26">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>). Patients were asked to imagine that they would have to live the rest of their life in their current condition and then to rate this condition between &#x02018;perfect health&#x02019; and &#x02018;worst health&#x02019;. This indicator was previously validated against a time trade-off (TTO) interview (i.e. a preference measure) in patients with metastatic breast cancer. The conventional negative anchor &#x02018;death&#x02019; was replaced by &#x02018;worst health&#x02019; in the adjuvant setting since the two versions showed comparable results and &#x02018;death&#x02019; was judged to be an unacceptable anchor for some of the language&#x0002f;culture groups in the present study.</p><p>Following the Q-TWiST model (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib21">Goldhirsch <italic>et al</italic>, 1989</xref>), we defined three clinical health states: Tox, TWiST and Rel. The clinical question of this trial was the impact of adding three cycles of CMF. Therefore, Tox was calculated only in patients randomised to receive CMF.</p><p>To calculate Q-TWiST, each health state is assigned a utility coefficient (<italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub> and <italic>u</italic><sub>rel</sub>) which gives a value to time spent in the state relative to the value of an equal amount of time spent in a state of &#x02018;perfect health&#x02019;. The utilities are assumed to be in the interval &#x0005b;0,1&#x0005d;, where a zero indicates worst possible health, and unity indicates a state as good as perfect health. The Q-TWiST model is obtained by taking the linear combination of the health state durations adjusted by the respective utilities:</p><p><disp-formula id="equ1"><!-- in formula template--><graphic mime-subtype="gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="91-6602230e1.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>Our objective was to make a realistic patient-derived estimate of the utilities to evaluate Q-TWiST. We hypothesised that utilities derived from observed SHE values in both the Tox and Rel states would be substantially higher than the arbitrary value of 0.5 used to illustrate the Q-TWiST method when it was introduced (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib21">Goldhirsch <italic>et al</italic>, 1989</xref>). Also, we predicted that the actual scores during the TWiST state would be less than &#x02018;perfect&#x02019;, if only because all patients were receiving Tam.</p><p>Within each defined health state, all available SHE scores were used (<italic>N</italic>&#x0003d;1669). For Tox, we used the median value at month 3 (i.e. peak of toxicity). For TWiST, we used the median of the SHE scores averaged within patients over the first 24 months after randomisation (excluding the first 3 months in patients with CMF). For Rel, we used the median of the SHE scores averaged within patients over the first 6 months after relapse. These SHE estimates were converted to quality weights using a power transformation: TTO&#x0003d;1&#x02013;(1&#x02013;SHE)<sup><italic>&#x003b1;</italic></sup> (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib44">Torrance <italic>et al</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib43">Torrance <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). We used the <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> value from our validation study (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>&#x0003d;1.6) and performed a sensitivity analysis for a range of published <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>'s.</p><p>An exploratory analysis was conducted to assess <italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub> confined to those patients who had any recorded subjective toxic effect of grade 2 or higher (excluding amenorrhea) during their chemotherapy as was done in the original Q-TWiST model (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib21">Goldhirsch <italic>et al</italic>, 1989</xref>).</p><p>Mean health state durations were estimated from censored survival data (product limit method) up to 72 months from randomisation by computing the areas between the survival curve estimates for the transition times. These durations were adjusted using the patient-derived utilities in order to estimate mean Q-TWiST for each treatment group. The treatments were separately compared overall and within the prospectively stratified ER-negative and ER-positive cohorts.</p><p>We performed a threshold utility analysis both overall and within the ER-negative and ER-positive cohorts. These findings provide a decision aid for a range of utilities for Tox and Rel. To account for the less than &#x02018;perfect health&#x02019;, we divided each of the three utilities by the patient estimated <italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub> so that Q-TWiST is interpreted relative to TWiST and more accurately reflects the patients&#x02019; perception during the time period: Q-TWiST&#x0003d;<italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub>&#x0002f;<italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub> &#x000d7; Tox&#x0002b;<italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub>&#x0002f;<italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub> &#x000d7; TWiST &#x000d7; <italic>u</italic><sub>r</sub>&#x0002f;<italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub> &#x000d7; Rel. The treatment comparison results are presented for all possible values of the utilities.</p><p>For all analyses, <italic>P</italic>-values less than 0.05 were deemed statistically significant. No adjustment was made for multiple testing.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Quality of life</title><p>Of the 1669 eligible patients, 1398 were assessable for the QL study. The submission rate of the QL form was 87&#x00025; (1213) at baseline declining to 75&#x00025; (1044) at month 24. The definition of the sample is shown in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The patient characteristics are shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Baseline characteristics of the 1398 patients with available QL data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>Tam</bold></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>CMF &#x02192; Tam</bold></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>Total</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Total eligible cases</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">701 (100)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">697 (100)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1398 (100)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ER-negative</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">147 (21)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">149 (21)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">296 (21)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ER-positive</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">525 (75)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">516 (74)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1041 (74)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ER-unknown</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">29 (4)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">32 (5)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">61 (4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Total mastectomy</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">332 (47)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">350 (50)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">682 (49)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Breast conservation</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">369 (53)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">347 (50)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">716 (51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;With planned RT</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">322 (87)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">313 (90)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">635 (89)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Without planned RT</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">47 (13)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">34 (10)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">81 (11)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Tumour size&#x02a7d;1.0&#x02009;cm</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">78 (11)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">84 (12)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">162 (12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Tumour size 1.1&#x02013;2.0&#x02009;cm</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">336 (48)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">335 (48)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">671 (48)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Tumour size&#x0003e;2.0&#x02009;cm</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">262 (37)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">252 (36)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">514 (37)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Tumour size unknown</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">25 (4)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">26 (4)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">51 (4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Tumour grade 1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">131 (19)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">123 (18)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">254 (18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Tumour grade 2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">294 (42)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">285 (41)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">579 (41)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Tumour grade 3</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">234 (33)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">242 (35)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">476 (34)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Tumour grade unknown</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">42 (6)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">47 (7)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">89 (6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Vessel invasion absent</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">540 (77)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">528 (76)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1068 (76)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Vessel invasion present</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">147 (21)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">151 (22)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">298 (21)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Vessel invasion not examined</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">14 (2)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">18 (2)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">32 (2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Age (median &#x0005b;range&#x0005d;)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">61 &#x0005b;34&#x02013;78&#x0005d;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">60 &#x0005b;44&#x02013;81&#x0005d;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">61 &#x0005b;34&#x02013;81&#x0005d;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Median tiredness scores by treatment group over the first 24 months. Higher values indicate less tiredness (i.e. better QL).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="91-6602230f1"/></fig> depicts the expected short-term effect between treatments at month 3, with less severe tiredness (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.01) in patients receiving Tam alone, as compared to those patients with three initial cycles of CMF. Nausea&#x0002f;vomiting (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01) and appetite were similarly affected (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01). Also, at 3 months, physical well being (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01) and mood (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01) showed effects in favour of Tam alone. Subjective health estimates (SHE) were similarly affected (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.02), as displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Median scores of subjective health (SHE) by treatment group over the first 24 months. Higher values indicate better health estimates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="91-6602230f2"/></fig>. In contrast, patients receiving CMF reported less hot flushes at 3 months (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01) than those receiving Tam. CMF recipients started tamoxifen after completing chemotherapy.</p><p>The global QL indicators showed effects in favour of Tam alone. The coping scores indicated a steady improvement over the first 24 months. This adaptation was delayed but not prevented in patients receiving CMF (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01), as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Median scores of coping effort (PACIS) by treatment group over the first 24 months. Higher values indicate less effort to cope (i.e. better QL).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="91-6602230f3"/></fig>. The ratio of the average change in the coping indicator between baseline and month 3 in patients with Tam alone <italic>vs</italic> those with CMF followed by Tam (ratio&#x0003d;3.17) was close to that observed in our previous trial (ratio&#x0003d;3.37), indicating a clinically meaningful difference. There was a baseline difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.03) with patients assigned to CMF reporting lower SHE scores. Of these patients, 43&#x00025; completed the QL form prior to randomisation (thus up to 57&#x00025; did so after knowing treatment assignment), and 95&#x00025; of all patients with CMF at day 1 of the first cycle or before (thus 5&#x00025; did so after experiencing initial toxicity).</p><p>The mean treatment differences in the changes of scores over the first 3 months are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Mean treatment differences over the first 3 months with their respective 95&#x00025; confidence intervals (<italic>N</italic>&#x0003d;914). Positive values indicate either an improvement or less deterioration in QL for patients randomised to receive Tam alone compared with patients randomised to receive CMF followed by Tam.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="91-6602230f4"/></fig>. After the completion of chemotherapy (i.e. month 6 assessment), there were no statistically significant residual differences between treatment groups for any of the QL measures.</p><p>Similar analyses were performed within the ER-negative and ER-positive cohorts. Contrary to our hypothesis, there was no indication for a different treatment effect on QL by ER status (data not shown).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>QUALITY-ADJUSTED SURVIVAL</title><p>Patients assigned to CMF had improved disease-free survival (DFS) compared with patients who received Tam alone (&#x0005b;CMF&#x0002b;Tam&#x0002f;Tam&#x0005d; RR&#x0003d;0. 80; 95&#x00025; CI&#x0003d;0.64 to 1.00; <italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.05). There was also a trend in favour of improved overall survival (OS) (&#x0005b;CMF&#x0002b;Tam&#x0002f;Tam&#x0005d; RR&#x0003d;0.75; 95&#x00025; CI&#x0003d;0.55 to 1.02; <italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.07). Disease-free survival and OS at 72 months for all 1669 eligible patients are summarised in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Overall survival (OS)and DFS by treatment at 72 months (<italic>N</italic>&#x0003d;1669)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>No. of patients</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>No. of events</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>6-year DFS&#x00025; (s.e.)</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>No. dead</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>6-year OS&#x00025; (s.e.)</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Overall</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Tam</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">846</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">166</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">78 (2)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.05</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">94</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">87 (1)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;CMF &#x02192; Tam</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">823</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">138</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">83 (1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">73</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">91 (1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>ER-negative</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Tam</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">190</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">57</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">67 (4)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.003</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">38</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">75 (4)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;CMF &#x02192; Tam</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">192</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">33</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">83 (3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">21</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">88 (3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>ER-positive</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Tam</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">621</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">101</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">81 (2)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.92</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">51</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">90 (2)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;CMF &#x02192; Tam</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">596</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">101</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">82 (2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">50</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">92 (1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote3"><label/><p>DFS&#x0003d;disease-free survival; s.e.&#x0003d;standard error.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>.</p><p>The patient derived utilities for the three health states estimated from SHE scores are shown in <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Calculated utility coefficients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Health state</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold><italic>N</italic><sup>a</sup></bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>SHE</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>TTO&#x0003d;1&#x02212;(1&#x02212;SHE)<sup>1.6</sup></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Tox (CMF)</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Overall</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">276</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.76</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.89</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-negative</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">59</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.75</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.89</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-positive</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">217</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.76</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>TWiST</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Tam alone</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">384</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.80</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;CMF</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">358</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.80</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-negative overall</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">161</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.80</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-positive overall</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">578</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.80</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Rel</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Tam alone</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">23</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.62</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;CMF</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">14</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.50</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.66</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Total sample</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">37</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.54</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-negative overall</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">12</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.54</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-positive overall</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">24</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.56</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.73</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote4"><label>a</label><p>Sample size reflects those patients who experienced that health state and who responded to the SHE question at least once during that health state. SHE&#x0003d;subjective health estimation; TTO&#x0003d;time trade-off ; ER&#x0003d;oestrogen receptor.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>. For Tox, 276 patients with CMF responded to the SHE question. The patient-derived utility for this period was 0.89. Of these patients, 66&#x00025; (<italic>N</italic>&#x0003d;183) had a subjective toxic effect of grade 2 or higher (excluding amenorrhea) reported during the three cycles. The estimated utility for Tox of this subgroup was also 0.89.</p><p>For TWiST, SHE scores were available for 742 patients. The estimated utility for this period was 0.91. There was no difference in utility during TWiST by randomised treatment. For Rel, SHE scores were available for 37 patients. Those who relapsed after adjuvant CMF indicated a trend to lower SHE scores (median&#x0003d;0.5, range: 0.10&#x02013;0.99) than those initially treated with Tam alone (median&#x0003d;0.62, range: 0.26&#x02013;1.0). Given the small subgroups, we used the overall SHE scores (median&#x0003d;0.54) for QAS (<italic>u</italic><sub>r</sub>&#x0003d;0.71).</p><p>The average values of time spent in Tox, TWiST and Rel within 72 months of randomisation are summarised in <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Components of Q-TWiST</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="5" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Treatment group</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Health state</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Tam alone (s.e.)</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>CMF &#x02192; Tam (s.e.)</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Difference (s.e.)</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>(95&#x00025; CI)</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Tox</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Overall</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0 (0)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.7 (0.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-negative</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0 (0)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.8 (0.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-positive</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0 (0)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.7 (0.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>TWiST</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Overall</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">63.4 (0.7)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">64.0 (0.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-negative</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">57.7 (1.7)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">62.6 (1.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-positive</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">65.4 (0.7)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">64.2 (0.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Rel</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Overall</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">5.1 (0.5)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">3.8 (0.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-negative</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">7.5 (1.2)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">3.3 (0.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-positive</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4.5 (0.6)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4.2 (0.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Q-TWiST</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Overall</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">61.4 (0.4)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">62.5 (0.3)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.1 (0.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">(0.1&#x02013;2.1)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-negative</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">57.8 (1.1)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">60.8 (1.0)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">3.0 (1.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">(0.2&#x02013;5.8)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;ER-positive</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">62.7 (0.4)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">63.0 (0.4)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.3 (0.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">(&#x02212;0.6&#x02013;1.3)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.50</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote5"><label/><p>Averaged months of Tox, TWiST and Rel accumulated within 72 months of randomisation, with Q-TWiST calculated for patient-derived utility coefficients (<italic>N</italic>&#x0003d;1669). s.e.&#x0003d;standard error; ER&#x0003d;oestrogen receptor.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>. The calculation of Q-TWiST is illustrated by the weighted combination of these components using the patient-derived estimates of <italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub>&#x0003d;0.89, <italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub>&#x0003d;0.91 and <italic>u</italic><sub>r</sub>&#x0003d;0.71. Based on these utilities, the average Q-TWiST within the first 6 years for patients receiving CMF followed by Tam was 62.5 months, 1.1 month longer than patients receiving Tam alone (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.03).</p><p>Patients benefited from adjuvant chemotherapy if their ER-status was negative, with an average gain in Q-TWiST of 3 months as compared to those with tamoxifen alone (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.03). Patients with ER-positive tumours obtained no Q-TWiST benefit from the chemotherapy .</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Threshold utility analysis of the total sample (<italic>N</italic>&#x0003d;1669). The diagonal lines indicate the units of months gained in Q-TWiST for different utilities for Tox and Rel. The utility for TWiST is defined as <italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub>&#x0003d;1 (i.e. reference state). The solid line labelled 0 is the threshold above which CMF followed by Tam results in improved Q-TWiST. The area below 0 with hatch marks represents improved Q-TWiST for Tam alone. The shaded region (top left) represents utilities (<italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub> and <italic>u</italic><sub>r</sub>) for which the improvement in Q-TWiST is statistically significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02a7d;0.05). S&#x0003d;significant and NS&#x0003d;not significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="91-6602230f5"/></fig> allows a sensitivity analysis to display the effect on Q-TWiST of any combination of utilities during Tox and Rel. To prepare this figure, we standardised the other utilities relative to <italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub> For example, a conventional treatment comparison for DFS makes no deduction for reduced utility during Tox (<italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub>&#x0003d;<italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub>&#x0003d;1). Based on these assumptions, CMF followed by Tam is obviously preferred to Tam alone. Taking into account different values for Tox (<italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub>&#x0003c;1;<italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub>&#x0003d;1) and including Rel, there is a gain in Q-TWiST for CMF followed by Tam for most values of <italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub> and <italic>u</italic><sub>r</sub>. This trend towards an improvement reaches statistical significance for relatively high values of <italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub> as well as over a wide range of plausible values of <italic>u</italic><sub>r</sub> as displayed in the upper left portion of the figure. For low values of <italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub> combined with high values of <italic>u</italic><sub>r</sub>, there is a nonsignificant benefit for tamoxifen alone as displayed in the lower right portion of the figure.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figures 6</xref><fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Threshold utility analysis of the ER-negative cohort (<italic>N</italic>&#x0003d;382). The diagonal lines indicate the units of months gained in Q-TWiST for different utilities for Tox and Rel. The utilities for TWiST is defined as <italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub>&#x0003d;1 (i.e. reference state). All values of the utilities for Tox and Rel result in improved Q-TWiST for CMF followed by Tam compared with Tam alone. The shaded region (top left) represents utilities (<italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub> and <italic>u</italic><sub>r</sub>) for which the improvement in Q-TWiST is statistically significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02a7d;0.05). S&#x0003d;significant and NS&#x0003d;not significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="91-6602230f6"/></fig> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref><fig id="fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Threshold utility analysis of the ER-positive cohort (<italic>N</italic>&#x0003d;1217). The diagonal lines indicate the units of months gained in Q-TWiST for different utilities for Tox and Rel. The utilities for TWiST is defined as <italic>u</italic><sub>twist</sub>&#x0003d;1 (i.e. reference state). The solid line labelled 0 is the threshold above which CMF followed by Tam results in improved Q-TWiST. The area below 0 with hatch marks represents improved Q-TWiST for Tam alone. The shaded region (bottom right) represents utilities (<italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub> and <italic>u</italic><sub>r</sub>) for which the improvement in Q-TWiST is statistically significant for Tam alone (<italic>P</italic> &#x02a7d; 0.05). S&#x0003d;significant and NS&#x0003d;not significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="91-6602230f7"/></fig> display similar threshold plots for the ER-negative and ER-positive cohorts, respectively. For patients with ER-negative tumours, CMF followed by Tam is favoured for all values of <italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub> and a broad range of <italic>u</italic><sub>r</sub>. For patients with ER-positive tumours, there was no benefit from the chemotherapy in terms of Q-TWiST. The trend towards an improvement in Tam alone reaches statistical significance in a small area defined by very low values of <italic>u</italic><sub>t</sub> and high values of <italic>u</italic><sub>r</sub>.</p><p>Finally, we performed a sensitivity analysis for a range of proposed <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>'s used to transform the SHE scale to reflect a TTO scale. After using an <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> of 1.4, the utilities for each of the three health states were similar although slightly reduced. After using an <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> value of 1.8, again the utilities were similar for all three health states although slightly higher. Thus, incorporating utilities using an <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> within the range of 1.4&#x02013;1.8 would not markedly affect the results obtained from our Q-TWiST analysis (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The main objective of these analyses was to link QL and QAS in comparing the randomised treatments. In addition, we investigated whether there was a difference in the magnitude of the chemotherapy effect according to ER status of the primary tumour as was found for survival in this trial (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib27">International Breast Cancer Study Group, 2002</xref>).</p><sec><title>Quality of life</title><p>The subjective impact of adjuvant therapy was investigated over the first 24 months of treatment. At month 3, patients receiving CMF reported the expected side effects. Better QL in patients with Tam alone was also indicated by the various global measures of well being, coping and health status, despite the earlier beginning of hot flushes for the Tam alone group.</p><p>After completing chemotherapy, QL scores rapidly improved as found in our previous trials (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1996b</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib42">The International Breast Cancer Study Group, 2001</xref>) and in an adjuvant trial by the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group with a more comprehensive QL questionnaire (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib15">Fairclough <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>). Contrary to our hypothesis, patients' perception of chemotherapy was not affected by the ER status of their tumour.</p><p>We faced problems with the timing of administration for the baseline QL assessment. A substantial proportion of patients completed the QL form after randomisation but before starting CMF. These patients were presumably aware of their assigned treatment. The baseline scores may reflect an anticipation of cytotoxic side effects or perception of worse health status, as described for indicators of QL and health status and for preference measures (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib23">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1996b</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib29">Jansen <italic>et al</italic>, 2001b</xref>). To eliminate any differential anticipatory effects on baseline scores in future studies, we have introduced a completed QL form as an eligibility criterion.</p><p>Overall, the improvement in QL over the first 6 months was more pronounced than the transient impairment by chemotherapy. These findings confirm those of IBCSG Trials VI and VII (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1996b</xref>), suggesting that a patient's psychological adaptation is more important for her QL than cytotoxic side effects. There were no residual effects of CMF as assessed by our indicators. Similarly, in a survey in premenopausal women with node-negative breast cancer treated with or without adjuvant CMF, there were no long-term effects of CMF in general and breast cancer-specific QL domains (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib31">Joly <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>). This finding does not exclude long-term sequelae, such as fatigue (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib7">Bower <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>), or impaired sexual (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib9">Broeckel <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>) or cognitive functioning (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib37">Phillips and Bernhard, 2003</xref>), in subgroups.</p></sec><sec><title>Quality-adjusted survival</title><p>The Q-TWiST method has hitherto used utilities assigned arbitrarily (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib21">Goldhirsch <italic>et al</italic>, 1989</xref>) or estimated based on patient reported QL (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib15">Fairclough <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>). Although this approach provides a useful decision aid via a threshold analysis, we wanted to take into account patients' own perception of their health status.</p><p>We used a global indicator for health status to reflect the patients' perception across the three distinct health states (Tox, TWiST, Rel) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib26">H&#x000fc;rny <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>). This extension of the Q-TWiST model has provided new information for decision-making. The extent of impairment during Tox was less severe than the conventional assumptions. This finding is not related to the timing of the baseline assessment as we used only the scores at month 3. Our finding is consistent with those of preference studies showing that a majority of patients who previously received adjuvant chemotherapy for breast cancer accept the morbidity of these therapies in turn for a relatively modest survival gain (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib32">Lindley <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib38">Ravdin <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib28">Jansen <italic>et al</italic>, 2001a</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib40">Simes and Coates, 2001</xref>).</p><p>The SHE scores during the TWiST health state were less than &#x02018;perfect&#x02019; and relatively close to the Tox scores. The fact of having cancer and late effects of surgical and systemic treatments may have had an impact on the health estimates (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib8">Broeckel <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib18">Ganz <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>). All patients received Tam. Endocrine side effects may be under-reported (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib17">Fellowes <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>), especially vasomotor and gynaecological symptoms (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib13">Day <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib16">Fallowfield <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>).</p><p>The SHE scores during the Rel state were distinctly worse than those of Tox and TWiST, although better than the arbitrary values used in previous analyses. For a majority, the relatively high value may reflect their readjustment and the beneficial impact of the treatment for advanced disease (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib5">Bernhard <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>). However, there was substantial variability due to both the small number of patients who had a recurrence and the limited information available on these cases.</p><p>Overall Q-TWiST accumulated within 72 months after randomisation indicated an advantage of 1 month longer of &#x02018;perfect health&#x02019; with CMF rather than Tam alone. However, in the ER-negative cohort, three cycles CMF provided 3 months more of Q-TWiST than Tam alone, while for the larger ER-positive cohort, CMF provided no benefit.</p><p>The findings of the QAS analysis thus complement and expand those of the QL investigation. They provide additional information for clinical policy and decision-making in postmenopausal patients with node-negative breast cancer: Taking patients' view into account, patients benefited substantially from adjuvant chemotherapy if their ER status was negative.</p><p>These analyses are truncated at 72 months follow-up. Further follow-up will enhance any advantage of chemotherapy over Tam alone.</p><p>In contrast to other studies using global indicators of health status for QAS analysis (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib14">Earle <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>), we specified the frame of individual reference. Patients were asked to imagine they would have to live the rest of their life in their current condition and then to rate their concurrent condition. Although not a true preference measure, this indicator is suitable for large-scale phase-III trials taking into account patients' own evaluation of distinct health states within a given context (e.g. culture). Our premise was to evaluate estimates based on actual experience instead of hypothetical scenarios. Experience of breast cancer (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib1">Ashby <italic>et al</italic>, 1994</xref>) and adjuvant chemotherapy (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib32">Lindley <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib29">Jansen <italic>et al</italic>, 2001b</xref>) have been shown to be associated with current preferences. Most often, this type of evaluation is based on cross-sectional comparisons (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib14">Earle <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>). A repeated formal utility interview is not feasible in an international phase-III trial and would not imply <italic>a priori</italic> a better performance than a rating scale such as our SHE indicator (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib19">Giesler <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>).</p><p>The method of insertion of utility values into decision models by multiplication of utilities and time assumes the independence of time and values. This assumption has been challenged (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib6">Bleichrodt and Johannesson, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib2">Bala <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib41">Stiggelbout <italic>et al</italic>, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib4">Bernhard <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). Preference studies in cancer patients with repeated assessment reported both reasonably stable (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib36">O'Connor <italic>et al</italic>, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib33">Llewellyn-Thomas <italic>et al</italic>, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib29">Jansen <italic>et al</italic>, 2001b</xref>) and unstable (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib34">Llewellyn-Thomas <italic>et al</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib30">Jansen <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>) utilities, suggesting caution in interpreting single point estimates. Variation in self-report health status across distinct clinical situations is plausible and argues for a longitudinal evaluation.</p><p>Further developments include the relationship between additional QL domains, such as fatigue (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib39">Sadler and Jacobsen, 2001</xref>) and cognitive function (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib37">Phillips and Bernhard, 2003</xref>), and the SHE-scores across different health states (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib35">Lowy and Bernhard, 2004</xref>). Finally, this concept can be adapted to the palliative setting where there are no clearly separated health states (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib20">Glasziou <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib12">Cole <italic>et al</italic>, 2004</xref>).</p><p>In summary, patients receiving initial CMF indicated the expected adverse impact on QL and a delay in adaptation compared to those assigned Tam alone. The patient estimated utilities for TWiST indicated less than &#x02018;perfect health&#x02019; under Tam. Longitudinal evaluations of SHE scores provide important information for QAS (Q-TWiST) analysis and clinical decision-making.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the patients, physicians, nurses and data managers who participated in the International Breast Cancer Study Group trials. We acknowledge Rita Hinkle for data management. We further acknowledge the initial support provided by the Ludwig Institute for Cancer Research and the Cancer League of Ticino and the continuing support for central coordination, data management and statistics provided by the Swedish Cancer Society, The Cancer Council Australia, Australian New Zealand Breast Cancer Trials Group (NHMRC Grant numbers 890028, 920876, 950328, 980379, 141711), the Frontier Science and Technology Research Foundation, the Swiss Group for Clinical Cancer Research (SAKK), the Swiss Cancer League, the American Cancer Society (RPG-90-013-08-PBP) and the United States National Cancer Institute (CA-75362). We also acknowledge support for the Cape Town participants from the Cancer Association of South Africa and for St Gallen participants from the Foundation for Clinical Cancer Research of Eastern Switzerland.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>O Hanlon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Buxton</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The time trade-off technique: how do the valuations of breast cancer patients compare to those of other groups</article-title><source>Qual Life Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Qual Life Res||3|257||bib1|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7812278</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bala</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarkin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gafni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are health states &#x02018;timeless&#x02019;? The case of the standard gamble method</article-title><source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>1047</fpage><lpage>1053</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Epidemiol||52|1047||bib2|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10526998</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000fc;rny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Castiglione Gertsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelber</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldhirsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Senn</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudenstam</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life assessment in patients receiving adjuvant therapy for breast cancer: the IBCSG approach. The International Breast Cancer Study Group</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>1997</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Ann Oncol||8|825||bib3|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9358933</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maibach</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000fc;rny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response shift in the perception of health for utility evaluation. An explorative investigation</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>2001</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1729</fpage><lpage>1735</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Eur J Cancer||37|1729||bib4|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11549425</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Th&#x000fc;rlimann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Castiglione Gertsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Morant</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fey</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnefoi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldhirsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000fc;rny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining clinical benefit in postmenopausal patients with breast cancer under second-line endocrine treatment: does quality of life matter</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1999</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1672</fpage><lpage>1679</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||17|1672||bib5|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10561203</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bleichrodt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Johannesson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The validity of QALYs: an experimental test of constant proportional tradeoff and utility independence</article-title><source>Med Decis Making</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Med Decis Making||17|21||bib6|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8994148</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bower</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganz</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Desmond</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Belin</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatigue in breast cancer survivors: occurrence, correlates, and impact on quality of life</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2000</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>753</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||18|743||bib7|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10673515</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broeckel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Balducci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyman</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life after adjuvant chemotherapy for breast cancer</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2000</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Breast Cancer Res Treat||62|141||bib8|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11016752</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broeckel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thors</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sexual functioning in long-term breast cancer survivors treated with adjuvant chemotherapy</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2002</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Breast Cancer Res Treat||75|241||bib9|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12353813</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butow</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000fc;rny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the receiving end IV: validation of quality of life indicators</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>1991</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>603</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Ann Oncol||2|597||bib10|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1793727</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelber</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A quality-adjusted survival model (Q-TWiST) for advanced stage cancer</article-title><source>J Biopharm Stat</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Biopharm Stat||14|111||bib12|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15027503</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganz</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Costantino</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickerham</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health-related quality of life and tamoxifen in breast cancer prevention: a report from the National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project P-1 Study</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1999</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2659</fpage><lpage>2669</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||17|2659||bib13|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10561339</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Earle</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandberg</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic overview of cost-utility assessments in oncology</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2000</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>3302</fpage><lpage>3317</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||18|3302||bib14|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10986064</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fairclough</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetting</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cella</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wonson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Moinpour</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life and quality adjusted survival for breast cancer patients receiving adjuvant therapy. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG)</article-title><source>Qual Life Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>731</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Qual Life Res||8|723||bib15|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10855346</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fallowfield</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleissig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Powles</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuzick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tamoxifen for the prevention of breast cancer: psychosocial impact on women participating in two randomized controlled trials</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1885</fpage><lpage>1892</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||19|1885||bib16|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283119</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fellowes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fallowfield</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tolerability of hormone therapies for breast cancer: how informative are documented symptom profiles in medical notes for &#x02018;well-tolerated&#x02019; treatments</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2001</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Breast Cancer Res Treat||66|73||bib17|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11368413</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganz</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Desmond</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leedham</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Belin</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life in long-term, disease-free survivors of breast cancer: a follow-up study</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2002</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Natl Cancer Inst||94|39||bib18|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11773281</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giesler</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashton</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Geraci</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Souchek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the performance of utility techniques in the absence of a gold standard</article-title><source>Med Care</source><year>1999</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>580</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Med Care||37|580||bib19|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10386570</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glasziou</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelber</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Simes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality adjusted survival analysis with repeated quality of life measures</article-title><source>Stat Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1215</fpage><lpage>1229</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Stat Med||17|1215||bib20|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9670411</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldhirsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelber</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Simes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Glasziou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><collab>for the Ludwig Breast Cancer Study Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Costs and benefits of adjuvant therapy in breast cancer: a quality-adjusted survival analysis</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1989</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||7|36||bib21|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2642538</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000fc;rny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wegberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomamichel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Spek</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Castiglione</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldhirsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Senn</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><collab>for the Swiss Group for Clinical Cancer Research (SAKK) and the International Breast Cancer Study Group (IBCSG)</collab></person-group><article-title>The Perceived Adjustment to Chronic Illness Scale (PACIS): a global indicator of coping for operable breast cancer patients in clinical trials</article-title><source>Support Care Cancer</source><year>1993</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Support Care Cancer||1|200||bib22|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8193882</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000fc;rny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Castiglione</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelber</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudenstam</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldhirsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Senn</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Timing of baseline quality of life assessment in an international adjuvant breast cancer trial: its effect on patient self-estimation. The International Breast Cancer Study Group</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>1994</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Ann Oncol||5|65||bib23|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000fc;rny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Castiglione-Gertsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelber</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudenstam</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindtner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldhirsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Senn</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Responsiveness of a single-item indicator <italic>versus</italic> a multi-item scale: assessment of emotional well-being in an international adjuvant breast cancer trial</article-title><source>Med Care</source><year>1996a</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Med Care||34|234||bib24|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8628043</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000fc;rny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Castiglione Gertsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelber</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudenstam</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Simoncini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Crivellari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldhirsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Senn</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of adjuvant therapy on quality of life in women with node-positive operable breast cancer. International Breast Cancer Study Group</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1996b</year><volume>347</volume><fpage>1279</fpage><lpage>1284</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Lancet||347|1279||bib25|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8622502</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000fc;rny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wegberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Th&#x000fc;rlimann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Real</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Perey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnefoi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subjective health estimations (SHE) in patients with advanced breast cancer: an adapted utility concept for clinical trials</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1998</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>985</fpage><lpage>991</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||77|985||bib26|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9528845</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>International Breast Cancer Study Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Endocrine responsiveness and tailoring adjuvant therapy for postmenopausal lymph node-negative breast cancer: a randomized trial</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2002</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>1054</fpage><lpage>1065</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Natl Cancer Inst||94|1054||bib27|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12122096</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kievit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nooij</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>de Haes</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Overpelt</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>van Slooten</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Maartense</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiggelbout</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patients' preferences for adjuvant chemotherapy in early-stage breast cancer: is treatment worthwhile</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2001a</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1577</fpage><lpage>1585</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||84|1577||bib28|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11401308</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kievit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nooij</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiggelbout</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stability of patients' preferences for chemotherapy: the impact of experience</article-title><source>Med Decis Making</source><year>2001b</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Med Decis Making||21|295||bib29|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11475386</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiggelbout</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakker</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Nooij</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Noordijk</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kievit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unstable preferences: a shift in valuation or an effect of the elicitation procedure</article-title><source>Med Decis Making</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Med Decis Making||20|62||bib30|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10638538</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joly</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Espie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heron</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry Amar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term quality of life in premenopausal women with node-negative localized breast cancer treated with or without adjuvant chemotherapy</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2000</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>582</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||83|577||bib31|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10944595</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawyer</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Winer</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life and preferences for treatment following systemic adjuvant therapy for early-stage breast cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1998</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1380</fpage><lpage>1387</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||16|1380||bib32|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9552041</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Llewellyn-Thomas</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do patients' evaluations of a future health state change when they actually enter that state</article-title><source>Med Care</source><year>1993</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1002</fpage><lpage>1012</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Med Care||31|1002||bib33|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8231333</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Llewellyn-Thomas</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>McGreal</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer patients' evaluations of their current health states: the influences of expectations, comparisons, actual health status, and mood</article-title><source>Med Decis Making</source><year>1992</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Med Decis Making||12|115||bib34|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1573978</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative assessment of changes in patients' constructs of quality of life: an application of multilevel models</article-title><source>Qual Life Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1177</fpage><lpage>1185</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Qual Life Res||13|1177||bib35|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15473496</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name><surname>Warde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolbach</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Till</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eliciting preferences for alternative drug therapies in oncology: influence of treatment outcome description, elicitation technique and treatment experience on preferences</article-title><source>J Chronic Dis</source><year>1987</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Chronic Dis||40|811||bib36|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3597681</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adjuvant breast cancer treatment and cognitive function: current knowledge and research directions</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2003</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Natl Cancer Inst||95|190||bib37|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12569140</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravdin</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Siminoff</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survey of breast cancer patients concerning their knowledge and expectations of adjuvant therapy</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1998</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||16|515||bib38|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9469335</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadler</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progress in understanding fatigue associated with breast cancer treatment</article-title><source>Cancer Invest</source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>731</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Invest||19|723||bib39|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11577813</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patient preferences for adjuvant chemotherapy of early breast cancer: how much benefit is needed</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr</source><year>2001</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr||30|146||bib40|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11773309</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stiggelbout</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiebert</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kievit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leer</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Habbema</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>De Haes</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The &#x02018;utility&#x02019; of the time trade-off method in cancer patients: feasibility and proportional trade-off</article-title><source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1207</fpage><lpage>1214</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Epidemiol||48|1207||bib41|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7561982</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The International Breast Cancer Study Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Randomized controlled trial of ovarian function suppression plus tamoxifen <italic>versus</italic> the same endocrine therapy plus chemotherapy: is chemotherapy necessary for premenopausal women with node-positive, endocrine responsive breast cancer? First results of International Breast Cancer Study Group Trial 11&#x02013;93</article-title><source>Breast</source><year>2001</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Breast||10|130||bib42|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torrance</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Feeny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Furlong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual analog scales: do they have a role in the measurement of preferences for health states</article-title><source>Med Decis Making</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Med Decis Making||21|329||bib43|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11475389</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torrance</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Feeny</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Furlong</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiattribute utility function for a comprehensive health status classification system. Health Utilities Index Mark 2</article-title><source>Med Care</source><year>1996</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>702</fpage><lpage>722</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Med Care||34|702||bib44|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8676608</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><app-group><app id="app1"><title>Appendix A. Trial IX</title><sec><title>INTERNATIONAL BREAST CANCER STUDY GROUP</title><p>Participants and Authors</p><p><italic>Scientific Committee:</italic> A Goldhirsch, AS Coates (Co-Chairs); <italic>Foundation Council:</italic> J Collins (Pres.), B Th&#x000fc;rlimann (VP), H-J Senn (Treasurer), S Holmberg, J Lindtner, A Veronesi, H Cort&#x000e9;s-Funes; <italic>Coordinating Center, Bern, Switzerland:</italic> M Castiglione-Gertsch (CEO and Study Chair), ML Nasi (Studies Coordinator), G Egli, M Rabaglio, R Maibach, M Iannino Gerber, A Hiltbrunner; <italic>Statistical Center, Harvard School of Public Health and Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, MA, USA:</italic> R Gelber (Group Statistician), K Price (Scientific Director), M Bonetti, H Peterson, D Zahrieh, M Zelen, S Gelber, A O&#x02019;Neill, H Litman; <italic>Data Management Center, Frontier Science &#x00026; Tech. Res. Found., Amherst, NY, USA:</italic> R Hinkle, M Isley, L Blacher (Director), S Lippert, J Celano; <bold>Pathology Office:</bold> B Gusterson, R Bettelheim, R Reed, G Viale, E Mallon; <italic>Quality of Life Office:</italic> J Bernhard, Ch H&#x000fc;rny, H Gusset, N Mathys, B Cliffe; <italic>Centro di Riferimento Oncologico, Aviano, Italy:</italic> D Crivellari, S Monfardini, E Galligioni, MD Magri, A Veronesi, A Buonadonna. S Massarut, C Rossi, E Candiani, A Carbone, R Volpe, M Roncadin, M Arcicasa, F Coran, S Morassut; <italic>Spedali Civili &#x00026; Fondazione Beretta, Brescia, Italy:</italic> E Simoncini, G Marini, P Marpicati, M Braga, P Grigolato, L Lucini; <italic>General Hospital, Gorizia, Italy:</italic> S Foladore, L Foghin, G Pamich, C Bianchi, B Marino, A Murgia, V Milan; <italic>European Institute of Oncology, Milano, Italy:</italic> A Goldhirsch, M Colleoni, G Martinelli, L Orlando, F Nol&#x000e9;, A Luini, R Orecchia, G Viale, F Peccatori, F de Braud, A Costa, S Zurrida, P Veronesi, V Sacchini, V Galimberti, M Intra, U Veronesi; <italic>Ospedale Infermi, Rimini, Italy:</italic> A Ravaioli, D Tassinari, G Oliverio, F Barbanti, P Rinaldi, L Gianni, G Drudi; <italic>Ospedale S Eugenio, Roma, Italy:</italic> M Antimi, M Minelli, V Bellini, R Porzio, E Pernazza, G Santeusanio, LG Spagnoli; <italic>Ospedale S. Bortolo, Vicenza, Italy:</italic> M Magazu, V Fosser, P Morandi, G Scalco, M Balli, M Gion, S Meli, G Torsello; <italic>Swiss Group for Clinical Cancer Research (SAKK) member institutions &#x02013; Inselspital, Bern, Switzerland:</italic> MF Fey, M Castiglione-Gertsch, E Dreher, H Schneider, S Aebi, J Ludin, G Beck, A Haenel, JM L&#x000fc;thi, HJ Altermatt, M Nandedkar, K Buser; <italic>Kantonsspital, St Gallen, Switzerland:</italic> HJ Senn, B Th&#x000fc;rlimann, Ch Oehlschlegel, G Ries, M T&#x000f6;pfer, U Lorenz, O Schiltknecht, B Sp&#x000e4;ti, A Ehrsam, M Bamert, WF Jungi; <italic>Istituto Oncologico della Svizzera Italiana, Bellinzona, Switzerland:</italic> F Cavalli, O Pagani, H Neuenschwander, L Bronz, C Sessa, M Ghielmini, T Rusca, P Rey, J Bernier, E Pedrinis, T Gyr, L Leidi, G Pastorelli, G Caccia, A Goldhirsch; <italic>Kantonsspital, Basel, Switzerland:</italic> R Herrmann, CF Rochlitz, JF Harder, S Bartens, U Eppenberger, J Torhorst; <italic>H&#x000f4;pital des Cadolles, Neuch&#x000e2;tel, Switzerland:</italic> D Piguet, P Siegenthaler, V Barrelet, RP Baumann; <italic>Kantonsspital, Z&#x000fc;rich, Switzerland:</italic> B Pestalozzi, C Sauter, D Fink, M Fehr, U Haller, U Metzger, P Huguenin, R Caduff; <italic>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vandois, Lausanne, Switzerland:</italic> L Perey, S Leyvraz, P Anani, F Gomez, D Wellman, G Chapuis, P De Grandi, P Reymond, M Gillet, JF Delaloye; <italic>H&#x000f4;pital Cantonal, Geneva, Switzerland:</italic> P Alberto, H Bonnefoi, P Sch&#x000e4;fer, F Krauer, M Forni, M Aapro, R Egeli, R Megevand, E Jacot-des-Combes, A Schindler, B Borisch, S Diebold; <italic>Kantonsspital Graub&#x000fc;nden, Chur, Switzerland:</italic> F Egli, P Forrer, A Willi, R Steiner. J Allemann, T R&#x000fc;edi, A Leutenegger, U Dalla Torre; <italic>Australian New Zealand Breast Cancer Trials Group (ANZ BCTG) member institutions &#x02013; Operations Office, University of Newcastle:</italic> JF Forbes, D Lindsay, A Wilson; <italic>Statistical Center, NHMRC CTC, University of Sydney:</italic> RJ Simes, H Dhillon; <italic>The Cancer Council Victoria (previously Anti-Cancer Council of Victoria), Australia:</italic> J Collins, R Snyder, E Abdi, R Basser, WI Burns, M Chipman, J Chirgwin, R Drummond, P Francis, M Green, P Gregory, S Hart, M Henderson, P Kitchen, R McLennan, C Murphy, S Neil, M Pitcher, G Richardson, A Rodger, M Schwarz, P Mitchell, D Joseph, J Griffiths, R Stanley, P Jeal, I Olver, J Zalcberg, G Lindeman, D Finkelde, G Goss, M Steele, B Mann, A Read, I Russell, J Stewart, C Underhill, D Reading; <italic>Auckland Breast Cancer Study Group, Auckland, New Zealand:</italic> RG Kay, VJ Harvey, CS Benjamin, P Thompson, A Bierre, M Miller, B Hochstein, A Lethaby, J Webber, D Porter; <italic>Flinders Medical Centre, Bedford Park, South Australia:</italic> T Malden; Mount Hospital, Perth, Western Australia: G Van Hazel; <italic>Newcastle Mater Misericordiae Hospital Waratah, Newcastle, Australia:</italic> JF Forbes, J Stewart, D Jackson, R Gourlay, J Bishop, S Cox, S Ackland, A Bonaventura, C Hamilton, J Denham, P O&#x02019;Brien, M Back, S Brae, R Muragasu; <italic>Prince of Wales, Randwick, NSW, Australia:</italic> C Lewis; <italic>Royal Adelaide Hospital, Adelaide, Australia:</italic> IN Olver, D Keefe, M Brown, PG Gill, A Taylor, E Yeoh, E Abdi, J Cleary, F Parnis; <italic>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital, Nedlands, Western Australia:</italic> M Byrne, G Van Hazel, J Dewar, M Buck, G Sterrett, D Ingram, D Hastrich, D Joseph, F Cameron; <italic>University of Sydney, Dubbo Base Hospital and Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Sydney, Australia:</italic> MHN Tattersall, AS Coates, F Niesche, R West, S Renwick, J Donovan, P Duval, RJ Simes, A Ng, D Glenn, RA North, J Beith, RG O&#x02019;Connor, M Rice, G Stevens, J Grassby, S Pendlebury, C McLeod, M Boyer, A Sullivan, J Hobbs, D Lind; <italic>Waikato Hospital, Hamilton, New Zealand:</italic> I Kennedy, G Round, J Long; <italic>West Swedish Breast Cancer Study Group, G&#x000f6;teborg, Sweden:</italic> CM Rudenstam, A Wallgren, S Ottosson-L&#x000f6;nn, R Hultborn, G Colldahl-J&#x000e4;derstr&#x000f6;m, E Cahlin, J Mattsson, SB Holmberg, L Ivarsson, O Ruusvik, LG Niklasson, S Dahlin, G Karlsson, B Lindberg, A Sundb&#x000e4;ck, S Bergeg&#x000e5;rdh, H Salander, C Andersson, M Heideman, Y Hessman, O Nelz&#x000e9;n, G Claes, T Ramhult, JH Svensson, P Liedberg, M Suurk&#x000fc;la, S Persson; <italic>Groote Schuur Hospital and University of Cape Town, Cape Town, Rep. of South Africa:</italic> DM Dent, A Gudgeon, E Murray, ID Werner, P Steynor, J Toop, E McEvoy; <italic>Sandton Oncology Center, Johannesburg, Rep. of South Africa:</italic> D Vorobiof, M Chasen, G Fotheringham, G de Muelenaere, B Skudowitz, C Mohammed, A Rosengarten; <italic>The Institute of Oncology, Ljubljana, Slovenia:</italic> J Lindtner, D Erzen, E Majdic, B Stabuc, A Plesnicar, R Golouh, J Lamovec, J Jancar, I Vrhoved, M Kramberger; <italic>Madrid Breast Cancer Group, Madrid, Spain:</italic> H Cort&#x000e9;s-Funes, D Mendiola, J Hornedo, R Colomer, F Cruz Vigo, P Miranda, A Sierra, F Martinez-Tello, A Garzon, S Alonso, A Ferrero.</p></sec></app></app-group></back></article>


