<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><!-- Original-type: cl--><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">14676800</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2395280</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6601367</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjc.6601367</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Phase I clinical trial of the bispecific antibody MDX-H210 (anti-Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI &#x000d7; anti-HER-2&#x0002f;neu) in combination with Filgrastim (G-CSF) for treatment of advanced breast cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Repp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="note10">10</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Ojik</surname><given-names>H H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="note10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Valerius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Groenewegen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wieland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oetzel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stockmeyer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="note11">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenhut</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Steininger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deo</surname><given-names>Y M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Blijham</surname><given-names>G H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kalden</surname><given-names>J R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van de Winkel</surname><given-names>J G J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gramatzki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><sup>1</sup>Department of Medicine III, Division of Hematology&#x0002f;Oncology, University of Erlangen-N&#x000fc;rnberg, Krankenhausstra&#x000df;e 12, Erlangen 91054, Germany</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><sup>2</sup>Department of Internal Medicine and Oncology. University Medical Center Utrecht, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><sup>3</sup>Immunotherapy Laboratory, Department of Immunology, University Medical Center Utrecht, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><sup>4</sup>Department of Gynecology, University of Erlangen-N&#x000fc;rnberg, Germany</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><sup>5</sup>Department of Nuclear Medicine, University of Goettingen, Germany</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><sup>6</sup>Department of Pathology, Hospital Friedrichshafen, Germany</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><sup>7</sup>Medarex Inc., Annandale, New Jersey</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label><sup>8</sup>Genmab, Utrecht, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="aff9"><label>9</label><sup>9</sup>Department of Nuclear Medicine, University of Heidelberg, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>Author for correspondence: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:Roland.Repp@med3.imed.uni-erlangen.de">Roland.Repp@med3.imed.uni-erlangen.de</email></corresp><fn fn-type="present-address" id="note10"><label>10</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this study</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="note11"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Dr Wolfgang Becker sadly passed away recently.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>12</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><volume>89</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2234</fpage><lpage>2243</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>02</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>18</day><month>08</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>09</month><year>2003</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright 2003, Cancer Research UK</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2003</copyright-year><permissions><copyright-holder>Cancer Research UK</copyright-holder></permissions><kwd-group><kwd>MDX-H210</kwd><kwd>Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI</kwd><kwd>HER-2&#x0002f;neu</kwd><kwd>G-CSF</kwd><kwd>immunotherapy</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Breast cancer represents a major public health problem in the Western world. In case of localised disease, cure rates have improved, but in women with metastatic disease results are still disappointing (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib15">Hortobagyi, 1998</xref>). Therefore, novel therapeutical approaches are under investigation. In the last decade, along with new chemotherapeutical drugs, developments in the field of immunology and genetic engineering have raised new perspectives. For example, Trastuzumab (Herceptin&#x000ae;), a humanised IgG1 monoclonal antibody (mAb) with specificity for HER-2&#x0002f;neu, has been approved for patients with metastatic breast cancer. As a single agent, the overall response rate was 15&#x00025; in heavily pretreated patients with HER-2&#x0002f;neu overexpressing metastatic breast cancer (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib6">Cobleigh <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib2">Baselga, 2001</xref>).</p><p>The HER-2&#x0002f;neu gene encodes a 185&#x02013;190&#x02009;000 molecular weight transmembrane protein with tyrosine kinase activity. Overexpressed HER-2&#x0002f;neu has transforming activity, and in a variety of human carcinomas, gene amplification and protein overexpression have been demonstrated. This includes approximately 30&#x00025; of breast cancer, in which it has been correlated with the development of metastases and is associated with poor prognosis (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib29">Slamon <italic>et al</italic>, 1987</xref>). In addition, HER-2&#x0002f;neu has limited expression on normal tissue, suggesting that it may constitute a valuable target for antibody therapy (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib20">Pegram and Slamon, 2000</xref>). Although many mechanisms have been proposed to account for the antitumour activities of therapeutical antibodies &#x02013; including blockade of signalling pathways, activation of apoptosis, and antibody-dependent cell-mediated cytotoxicity (ADCC) &#x02013; the relevance of these mechanisms in humans is still unclear (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib16">Houghton and Scheinberg, 2000</xref>). In mice, the significance of Fc receptor-bearing effector cells is clearly demonstrated by the reduced efficacy of Trastuzumab to arrest tumour growth in animals deficient in activating Fc receptors (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib5">Clynes <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>).</p><p>Three different classes of leucocyte receptors for IgG (Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>R) have been distinguished in humans (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib36">van de Winkel and Capel, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">Ravetch and Bolland, 2001</xref>). Fc gamma receptor I (Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI) (CD64) is constitutively expressed on myeloid precursors in the bone marrow, monocytes&#x0002f;macrophages, immature dendritic cells, and can be induced on polymorphonuclear cell (PMN) by interferon gamma (IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>) or granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib21">Perussia <italic>et al</italic>, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib26">Repp <italic>et al</italic>, 1991</xref>). Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI is unique among Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>R because of its high affinity for IgG, the limited cell expression solely on cytotoxic effector cells, and because of its inherent capacity to trigger cytotoxic effector cells. Furthermore, Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI contains a distinct cytoplasmatic domain, which targets antigens to MHC class II-containing vesicles, and thereby, enhances antigen presentation (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib37">van Vugt <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>).</p><p>Bispecific antibodies (BsAbs) can effectively link target cells to cytotoxic trigger molecules on immune effector cells, and may overcome some of the limitations of conventional mAb (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib28">Segal <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>). For example, high concentrations of serum immunoglobulins compete <italic>in vivo</italic> for binding to Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI on immune effector cells. Hereby, the ability of therapeutical antibodies to trigger Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI could be impaired. To overcome this problem, the BsAb MDX-H210 was constructed by chemical crosslinking of F(ab&#x02032;) fragments from humanised mAb 22 (H22), directed to Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI, and mAb 520C9, to the proto-oncogene product HER-2&#x0002f;neu, respectively. Monoclonal antibody H22 binds to a site distinct from the ligand-binding site, yet effectively triggers Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI-mediated cellular responses (such as phagocytosis, respiratory burst, and ADCC) in the presence of high concentrations of human serum IgG (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib12">Guyre <italic>et al</italic>, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib33">Valerius <italic>et al</italic>, 1993</xref>). To influence the effector cell system specifically, G-CSF was added to the treatment schedule to increase the absolute numbers of PMN, to induce the expression of Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib26">Repp <italic>et al</italic>, 1991</xref>), and to enhance their functional capacity (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib33">Valerius <italic>et al</italic>, 1993</xref>). Preclinical studies demonstrated the binding of MDX-H210 to Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI on G-CSF-primed PMN and to HER-2&#x0002f;neu on SK-BR-3 breast carcinoma cells to be comparable to the respective parental mAb. More importantly, <italic>in vitro</italic> MDX-H210 was highly cytotoxic to HER-2&#x0002f;neu overexpressing cell lines, when Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI-positive PMN from G-CSF-treated patients served as effector cells (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib32">Stockmeyer <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib31">Stockmeyer <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). In addition, studies in an Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI-transgenic animal model reported synergism of Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI-directed BsAb and G-CSF, resulting in antitumour activity and in &#x02018;memory&#x02019; induction (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib14">Honeychurch <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>).</p><p>To analyse whether these preclinical observations may translate into the clinical situation, MDX-H210 in combination with G-CSF was tested in a phase I study. The primary objectives of this trial were to define the maximum tolerated dose (MTD), and to identify the optimal biologically active dose of MDX-H210. The secondary objective was to assess the clinical responses.</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>PATIENTS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Patients</title><p>Patients, aged 18&#x02013;70 years, with stage IV breast cancer were eligible if their primary tumour or metastases were overexpressing HER-2&#x0002f;neu. The expression of HER-2&#x0002f;neu was determined on paraffin-embedded tissues using standard immunohistochemical methods (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib38">Venter <italic>et al</italic>, 1987</xref>). Inclusion in the trial demanded a 2&#x0002b; or 3&#x0002b; membrane staining (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib35">van de Vijver, 2001</xref>). Patients needed to be progressive after at least two standard chemotherapy or hormonal regimens, or one hormonal and one chemotherapy regimen. Sufficient blood cell counts, normal hepatic, and renal function, as well as an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status of &#x0003c;3, and a life expectancy of more than 3 months were required. The protocol was approved by the local Ethics Committee, and written informed consent before treatment was obligatory.</p></sec><sec><title>Study design</title><p>Bispecific antibody MDX-H210 was given as a single, 2-h intravenous (i.v.) infusion, in combination with a fixed subcutaneous (s.c.) dose of 5&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> Filgrastim for 8 days in the afternoon, with a minimum of 4&#x02009;h after the end of MDX-H210 on day 0 (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Treatment schedule</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Day</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>&#x02212;3</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>&#x02212;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>&#x02212;1</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>0</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>4</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Filgrastim s.c. (5&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">x</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">x</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">x</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">x</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">x</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">x</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">x</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">x</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">MDX-H210 i.v. (dose escalation<sup>a</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">x</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote1"><label>a</label><p>MDX-H210 is given as a single 2&#x02009;h infusion with escalating doses from 0.35 up to 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>). Filgrastim was started 3 days before the administration of MDX-H210 to ensure maximal expression of Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI on neutrophils (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib26">Repp <italic>et al</italic>, 1991</xref>). The dose of MDX-H210 was escalated in cohorts of three patients, and not in an individual patient. For the first cohort of patients, Filgrastim was skipped if the absolute neutrophil count (ANC) was higher than 20&#x02009;000&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to prevent toxicity. As no toxicity was observed, the upper limit for ANC was raised to 50&#x02009;000&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> from the second cohort onwards. In the first two cohorts, the same dose of MDX-H210 (0.35&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) was given. Patients treated in the third to tenth cohort received escalating doses of MDX-H210 from 1 up to 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (1, 3.5, 7, 10, 15, 30, 100, and 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>). Dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) was defined as the dose where three or more patients in a cohort of six patients experienced grade III or IV toxicity, and the MTD as the dose level below which DLT occurred. Reassessment for tumour response was performed after 30 days. If patients had an objective response or stable disease, a second treatment on compassionate use basis was possible for patients enrolled during the last period according to an amendment. The overall goals of this phase I trial were to determine toxicity, MTD, pharmacokinetics, and pharmacodynamics of MDX-H210, to describe the biological effects of MDX-210 in combination with Filgrastim, and to elucidate the effects of Filgrastim on immune effector cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Production of MDX-H210</title><p>Bispecific antibody MDX-H210 (Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI &#x000d7; HER-2&#x0002f;neu) was produced by chemically crosslinking F(ab&#x02032;) fragments of mAb 22 against Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI (CD64) with mAb 520C9 against HER-2&#x0002f;neu, as described by <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib11">Glennie <italic>et al</italic> (1987)</xref>. Briefly, F(ab&#x02032;<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>)<sub>2</sub> fragments were produced by limited proteolysis with pepsin, and were then reduced to provide F(ab&#x02032;<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>) with free hinge region SH groups. The SH groups on one of the F(ab&#x02032;<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>)-SH partners were then fully alkylated with excess <italic>o</italic>-phenylendimaleimide (<italic>o</italic>-PDM) to provide free maleimide groups. Finally, the two <italic>o</italic>-PDM and F(ab&#x02032;)-SH preparations F(ab&#x02032;) were combined at a ratio of 1&#x02009;:&#x02009;1 to generate heterochimeric constructs. After purification by size exclusion chromatography, the binding activity of the individual components was verified by flow cytometry, using HER-2&#x0002f;neu-expressing SK-BR-3 cells, Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI-expressing human monocytes, and U937 cells as targets. The bispecific nature of the construct was confirmed by a solid-phase immunoassay. MDX-H210 was produced according to GMP guidelines by Medarex (Medarex Inc., Annandale, NJ, USA), and shipped as a clear colourless liquid in sterile phosphate-buffered saline for i.v. infusion.</p></sec><sec><title>Assessment of adverse reactions</title><p>Patients were hospitalised on day &#x02212;1 and MDX-H210 was administered as a 2-h i.v. infusion on day 0 (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The vital signs were frequently monitored during and for 24&#x02009;h after the administration of the BsAb. Afterwards, patients were checked on an outpatient basis. Laboratory tests were performed daily starting on day &#x02212;3 with additional time points 2, 4, and 8&#x02009;h after the start of MDX-H210 infusion. Toxicity was graded according to the NCI Common Toxicity Criteria. For dose escalation, transient leucopenia, neutropenia without signs of infection, or fever with mild hypotension were not graded as toxicity, because these symptoms were known to be correlated to MDX-H210 infusion, and to recover spontaneously (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib34">Valone <italic>et al</italic>, 1995</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Pharmacokinetics</title><p>Blood samples were obtained before and 2, 4, 8, 24, 48, 72, and 96&#x02009;h after BsAb infusion. Plasma was immediately separated and stored at &#x02212;70&#x000b0;C until analysis. Microtitre plates, coated with goat antimurine IgG, were incubated with serial dilutions of the patient's plasma, or with MDX-H210 diluted in normal human plasma (Nabi Inc., Boca Raton, FL, USA). The captured BsAb was detected by an alkaline phosphatase-conjugated antimurine IgG. Pharmacokinetic analysis was performed using PKPD Tools for Excel Version 1.02 (Charles Minto, Stanford, CA, USA) with a constant i.v. infusion open noncompartmental model.</p></sec><sec><title>Cytokines, tumour markers, and plasma HER-2&#x0002f;neu levels</title><p>Plasma &#x02013; separated and stored as described above &#x02013; was analysed for levels of interleukin (IL)-1<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>, IL-1<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>, IL-2, IL-6, IL-10, IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>, tumour necrosis factor alpha (TNF-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>), G-CSF, soluble IL-2 receptor (sIL-2R), CEA, CA125, and CA15.3 by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay using kits according to the manufacturer's instructions (R&#x00026;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA). Plasma HER-2&#x0002f;neu was measured by enzyme immunosorbent assay using a commercial kit (Chiron Diagnostics, Alameda, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Radioimaging with Technetium-99m (<sup>99m</sup>Tc) MDX-H210</title><p>Antibody labelling was performed according to a published kit-formulated NHS-BAT (NHS&#x0003d;<italic>N</italic>-hydroxysuccinimide and BAT&#x0003d;<italic>bis</italic>(aminoethanethid)type) ester conjugation (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib8">Eisenhut <italic>et al</italic>, 1996</xref>). Briefly, NHS ester of the BAT ligand, 6-(4&#x02032;(4&#x02033;-carboxyphenoxy)butyl)-2,10-dimercapto-2.10-dimethyl-4,8-dizaun-decane was conjugated with MDX-H210 at ambient temperature, and pH ranging from pH 7.0 to pH 8.5. Unreacted or hydrolysed NHS-BAT ester was separated by one or two ultracentrifugation steps (for 15&#x02009;min each). The conjugation yield was 70&#x02013;80&#x00025; independent of pH. Complexation of the BsAb conjugate with <sup>99m</sup>Tc was accomplished using Sn(II)-tartrate as a reducing agent. Within 5&#x02009;min, labelling yield &#x0003e;95&#x00025; was achieved using 1&#x02009;mg BAT-MDX-H210 comprising about three BAT ligands per antibody, and up to 1.5&#x02009;GBq <sup>99m</sup>Tc-pertechnetate. Localisation of MDX-H210 in normal and tumour tissues was investigated in a subset of patients who voluntarily participated, using planar whole-body scans, and single photon emission tomography (SPECT) images of the regions of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Granulocyte scintigraphy with Indium-111-oxine (<sup>111</sup>In)-labelled PMN</title><p>Autologous granulocytes were isolated using a Percoll&#x0002f;plasma gradient, and labelled with <sup>111</sup>In-oxine as described (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib3">Becker <italic>et al</italic>, 1986</xref>). Labelled granulocytes were reinfused either 30&#x02009;min before, or 72&#x02009;h after application of MDX-H210. Dynamic imaging was performed with a gamma camera linked to a computer system during 2&#x02009;h after injection of labelled cells to trace the route of PMN.</p></sec><sec><title>Human antibispecific antibody (HABA) response</title><p>Microtitre plates coated with MDX-H210 were incubated with dilutions of plasma samples. Anti-MDX-H210 antibodies were detected with an alkaline-phosphatase-conjugated goat anti-human IgG Fc-specific probe. The dilution of plasma required to reach the background level (<italic>A</italic><sub>405</sub>&#x0003d;0.1) was determined for samples before infusion, and on days 7, 14, and 30 postinfusion. Human antibispecific antibody levels were expressed as <italic>x</italic>-fold increase over the baseline preinfusion value.</p></sec><sec><title>Assessment of biological effects</title><sec><title>Isolation of effector cells</title><p>A measure of 10&#x02013;20&#x02009;ml of peripheral blood was drawn from patients or healthy donors (HDs) after informed consent. The total leucocyte counts in whole blood were determined on an EPICS&#x02122; Profile flow cytometer (Coulter, Hialeah, FL, USA), and PMN counts in whole blood were calculated from the total leucocyte counts and differentials of Wright-stained blood smears. Isolated PMN were obtained by a method slightly modified from that described in <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib26">Repp <italic>et al</italic> (1991)</xref>. Briefly, citrate anticoagulated blood was layered over a discontinuous Percoll (Seromed, Berlin, Germany) gradient consisting of 70 and 62&#x00025; for HD, and of 68 and 59&#x00025; of Percoll for Filgrastim recipients, respectively. After centrifugation, PMN were collected at the interphase between the two Percoll layers, and mononuclear cells from the Percoll&#x0002f;plasma interphase. The remaining erythrocytes were removed by hypotonic lysis. The purity of PMN was determined by cytospin preparations and exceeded 95&#x00025;, with few contaminating eosinophils and &#x0003c;1&#x00025; mononuclear cells. The viability of cells tested by Trypan blue exclusion was always exceeding 95&#x00025;.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunofluorescence</title><p>Antibodies 32.2 (Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI, CD64; mIgG1) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib12">Guyre <italic>et al</italic>, 1989</xref>), IV.3 (Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RII, CD32; mIgG2b) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib18">Looney <italic>et al</italic>, 1986</xref>), 3G8 (Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RIII, CD16; mIgG1) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib9">Fleit <italic>et al</italic>, 1982</xref>), and 520C9 (HER-2&#x0002f;neu; mIgG1) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib27">Ring <italic>et al</italic>, 1989</xref>) were obtained from Medarex Inc. (Annandale, NJ, USA). Whole blood (100&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l) was incubated with different lineage-specific FITC- or RPE-conjugated antibodies (CD3, CD4, CD8, CD20, CD11b, CD56, CD67) for 30&#x02009;min at 4&#x000b0;C. Afterwards, samples were subjected to FACS&#x000ae; Lysing solution to lyse red blood cells and fix white cells. Cells were then washed three times in phosphate-buffered saline supplemented with 1&#x00025; bovine serum albumin, and analysed on an EPICS&#x02122; Profile flow cytometer (Coulter). For each cell population, the relative fluorescence intensity (RFI) was calculated as the ratio of mean linear fluorescence intensity of relevant to irrelevant, isotype-controlled antibodies.</p></sec><sec><title>ADCC assay</title><p>Antibody-dependent cell-mediated cytotoxicity was performed as described (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib33">Valerius <italic>et al</italic>, 1993</xref>). Briefly, human SK-BR-3 breast carcinoma cells were used as the target. This cell line was obtained from the American Type Culture Collection (Manassas, VA, USA), and kept in an RF10<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> medium consisting of RPMI 1640 medium (Gibco BRL, Paisley, Scotland) supplemented with 10&#x00025; heat-inactivated foetal calf serum, 100&#x02009;U&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> penicillin, 100&#x02009;U&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> streptomycin, and 4&#x02009;m<sc>M L</sc>-glutamine (all Gibco BRL). The target cells were labelled with 200&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>Ci <sup>51</sup>Cr for 2&#x02009;h. After extensive washing with RF10<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>, cells were adjusted to 10<sup>5</sup>&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Isolated PMN, effector-to-target ratio 80&#x02009;:&#x02009;1 (E&#x02009;:&#x02009;T, 80&#x02009;:&#x02009;1), or 50&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l of whole blood as effector source, sensitising antibodies and RF10<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> were added into round-bottom microtitre plates. By adding the target cell suspension, giving a final volume of 200&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l, the assays were started. After 3&#x02009;h at 37&#x000b0;C, assays were stopped by centrifugation, and <sup>51</sup>Cr release from triplicates was measured in counts per minute (c.p.m.). The percentage of cellular cytotoxity was calculated using the formula:</p><p><disp-formula id="equ1"><!-- in formula template--><graphic mime-subtype="gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="89-6601367e1.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>with maximal <sup>51</sup>Cr release determined by adding perchloric acid (3&#x00025; final concentration) to target cells, and basal release measured in the absence of sensitising antibodies and effector cells. Only very low levels of antibody-mediated noncellular cytotoxicity (without effector cells) were observed under these assay conditions (&#x0003c;5&#x00025; specific lysis). Low levels of antibody-independent killing were seen in whole-blood assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Oxidative burst and phagocytosis</title><p>The activity of neutrophil respiratory burst was measured by a method modified from <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib30">Smith and Weidemann (1993)</xref>. In short, 100&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l of whole blood was incubated for 15&#x02009;min with 1&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l of 2&#x02032;,7&#x02032;-dichlorofluorescein diacetate (200&#x02009;m<sc>M</sc> solution in ethanol; Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR, USA). After stimulation for 15&#x02009;min with 1&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> PMA (Sigma, Deisenhofen, Germany), red cell lysis and fixation of white cells was obtained by Q-prep (Coulter). Fluorescence of single cells was measured on an EPICS&#x02122; Profile flow cytometer (Coulter), and the results were analysed comparing mean fluorescence intensity.</p><p>For measurement of phagocytosis, fluorescent polystyrene beads (1.0&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m in diameter; Fluoresbrite, Polysciences Inc., Warrington, PA, USA) were opsonised with human albumin or polyclonal human IgG, respectively, according to the manufacturer's instructions for coupling proteins to carboxylated polystyrene microparticles (Carbodiimide method, Polysciences Inc., Warrington, PA, USA). A measure of 2&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l of 2.5&#x00025; carboxylated microparticles were added to 100&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l whole blood, and incubated for 30&#x02009;min at 37&#x000b0;C. Red cell lysis and fixation of white cells was obtained by Q-prep, and the fluorescence of single cells was measured on an EPICS&#x02122; Profile flow cytometer (Coulter). Polymorphonuclear cell populations were gated according to forward light scatter and perpendicular light scatter. Data were expressed as the percentage of PMN-containing FITC-labelled beads and the mean number of beads per PMN (calculated from the fluorescence intensity of PMN with a single particle ingested).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Group data are reported as mean&#x000b1;standard deviation (s.d.). The differences between groups were analysed by unpaired (or, when appropriate, paired) Student's <italic>t</italic>-tests. Levels of significance are indicated. Data presented correspond to the whole patient population, or is indicated when different.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Patient characteristics</title><p>In all, 30 women with metastatic breast cancer were treated in this trial. Three patients were treated in each of 10 cohorts received escalating doses of MDX-H210 from 0.35 up to 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>. The first and second cohorts were treated with 0.35&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> with an upper limit of the ANC of 20&#x02009;000&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in the first and 50&#x02009;000&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> from the second cohort onwards. Their ages ranged from 40 to 69 years, with a median age of 50 years. The median time from diagnosis was 70.2 months. Patients were heavily pretreated, but had not received previous antibody therapy (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Patient characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><tbody valign="top"><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Patient demographics</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Total number</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Age (years)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">50 (40&#x02013;69)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Median time since diagnosis (months)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">70.2 (7.1&#x02013;181.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Metastatic sites</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">2 (1&#x02013;5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Prior therapy</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Chemotherapy</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="vmk" charoff="50">2 (0&#x02013;6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Radiotherapy</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">1 (0&#x02013;7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Hormonal treatment</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">2 (0&#x02013;4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>ECOG</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">6</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>).</p></sec><sec><title>Pharmacokinetics</title><p>Plasma levels of MDX-H210 were measured up to 4 days after BsAb infusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Plasma levels of MDX-H210. Plasma levels of MDX-H210 in the different patient cohorts were determined 2, 4, 8, 24, 48, 72, and 96&#x02009;h after BsAb infusion. The related pharmacokinetic parameters are described in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Data presented relate to all participating patients treated with &#x02a7e;10&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="89-6601367f1"/></fig>). The mean <italic>t</italic><sub>1&#x0002f;2</sub> values ranged from 4.76&#x02009;h in the 3.5&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> cohort to 17.41&#x02009;h in the 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>. <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> values were correlated with the applied dose, and varied from 0.24&#x02009;mg&#x02009;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at the 1&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> level to 155.7&#x02009;mg&#x02009;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at the 100&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> dose level (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Plasma pharmacokinetics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Dose level<sup>a</sup>(mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold><italic>t</italic><sub>1&#x0002f;2</sub> (h)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold><italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub><sup>b</sup>(<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold><italic>T</italic><sub>max</sub> (h)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>AUC<sup>c</sup>(<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g&#x02009;h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold><italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sup>d</sup></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Vd<sup>e</sup>(l&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Cl<sup>f</sup>(ml&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.24</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4.76</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.28</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9.33</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.180</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.070</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.747</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5.19</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5.95</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">41.90</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.137</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.036</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.300</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10.54</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5.82</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">65.22</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.078</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.063</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.269</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6.09</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6.72</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">70.72</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.117</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.052</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.417</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">30</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">29.34</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">381.06</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.078</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.027</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.134</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9.53</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">155.27</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1937.77</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.073</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.020</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.091</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">200</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">17.41</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">109.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2523.08</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.041</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.049</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.147</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote2"><label>a</label><p>Pharmacokinetic results could not be determined accurately for dose level 0.35&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> because low plasma concentrations of MDX-H210 resulted in very few measurements.</p></fn><fn id="tbfnote3"><label>b</label><p>Maximal concentration.</p></fn><fn id="tbfnote4"><label>c</label><p>Area under the curve.</p></fn><fn id="tbfnote5"><label>d</label><p>Elimination rate constant <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="tbfnote6"><label>e</label><p>Volume of distribution.</p></fn><fn id="tbfnote7"><label>f</label><p>Plasma clearance.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>). At the 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> dose level, infusion of MDX-H210 was temporarily stopped in two patients because of chills and vomiting during the infusion period and restarted after about 1&#x02009;h. Owing to the prolonged infusion time, <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> was lower compared to the 100&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> dose level and was reached after 4&#x02009;h (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Both granulocytes and monocytes were opsonised with MDX-H210 at the end of the infusion, and continued to be &#x02018;armed&#x02019; with MDX-H210 up to 4 days after the infusion of 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Cell-bound MDX-H210. The total number of Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI expressed by circulating cells was determined after incubation with a saturating dose of MDX-H210. Patients were divided into three groups according to treatment with low (0.35&#x02013;7&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>), medium (10&#x02013;30&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>), and high (100&#x02013;200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) doses of MDX-H210. Cell-bound murine IgG without or with this preincubation was determined by incubation with FITC-labelled goat anti-mouse mAb. Significant amount of bound MDX-H210 was found on monocytes and PMN on day 1 in the low-dose group and days 1&#x02013;4 in the medium- and high-dose group (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="89-6601367f2"/></fig>), with a comparable expression of Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI (CD64) on days 0 and 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Toxicity</title><p>In the current study, the combination of MDX-H210 with Filgrastim was well tolerated with minimal to moderate toxicity up to doses of 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref><table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Maximum nonhaematological toxicity</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="18" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Cohort (mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>)&#x0002f;toxicity (grade)</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Dose level (number of patients)</bold></th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>0.35 (<italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;6)</bold></th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1 (<italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;3)</bold></th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3.5 (<italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;3)</bold></th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>7 (<italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;3)</bold></th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>10 (<italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;3)</bold></th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>15 (<italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;3)</bold></th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>30 (<italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;3)</bold></th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>100 (<italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;3)</bold></th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>200 (<italic>n</italic>&#x0003d;3)</bold></th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Toxicity grade</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x0002f;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x0002f;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x0002f;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x0002f;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x0002f;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x0002f;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x0002f;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x0002f;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x0002f;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Nausea</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Vomiting</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Fever</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Chills</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Hepatic</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Respiratory</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Tachycardia</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Hypotension</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Tumour pain</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Redness of skin</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Diarrhoea</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Emotional</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>). No grade IV toxicity occurred. Nonhaematological toxicities consisted mainly of short periods of chills, low-grade fever, nausea, and vomiting all occurring towards the end of the MDX-H210 infusion. Most side effects resolved spontaneously within 8&#x02009;h, or could easily be treated with either acetaminophen or antiemetics. Several patients complained about pain at metastatic sides, possibly related to local inflammatory reactions in tumour tissue induced by the BsAb, or to therapy-related cytokine release. A one- to two-fold increase of alkaline phosphatase and <italic>&#x003b3;</italic>GT was noted, which was maximal after 3&#x02013;4 days, and resolved spontaneously after 1 week. Haematological changes were mainly related to the treatment medication. After the start of Filgrastim an asymptomatic granulocytosis emerged. At 2&#x02009;h after infusion of MDX-H210, granulocytes and monocytes decreased dramatically. However, these values returned to preinfusion levels within approximately 12&#x02009;h. Lymphocytes, which do not express Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI, also demonstrated a significant drop after infusion of MDX-H210. Red blood cell counts and platelet numbers did not significantly change (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Effects of MDX-H210 on circulating white blood cells numbers. In all patients, ANC increased during Filgrastim application. A significant drop of ANC, monocytes, and lymphocytes was observed after infusion of MDX-H210 with a minimum 2&#x02013;4&#x02009;h after start of BsAb infusion. Data presented relate to all participating patients.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="89-6601367f3"/></fig>).</p></sec><sec><title>Receptor expression</title><p>At 72&#x02009;h after the start of Filgrastim, all blood PMN expressed Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI (CD64), declining slowly after G-CSF cessation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Receptor expression of PMN and monocytes during treatment with MDX-H210&#x0002f;Filgrastim. Receptor expression was determined by flow cytometry and expressed as RFI. Changes from days &#x02212;3 to 0 are attributed to the effect of Filgrastim; further changes were noted after start of the 2&#x02009;h during infusion of MDX-H210 on day 0. Data presented relate to all participating patients. <sup>&#x0002a;&#x0002a;</sup>Significant changes (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05) were seen for all tested antigens between days &#x02212;3 and 0 and for all, except CD11b on monocytes between day 0 and the end of MDX-H210 infusion. No significant differences were seen between days &#x02212;3 and 30.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="89-6601367f4"/></fig>). A small increase of Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI expression was seen on monocytes. Within 2&#x02009;h after the start of MDX-H210, a transient decrease of Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI expression was seen on monocytes and PMN, suggesting a more rapid decline of Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI-positive cells. Interestingly, Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RII (CD32) expression on monocytes and PMN was also increased during Filgrastim application, whereas Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RIII (CD16) expression of PMN significantly decreased. The expression of CD67 on PMN, and of CD11b on PMN and monocytes increased after the administration of MDX-H210, probably due to concomitant cytokine release.</p></sec><sec><title>Functional assays</title><sec><title>ADCC, phagocytosis, and oxidative burst</title><p><italic>In vitro</italic> cytotoxicity assays against SK-BR-3 breast cancer cells with isolated PMN demonstrated significantly enhanced cytotoxicity in the presence of MDX-H210 during, but not before or 1 week after the start of Filgrastim application (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>ADCC of isolated PMN via MDX-H210. Isolated PMN from HD were compared with PMN from patients in their capacity to mediate cytotoxicity against SK-BR-3 breast cancer cells in the presence of 0.4&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> MDX-H210 at an E&#x02009;:&#x02009;T ratio of 80&#x02009;:&#x02009;1. Lysis of SK-BR-3 by PMN from patients on days 0, 1, and 4 is significantly higher compared to day &#x02212;3 (before start of Filgrastim) as well as compared to healthy controls (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.005, indicated by <sup>&#x0002a;</sup>). Data presented (mean&#x000b1;s.d.) relate to a subset of 26 patients and 26 HDs.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="89-6601367f5"/></fig>). A small decrease in ADCC activity of PMN on day 1 probably reflected the reduced Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI expression on the remaining circulating PMN.</p><p>Spontaneous cytotoxicity of whole blood, without the addition of MDX-H210 <italic>in vitro</italic> could be demonstrated on day 1 in cohorts treated with doses above 10&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, lasting up to day 4 with doses above 100&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref><fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Spontaneous cytotoxicity. For whole-blood ADCC, citrate anticoagulated, freshly drawn blood was added to <sup>51</sup>Cr-labelled SK-BR-3 cells without the addition of antibody. Patients were divided into three groups according to treatment with low (0.35&#x02013;7&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>), medium (10&#x02013;30&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>), and high (100&#x02013;200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) doses of MDX-H210. Significant enhanced lysis was seen in patients of the high-dose group (day 1 <italic>vs</italic> day 0, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, indicated by <sup>&#x0002a;</sup>). The medium- and high-dose group showed enhanced lysis compared to the low-dose group on day 1 (&#x00023;: <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05; &#x00023;&#x00023;: <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01). Patients treated with high doses of MDX-H210 (&#x02a7e;100&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) showed a trend toward enhanced lysis of SK-BR-3 even 4 days after MDX-H210 infusion, although not statistically significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="89-6601367f6"/></fig>). This spontaneous cytotoxicity documented adequate circulating MDX-H210 levels to induce ADCC, and was in agreement with the measurement of cell-bound MDX-H210 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>).</p><p>Phagocytosis of IgG-coated beads by PMN was increased during Filgrastim application, with a further increase 24&#x02009;h after MDX-H210 infusion. In contrast, phagocytosis of albumin-coated beads did not change (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref><fig id="fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Phagocytosis of latex beads by PMN during treatment with MDX-H210. Phagocytosis of 1.0&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sc>M</sc> fluorescent polystyrene beads, coated with human albumin and polyvalent human IgG, respectively, was measured by flow cytometry. Mean beads per neutrophil from a patient and an HD measured simultaneously were calculated as described in Material and Methods. The relation of beads per PMN of patient to HD is expressed. Phagocytosis of IgG-coated beads is significantly higher on days 0 and 1 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, indicated by <sup>&#x0002a;</sup>) compared to baseline (day &#x02212;3).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="89-6601367f7"/></fig>).</p><p>Baseline oxidative burst, unstimulated and stimulated with PMA, was comparable to HDs (60.5&#x000b1;22.1 <italic>vs</italic> 59.8&#x000b1;29.0 and 151.5&#x000b1;25.8 <italic>vs</italic> 149.6&#x000b1;25.7, respectively). A slight increase of PMA-stimulated oxidative burst was seen during Filgrastim (158.3&#x000b1;23.2; <italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.07), which increased to significant values 24&#x02009;h after the application of MDX-H210 (163.7&#x000b1;21.6; <italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.01), returning to baseline on day 4.</p></sec><sec><title>Cytokines, HABA</title><p>Cytokine plasma concentrations were measured at baseline, and at several time points during the study. Elevated levels of IL-6 and TNF-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> were consistently found during the first hour after MDX-H210 infusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref><fig id="fig8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Cytokine plasma levels. Mean plasma levels of all patients are shown. Plasma levels of IL-6 and TNF-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> increase after the infusion of MDX-H210 with a maximum 2&#x02009;h after the start of infusion. Anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10 is released with a similar time kinetic. G-CSF levels begin to rise after the start of Filgrastim therapy, with a further significant increase after MDX-H210. Plasma levels of sIL-2R and G-CSF were significantly different between days &#x02212;3 and 0 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001). Significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05) of plasma levels before (day 0) and after infusion of MDX-H2120 were seen for TNF-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> (8&#x02009;h and 1 day after start of MDX-H210), IL-6 (2&#x02009;h and 1 day after start of MDX-H210), and sIL-2R (from 2&#x02009;h up to 3 days after start of MDX-H210). No significant release of IL-1<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>, IL-1<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>, IL-2, IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>, and IL-12 was seen.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="89-6601367f8"/></fig>), and related to flu-like symptoms. Peak levels of TNF-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> and IL-6 did not correlate to the dose of BsAb applied. Whereas peak levels of TNF-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> were reached after 2&#x02009;h, IL-6 levels were maximal after 4&#x02009;h. The anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10 also increased, with a maximum after 2&#x02009;h. Granulocyte colony-stimulating factor plasma levels increased during the application of Filgrastim, with a small, additional increase after MDX-H210 infusion. Soluble IL-2 receptor increased after the start of Filgrastim, and reached its maximum after MDX-H210. Serum levels of IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>, IL-1<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>, IL-1<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>, IL-2, and IL-12 were not altered during the study period. Human antibispecific antibody was detected in 19 patients on day 30, in seven of them &#x02a7e;16 times above baseline.</p></sec><sec><title>Scintigraphy</title><p>The number of circulating PMN rapidly decreased after the tart of MDX-H210 infusion. In order to evaluate whether G-CSF-activated PMN could cause additional toxicity, for example, by trapping of PMN in the lung, dynamic granulocyte imaging was performed with <sup>111</sup>In-labelled autologous granulocytes infused 30&#x02009;min prior to MDX-210 infusion. A normal distribution of granulocytes with no abnormal accumulation at any particular site was found (patient &#x00023;3). In two patients, either <sup>111</sup>In-labelled (patient &#x00023;12) or <sup>99m</sup>Tc-HMPAO-labelled autologous granulocytes (patient &#x00023;23) were infused 72&#x02009;h after the administration of MDX-H210. Imaging of the liver, spleen, and bone marrow was normal. However, sites of bone metastasis were spared (patient &#x00023;12), and soft-tissue metastases did not image well. In three patients (patient &#x00023;6, &#x00023;11, and &#x00023;28), 200&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g of <sup>99m</sup>Tc-labelled MDX-H210 was injected simultaneously with unlabelled antibody, resulting in imaging of the liver, spleen, and bone marrow, but without imaging tumour sites. In patient &#x00023;28, however, asymptomatic brain metastases were detected by SPECT. Since these lesions were also seen with <sup>99m</sup>Tc-DTPA SPECT without antibody, a nonspecific imaging due to an altered blood&#x02013;brain barrier has to be considered. In all three patients, activity was detected in the gut, suggesting excretion of labelled MDX-H210 via the bile duct.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Response</title><p>No objective responses were seen in this single dose study in advanced patients. A total of 11 patients had stable, and 19 patients progressive disease at the end of the study period. Three patients with metastatic skin lesions developed an erythema between days 1 and 4 after the administration of MDX-H210. In one of them, a skin biopsy was performed before and 3 days after MDX-H210 application. Immunohistochemical analyses revealed local infiltration of mononuclear cells and PMN at the tumour site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref><fig id="fig9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Immunohistochemical staining of a skin biopsy. A skin biopsy taken 3 days after the administration of MDX-H210 (patient &#x00023;21) was stained for macrophages and PMN. Macrophages (arrow) were stained with a CD68 antibody, and PMN (arrow) with chloroacetate esterase. A skin biopsy from the same patient taken before the start of treatment showed no relevant infiltration with macrophages and PMN.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="89-6601367f9"/></fig>). A control biopsy before the study showed no effector cell infiltration. Patient &#x00023;29 (200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) demonstrated a reduction of CA 15.3&#x02013;40.2&#x00025; (341 <italic>vs</italic> 137&#x02009;E&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and CEA to 37.8&#x00025; (64.9 <italic>vs</italic> 24.1&#x02009;UG&#x02009;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) on day 30, increasing later again. Soluble HER-2&#x0002f;neu levels increased 4&#x02009;h after infusion of MDX-H210 in average by 25.2&#x000b1;23.2&#x02009;U&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.045) in patients treated with 0.35&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, whereas an early drop was seen in most of the patients treated with higher doses (mean decrease of 32.9&#x000b1;36.7&#x02009;U&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001). The mean decrease of all patients was maximal on day 7 (mean decrease of 34.8&#x000b1;79.0&#x02009;U&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; <italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.034), while on day 30 this was less impressive (a mean decrease of 26.2&#x000b1;76.8&#x02009;U&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; <italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.083) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10</xref><fig id="fig10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Plasma levels of soluble HER-2&#x0002f;neu. Soluble HER-2&#x0002f;neu levels were measured during treatment with MDX-H210 and Filgrastim. A significant decrease of sHer-2&#x0002f;neu was seen between 4&#x02009;h after the start of infusion and 7 days (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05). Data are presented as mean&#x000b1;s.e.m. of all patients.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="89-6601367f10"/></fig>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Based on our preclinical data (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib32">Stockmeyer <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>), the combination of MDX-H210 and G-CSF was analysed in a phase I study, performed in 30 heavily pretreated breast carcinoma patients overexpressing HER-2&#x0002f;neu. This phase I trial was designed to determine the tolerability, safety, and MTD of BsAb MDX-H210 (anti-Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI &#x000d7; anti-HER-2&#x0002f;neu) in combination with Filgrastim. Aside from clinical toxicity, we focused on the biological activity, and pharmacokinetics of the combination. Treatment was generally well tolerated, with a successful dose escalation of MDX-H210 up to 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> without reaching MTD. Nonhaematologic toxicity appeared within the first 2&#x02013;4&#x02009;h, was mainly infusion related, and consisted of transient fever, chills, nausea and vomiting, and hypotension. Tumour necrosis factor alpha and IL-6 levels increased timely related to the side effects with a maximum after 2 and 4&#x02009;h, respectively. Interestingly, toxicity appeared not to be dose related, in line with comparable peak levels of IL-6 and TNF-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> in all cohorts above 0.35&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>. Despite high peak levels of IL-6 and TNF-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>, exceeding 300 pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, side effects were only moderate, which might be due to the absence of IL-1 and IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib39">Waage <italic>et al</italic>, 1989</xref>), and to antagonistic effects of an early release of anti-inflammatory cytokines such as IL-10. Furthermore, G-CSF might contribute to an enhanced anti-inflammatory cytokine response (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib13">Hartung <italic>et al</italic>, 1995</xref>). Concomitant administration of MDX-H210 and G-CSF seems to be safe in our study as well as in a multidose trial with MDX-H210 (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib24">Pullarkat <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>). Interestingly, the side effects in our study were similar to other MDX-H210 studies, with other cytokines such as IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> or GM-CSF (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib23">Posey <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib17">Lewis <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). On the other hand, the addition of G-CSF led to unacceptable toxicity in combination with an anti-Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI &#x000d7; anti-EGFR BsAb (MDX-447) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib22">Pfister <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>).</p><p>As MDX-H210 is designed to trigger phagocytic cells, the transient drop in ANC and monocytes was not surprising. Additional haematological changes were a more than 10-fold increase of circulating PMN, due to Filgrastim, and all PMN expressed Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI. Pulmonary toxicity, resulting from entrapment of activated Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI-positive PMN in the lungs, was considered to be a potential risk from G-CSF administration. Therefore, in some patients imaging with <sup>111</sup>In-labelled granulocytes was performed. However, we did not observe increased clinical pulmonary toxicity nor did we observe abnormal accumulation of PMN in the lung. Three patients were retreated because of stable disease after 30 days. Strikingly less side effects were noted in these patients. This desensitisation phenomenon was also reported in other clinical trials with BsAb or mAb (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib19">Maloney <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib7">Dillman, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib23">Posey <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib24">Pullarkat <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>).</p><p>In patients with advanced cancer, the cytotoxic capabilities of effector cells are often impaired (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib4">Brittenden <italic>et al</italic>, 1996</xref>). In contrast, granulocyte function was not diminished in our patients with regard to phagocytosis and oxidative burst, and was even further enhanced during G-CSF treatment. Isolated PMN were highly cytotoxic <italic>in vitro</italic> in the presence of MDX-H210, concomitant with the induction of Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI expression during G-CSF application. Maximum lysis was achieved at a concentration of 0.4&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, with reduced efficacy at higher doses, probably resulting from inhibition by monomeric binding of MDX-H210 to effector and tumour cells (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib32">Stockmeyer <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>). Plasma concentrations of MDX-H210 exceeding 1&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> were already found in the 3.5&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> cohort; with increasing peak levels and AUC up to 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> with a serum half-life of 4&#x02013;10&#x02009;h, increasing to 17&#x02009;h at doses of 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>. Granulocytes and monocytes of patients treated at the 200&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> cohort documented complete saturation of Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI by BsAb for up to 4 days. These &#x02018;armed&#x02019; effector cells are functionally active with high cytolytic activity in an ADCC assay without additional MDX-H210.</p><p><italic>In vivo</italic>, erythema of involved skin areas in three patients and pain at tumour sites after antibody infusion suggest the induction of an inflammatory response within tumour lesions. In addition, biopsies from a metastatic skin lesion revealed infiltration with monocytes and PMN. Despite the fact that we were able to achieve adequate plasma concentrations for up to 4 days, it was unlikely that optimal concentrations of MDX-H210 were achieved within the tumour, since unfortunately we could not detect MDX-H210 in histological sections (data not shown), and failed to demonstrate tumour imaging using technetium-labelled MDX-H210. In contrast, good imaging of the Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI-positive effector cell pool was seen. One way of overcoming this limitation, probably caused by the preferential binding of MDX-H210 to effector cells, could be to either start Filgrastim after the administration of MDX-H210 to reduce the accessible Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI-binding sites, or by altering the pharmacokinetic properties of MDX-H210 to achieve high blood levels over a longer period of time. One way could be repetitive doses of MDX-H210, which might be limited by rapid HABA induction seen in more than half of the patients in this study. A BsAb construct with two fully humanised parts could help to overcome this problem. Compared to complete IgG antibodies, MDX-H210 has a very short half-life that cannot be fully explained by the reduced size of about 100&#x02009;kDa. Since MDX-H210 lacks binding sites for the neonatal Fc receptor FcRn, which is critical for the serum half-life of IgG, engineered BsAb with altered affinities for FcRn might also help to increase the serum half-life (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib10">Ghetie and Ward, 2000</xref>). Another possibility of improving the off rate of the antibody from tumour sites is to design BsAb with an increased affinity for the tumour target, although a very high affinity could lead to impaired tumour penetration (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib1">Adams <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>).</p><p>The intention of this trial with BsAb MDX-H210 was to utilise PMN as additional effector cells for breast cancer immunotherapy. This large cell population can be expanded and activated by G-CSF, which also induced Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI expression. Fortunately, concomitant treatment with MDX-H210 and Filgrastim did not lead to limiting toxicity. Although no objective response could be documented in these heavily pretreated patients with progressive breast cancer, biological effects were noted. Thus, MDX-H210 can be safely administered in combination with Filgrastim, and leads to highly efficient, expanded effector cell populations that may well have a significant therapeutic impact when employed in an optimised extended treatment schedule.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are indebted to Medarex Inc. (Annandale, NJ, USA) for the excellent support of the phase I trial. We thank Dr MW Fanger and Dr PM Guyre (Dartmouth Medical School, Lebanon, NH, USA) for stimulating discussions. Very gratefully we acknowledge the excellent technical assistance of Christiane Asche, Barbara Bock, Cora Damen, Steffi Gehr, Annemiek van Oers, and Hans Vermeulen. This work was supported by grants from the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (Va 124&#x0002f;1-3), the Dutch Cancer Society &#x02018;KWF.&#x02019; (UU97-1517), and Medarex Inc., Annandale, NJ, USA.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Schier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Horak</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alpaugh</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High affinity restricts the localization and tumor penetration of single-chain fv antibody molecules</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>4750</fpage><lpage>4755</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||61|4750||bib1|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11406547</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baselga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical trials of Herceptin (trastuzumab)</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>2001</year><volume>37</volume><supplement>Suppl. 1</supplement><fpage>S18</fpage><lpage>S24</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Eur J Cancer||37|S18||bib2|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11167087</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischbach</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiners</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Borner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three-phase white blood cell scan: diagnostic validity in abdominal inflammatory diseases</article-title><source>J Nucl Med</source><year>1986</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1109</fpage><lpage>1115</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Nucl Med||27|1109||bib3|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3088223</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brittenden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heys</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eremin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural killer cells and cancer</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>1996</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1226</fpage><lpage>1243</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer||77|1226||bib4|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8608497</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clynes</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Towers</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Presta</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravetch</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory Fc receptors modulate <italic>in vivo</italic> cytotoxicity against tumor targets</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Nat Med||6|443||bib5|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10742152</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cobleigh</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fehrenbacher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolter</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Shak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Slamon</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multinational study of the efficacy and safety of humanized anti-HER2 monoclonal antibody in women who have HER2-overexpressing metastatic breast cancer that has progressed after chemotherapy for metastatic disease</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1999</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2639</fpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||17|2639||bib6|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10561337</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dillman</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infusion reactions associated with the therapeutic use of monoclonal antibodies in the treatment of malignancy</article-title><source>Cancer Metastasis Rev</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Metastasis Rev||18|465||bib7|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10855789</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenhut</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Behr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Elser</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Strittmatter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinstraesser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Valerius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Repp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Deo</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bifunctional NHS-BAT ester for antibody conjugation and stable technetium-99m labeling: conjugation chemistry, immunoreactivity and kit formulation</article-title><source>J Nucl Med</source><year>1996</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>362</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Nucl Med||37|362||bib8|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8667077</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleit</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Unkeless</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human neutrophil Fc gamma receptor distribution and structure</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1982</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>3275</fpage><lpage>3279</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Proc Natl Acad Sci USA||79|3275||bib9|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghetie</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple roles for the major histocompatibility complex class I-related receptor FcRn</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2000</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>766</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Annu Rev Immunol||18|739||bib10|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10837074</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glennie</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Worth</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation and performance of bispecific F(ab&#x02032;<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>)2 antibody containing thioether-linked Fab&#x02032;<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> fragments</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1987</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>2367</fpage><lpage>2375</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunol||139|2367||bib11|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2958547</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guyre</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Graziano</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morganelli</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanger</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monoclonal antibodies that bind to distinct epitopes on Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI are able to trigger receptor function</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1989</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>1650</fpage><lpage>1655</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunol||143|1650||bib12|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2474608</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartung</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Docke</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gantner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Volk</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of granulocyte colony-stimulating factor treatment on <italic>ex vivo</italic> blood cytokine response in human volunteers</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1995</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>2482</fpage><lpage>2489</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Blood||85|2482||bib13|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7537116</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honeychurch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tutt</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Valerius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Heijnen</surname><given-names>IAFM</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Winkel</surname><given-names>JGJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Glennie</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic efficacy of Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI&#x0002f;CD64-directed bispecific antibodies in B-cell lymphoma</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2000</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>3544</fpage><lpage>3552</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Blood||96|3544||bib14|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11071653</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hortobagyi</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of breast cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>974</fpage><lpage>984</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'N Engl J Med||339|974||bib15|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9753714</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheinberg</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monoclonal antibody therapies &#x02013; a &#x02018;constant&#x02019; threat to cancer</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Nat Med||6|373||bib16|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10742135</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Waugh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyre</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanger</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Curnow</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ernstoff</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetic-pharmacodynamic relationships of the bispecific antibody MDX-H210 when administered in combination with interferon gamma: a multiple-dose phase-I study in patients with advanced cancer which overexpresses HER-2&#x0002f;neu</article-title><source>J Immunol Methods</source><year>2001</year><volume>248</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunol Methods||248|149||bib17|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11223076</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Looney</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human monocytes and U937 cells bear two distinct Fc receptors for IgG</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1986</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>1641</fpage><lpage>1647</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunol||136|1641||bib18|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2936805</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Grillo-Lopez</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bodkin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilder</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Neidhart</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Janakiraman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Foon</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Liles</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dallaire</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Royston</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IDEC-C2B8 (Rituximab) anti-CD20 monoclonal antibody therapy in patients with relapsed low-grade non-Hodgkin's lymphoma</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1997</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>2188</fpage><lpage>2195</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Blood||90|2188||bib19|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9310469</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pegram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Slamon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological rationale for HER2&#x0002f;neu (c-erbB2) as a target for monoclonal antibody therapy</article-title><source>Semin Oncol</source><year>2000</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Semin Oncol||27|13||bib20|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perussia</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dayton</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanning</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Trinchieri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immune interferon induces the receptor for monomeric IgG1 on human monocytic and myeloid cells</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1983</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>1092</fpage><lpage>1113</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Exp Med||158|1092||bib21|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6225822</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Belt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Motzer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Winston</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Metz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Curnow</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A phase I trial of the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR)-directed bispecific antibody (BsAb) MDX-447 in patients with solid tumors</article-title><source>Proc Am Soc Clin Oncol</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>433a</fpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Proc Am Soc Clin Oncol||18|433a||bib22|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Posey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Raspet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Deo</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazumder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A pilot trial of GM-CSF and MDX-H210 in patients with erbB-2-positive advanced malignancies</article-title><source>J Immunother</source><year>1999</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunother||22|371||bib23|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10404439</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pullarkat</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Deo</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Spears</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Curnow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Groshen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A phase I study of a HER2&#x0002f;neu bispecific antibody with granulocyte-colony-stimulating factor in patients with metastatic breast cancer that overexpresses HER2&#x0002f;neu</article-title><source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source><year>1999</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Immunol Immunother||48|9||bib24|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10235484</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravetch</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IgG Fc receptors</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Annu Rev Immunol||19|275||bib25|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11244038</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Repp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Valerius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sendler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gramatzki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iro</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalden</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Platzer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neutrophils express the high affinity receptor for IgG (Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI, CD64) after <italic>in vivo</italic> application of recombinant human granulocyte colony-stimulating factor</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1991</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>889</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Blood||78|885||bib26|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1714327</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh-Ma</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjorn</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tringale</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution and physical properties of BCA200, a Mr 200,000 glycoprotein selectively associated with human breast cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1989</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>3070</fpage><lpage>3080</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||49|3070||bib27|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2470501</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bispecific antibodies in cancer therapy</article-title><source>Curr Opin Immunol</source><year>1999</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>558</fpage><lpage>562</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Curr Opin Immunol||11|558||bib28|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508714</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slamon</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human breast cancer: correlation of relapse and survival with amplification of the HER-2&#x0002f;neu oncogene</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1987</year><volume>235</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Science||235|177||bib29|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3798106</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weidemann</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Further characterization of the neutrophil oxidative burst by flow cytometry</article-title><source>J Immunol Methods</source><year>1993</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunol Methods||162|261||bib30|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8315293</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stockmeyer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsasser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dechant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Repp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gramatzki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Glennie</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Winkel</surname><given-names>JGJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Valerius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of G-CSF- or GM-CSF-stimulated tumor cell killing by Fc receptor-directed bispecific antibodies</article-title><source>J Immunol Methods</source><year>2001</year><volume>248</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunol Methods||248|103||bib31|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11223072</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stockmeyer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Valerius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Repp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Heijnen</surname><given-names>IAFM</given-names></name><name><surname>Buhring</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Deo</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalden</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gramatzki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Winkel</surname><given-names>JGJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preclinical studies with Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>R bispecific antibodies and granulocyte colony-stimulating factor-primed neutrophils as effector cells against HER-2&#x0002f;neu overexpressing breast cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>696</fpage><lpage>701</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||57|696||bib32|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9044847</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valerius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Repp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>TPM</given-names></name><name><surname>Berthold</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Platzer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalden</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gramatzki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Winkel</surname><given-names>JGJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of the high-affinity receptor for IgG (Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RI; CD64) in enhanced tumor cell cytotoxicity of neutrophils during granulocyte colony-stimulating factor therapy</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1993</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>931</fpage><lpage>939</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Blood||82|931||bib33|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7687898</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valone</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyre</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Memoli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Deo</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Graziano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mrozek-Orlowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wardwell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyre</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Marley</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Arzivu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanger</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phase Ia&#x0002f;Ib trial of bispecific antibody MDX-210 in patients with advanced breast or ovarian cancer that overexpresses the proto-oncogene HER-2&#x0002f;neu</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1995</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2281</fpage><lpage>2292</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||13|2281||bib34|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7545221</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van de Vijver</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the need and appropriate method for testing for the human epidermal growth factor receptor-2 (HER2)</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>2001</year><volume>37</volume><supplement>Suppl. 1</supplement><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Eur J Cancer||37|11||bib35|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11342195</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van de Winkel</surname><given-names>JGJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Capel</surname><given-names>PJA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human IgG Fc receptor heterogeneity: molecular aspects and clinical implications</article-title><source>Immunol Today</source><year>1993</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Immunol Today||14|215||bib36|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8517920</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Vugt</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleijmeer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Keler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeelenberg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dijk</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leusen</surname><given-names>JHW</given-names></name><name><surname>Geuze</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Winkel</surname><given-names>JGJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Fc<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>RIa (CD64) ligand binding chain triggers major histocompatibility complex class II antigen presentation independently of its associated FcR <italic>&#x003b3;</italic>-chain</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1999</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>808</fpage><lpage>817</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Blood||94|808||bib37|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10397749</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venter</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuzi</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gullick</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of the c-erbB-2 oncoprotein in human breast carcinomas: immunohistological assessment correlates with gene amplification</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1987</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Lancet||2|69||bib38|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waage</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandtzaeg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Halstensen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kierulf</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Espevik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The complex pattern of cytokines in serum from patients with meningococcal septic shock. Association between interleukin 6, interleukin 1, and fatal outcome</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1989</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Exp Med||169|333||bib39|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2783334</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


