<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><!-- Original-type: cl--><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">12799625</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2741109</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6600992</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjc.6600992</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Clinical aspects of a phase I trial of 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid (DMXAA), a novel antivascular agent</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jameson</surname><given-names>M B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P I</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>B C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>B D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>V J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>D J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCrystal</surname><given-names>M R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bellenger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gumbrell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Halbert</surname><given-names>G W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kestell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><sup>1</sup>Department of Clinical Oncology, Auckland Hospital, Private Bag 92024, Auckland, New Zealand</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><sup>2</sup>Auckland Cancer Society Research Centre, University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019, Auckland, NZ</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><sup>3</sup>Drug Development Office of Cancer Research UK, 10 Cambridge Tce, London NW1 4JL, UK</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><sup>4</sup>Cancer Research UK Formulation Unit, University of Strathclyde, 204 George St, Glasgow G1 1XW, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>Author for correspondence: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:jameson@waikatodhb.govt.nz">jameson@waikatodhb.govt.nz</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>06</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>16</day><month>06</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><volume>88</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1844</fpage><lpage>1850</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2002</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>04</month><year>2003</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright 2003, Cancer Research UK</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2003</copyright-year><permissions><copyright-holder>Cancer Research UK</copyright-holder></permissions><kwd-group><kwd>DMXAA</kwd><kwd>antivascular</kwd><kwd>phase I clinical trial</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Targeting tumour vasculature as a treatment for cancer is the subject of much research, with most effort currently directed at angiogenesis inhibitors. Yet therapies that interrupt existing tumour vasculature and result in haemorrhagic necrosis of tumours have been investigated for over a century and were mostly associated with bacterial infections or their toxins (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib9">Chaplin and Dougherty, 1999</xref>). William Coley, who pursued the method avidly from 1891 (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib16">Council on Pharmacy and Chemistry, 1934</xref>), achieved significant cure rates, especially in sarcoma and lymphoma, using various bacterial toxins both for advanced disease and as adjuvant therapy (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib14">Coley-Nauts <italic>et al</italic>, 1953</xref>). Coley's toxins were abandoned in favour of radiotherapy, but more recent clinical studies with bacterial endotoxins have shown modest antitumour activity, although systemic toxicity remains dose-limiting (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib41">Otto <italic>et al</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib18">DeVore <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>).</p><p>In 1947, investigators at the National Cancer Institute observed that a toxin from the bacterium <italic>Serratia marcescens</italic> acutely and irreversibly reduced blood flow to sarcomas in mice, while blood flow to muscle recovered within 18&#x02009;h (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib1">Algire <italic>et al</italic>, 1947</xref>). The induction of tumour necrosis factor (TNF) by bacterial toxins was later shown to be the cause of haemorrhagic necrosis in tumours (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib8">Carswell <italic>et al</italic>, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib39">Old, 1985</xref>). Clinical trials of recombinant human TNF were unable to deliver therapeutic doses systemically because of toxicity (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib55">Spriggs and Yates, 1992</xref>), but TNF is highly effective in conjunction with chemotherapy in isolated limb perfusion for melanoma and sarcoma, where it has been shown to have selective tumour vascular effects (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib34">Lejeune <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib50">Ruegg <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib20">Eggermont and ten Hagen, 2001</xref>).</p><p>Nonbacterial, tumour vascular-targeting agents could have advantages over bacterial products in terms of toxicity and pharmacology. One such agent, flavone acetic acid (FAA), showed remarkable anticancer activity in murine models (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib38">O'Dwyer <italic>et al</italic>, 1987</xref>) but its activity was minimal in clinical trials, although these were conducted when it was thought to be directly cytotoxic and its indirect mechanisms of antitumour action were poorly understood (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib29">Kerr and Kaye, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib5">Bibby, 1991</xref>). Further preclinical studies at the Auckland Cancer Society Research Centre (ACSRC) showed that FAA induced TNF production, acute tumour vascular collapse, haemorrhagic necrosis of tumours and enhanced activity of immune effector cells (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib10">Ching and Baguley, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib53">Smith <italic>et al</italic>, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib21">Finlay <italic>et al</italic>, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib63">Zwi <italic>et al</italic>, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib62">1992</xref>) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib66">Zwi <italic>et al</italic>, 1990 ID: 286</xref>). Few appropriate pharmacodynamic (PD) studies were performed in the clinical trials of FAA, so it is not known whether it has significant antivascular or immunological activity in humans. However, <italic>in vitro</italic> studies suggested a species difference in antitumour activity, because FAA induced TNF in murine, but not human, peripheral blood mononuclear cells (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib11">Ching <italic>et al</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib45">Philpott <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>).</p><p>5,6-Dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid (DMXAA), a new analogue of FAA developed in the ACSRC, showed greater activity and 12-fold higher dose-potency than FAA in murine tumour models (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib47">Rewcastle <italic>et al</italic>, 1991</xref>) and appeared to overcome the species difference in <italic>in vitro</italic> TNF production (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib11">Ching <italic>et al</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib45">Philpott <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>). Dose-limiting toxicity in mice was consistent with hypotension, and was not strictly related to TNF production (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib44">Philpott <italic>et al</italic>, 1995</xref>). While DMXAA proceeded into clinical development because of this favourable profile, further studies in animal tumour models have demonstrated synergistic interactions between DMXAA with radiotherapy (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib61">Wilson <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>), chemotherapy (particularly taxanes) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib46">Pruijn <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib26">Horsman <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib60">Wilson and Baguley 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib52">Siim <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>), bioreductive cytotoxic drugs (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib13">Cliffe <italic>et al</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib33">Lash <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>), radioimmunotherapy (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib42">Pedley <italic>et al</italic>, 1996</xref>), antibody-directed enzyme prodrug therapy (ADEPT) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib43">Pedley <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>), thalidomide (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib7">Cao <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>) and immunotherapy (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib27">Kanwar <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>).</p><p>Cancer Research UK selected DMXAA for two parallel phase I trials with different schedules, one in the UK using a weekly administration schedule (at Mt Vernon Hospital, Northwood, and Bradford Royal Infirmary, Bradford) and the other in Auckland, NZ, dosing every 3 weeks. The objectives of the NZ study were to determine the toxicity of DMXAA, its maximum tolerated dose (MTD), pharmacokinetics (PK), selected PD end points and, as a secondary objective, antitumour efficacy. A protocol amendment permitted evaluation of changes in tumour blood flow by dynamic magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and the findings (including both UK and NZ trial patients) have recently been published (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib23">Galbraith <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>). This report focuses on clinical aspects of the NZ trial; PD and PK aspects, due to their complexity, will be reported separately.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Patients</title><p>Eligibility criteria included: patients &#x02a7e;18 years with histologically or cytologically proven cancer refractory or not amenable to conventional therapy; WHO performance status of 0&#x02013;2; life expectancy &#x0003e;3 months; haemoglobin &#x02a7e;9&#x02009;g&#x02009;dl<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, WBC &#x02a7e;3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>9</sup>&#x02009;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, platelets &#x02a7e;100 &#x000d7; 10<sup>9</sup>&#x02009;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; creatinine &#x02a7d;130&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>mol&#x02009;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; bilirubin within normal limits, ALT and alkaline phosphatase &#x0003c;2 &#x000d7; upper limit of normal unless due to liver and&#x0002f;or bone metastases; coagulation (international normalised ratio (INR) and activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT)) within normal limits; not pregnant or lactating (adequate contraception if capable of child-bearing); no anticancer therapy within 4 weeks (6 weeks for nitrosoureas and mitomycin C); no other serious medical conditions, uncontrolled infection or serious infection within 28 days; no glucocorticoid treatment in excess of physiological replacement doses within 2 weeks; and no concurrent malignancies with the exception of cone-biopsied cervical intraepithelial neoplasia and adequately treated basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin. All patients gave written informed consent and the regional ethics committee approved the study.</p></sec><sec><title>Drug administration</title><p>DMXAA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Structure of DMXAA.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="88-6600992f1"/></fig>) was formulated as a 20&#x02009;mg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> solution of the sodium salt in 0.1&#x02009;<sc>M</sc> phosphate buffer, pH 7.7 and stored in amber glass ampoules at room temperature. Exposure of DMXAA to direct sunlight was avoided to prevent decarboxylation and precipitation (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib48">Rewcastle <italic>et al</italic>, 1990</xref>). A more concentrated formulation (100&#x02009;mg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in 0.02&#x02009;<sc>M</sc> phosphate buffer, pH 7.9) was developed in order to reduce infusion volumes at higher doses. The drug was administered every 3 weeks as a 20-min i.v. infusion (made up to a minimum volume of 100&#x02009;ml with normal saline) using Imed 960A or Gemini PC-2 infusion pumps (Alaris Medical Systems, San Diego, CA, USA). Patients could receive a maximum of six courses if static disease was seen, but if responding they could continue to maximum response plus two courses up to a maximum of 12 courses. No intrapatient dose escalation was permitted, but when a partial response was observed a protocol amendment was introduced to allow patients treated at lower doses to re-enter the trial at a higher dose level (if still eligible) to gain the opportunity of therapeutic benefit.</p></sec><sec><title>Dose escalation</title><p>The starting dose of 6&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> was one-tenth of the LD<sub>10</sub> in mice. Dose escalation was planned to follow a modified Fibonacci scheme, but could be modified by PK data and the clinical judgement of the investigators and a protocol amendment permitted results from the parallel UK phase I study to influence dose escalation. Three patients were planned at each dose level and three additional patients were to be entered if any of the following toxicities occurred: neutrophil nadir &#x0003c;1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>9</sup>&#x02009;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; platelet nadir &#x0003c;75 &#x000d7; 10<sup>9</sup>&#x02009;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; grade 2 neurologic or cardiac toxicity or an increase of one grade of peripheral neuropathy if present at baseline; grade 3 vomiting not responding to symptomatic treatment or other grade 3 nonhaematological toxicity. The MTD was defined as the dose below that at which two of three patients suffered a dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) due to the drug (neutrophil nadir &#x0003c;0.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>9</sup>&#x02009;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> or platelet nadir &#x0003c;25 &#x000d7; 10<sup>9</sup>&#x02009;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> or Grade 2 neurotoxicity or Grade 3 other nonhaematological toxicity (excluding alopecia and nausea)). When DLT was reached, an additional three patients were to be treated at the previous dose level to determine the recommended dose for phase II trials.</p></sec><sec><title>Patient assessments</title><p>Prior to treatment and weekly while on trial each patient had a history taken, clinical examination and blood tests including complete blood count (CBC) and differential, INR, APTT, chemistry and urinalysis. Complete blood count was repeated 24 and 72&#x02009;h after course 1 and 24&#x02009;h after course 4. International normalised ratio and APTT were repeated 4&#x02009;h after DMXAA infusion on courses 1 and 4. Blood pressure and heart rate were monitored from 30&#x02009;min before each infusion to 6&#x02009;h afterwards. On course 1 (and on course 2 in one patient at each dose level) patients were hospitalised for 24&#x02009;h to monitor toxicity and PK. Later in the trial, 24-h urine collections were made immediately prior to and after DMXAA administration, in order to evaluate changes in creatinine clearance. The National Cancer Institute of Canada Clinical Trials Group (NCIC-CTG) Expanded Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) was used to assess adverse events.</p><p>An electrocardiograph (ECG) was performed prior to trial entry. When transient prolongation of the cardiac corrected QT interval (QT<sub>c</sub>) was noticed in a patient after treatment with DMXAA at 2000&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, subsequent patients had serial ECGs (in two patients) or ambulatory digital Holter ECG monitoring (in 12 patients) to evaluate acute changes in the QT<sub>c</sub>. The QT<sub>c</sub> was calculated using Bazett's formula (QT<sub>c</sub>&#x0003d;QT&#x0002f;square root of preceding R-R interval) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib32">Kligfield <italic>et al</italic>, 1996</xref>) and was measured in multiple ECG traces over the first 6&#x02013;24&#x02009;h after DMXAA administration.</p><p>Tumour response was assessed clinically each week, by plain radiographs every 3 weeks and by computed tomography (CT) or ultrasound scans every 6 weeks. A complete response was defined as the disappearance of all disease on two assessments at least 4 weeks apart. A partial response was defined as at least 50&#x00025; decrease in the sum of the products of bidimensional measurements (or the sum of maximum diameters of lesions where bidimensional measurements were not feasible) of defined measurable lesions on two assessments at least 4 weeks apart, and no lesion should have progressed and no new lesions appeared. No change (static disease) was defined as less than 50&#x00025; decrease and less than 25&#x00025; increase in these measurements.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Patient characteristics</title><p><xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Patient characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Characteristic</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>No. of patients</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Total patients</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">63</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Gender</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Male</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">21</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Female</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">42</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Age (years)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Median</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">55</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Range</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">24&#x02013;75</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>WHO performance status</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;0</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">22</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">28</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Tumour primary site</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Colon&#x0002f;rectum</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">20</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Ovary</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Melanoma</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Lung</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Breast</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Cervix</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Unknown primary</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Pancreas</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Oesophagus</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Kidney</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Soft-tissue sarcoma</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Other</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Previous treatment</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Chemotherapy</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">55</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Radiotherapy</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">25</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Biotherapy&#x0002f;hormones</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;None</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap> summarises the gender, age, performance status, diagnosis and prior systemic therapy of patients enrolled onto the trial. A total of 161 courses were administered to 63 patients (60 individual patients, three of whom were re-enrolled at a higher dose level and evaluated as new patients). The median number of courses was 2 (range 1&#x02013;8).</p></sec><sec><title>Dose escalation</title><p><xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Dose escalation schedule</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="char" char="."/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>DMXAA dose level (mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>No. of patients</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>No. of courses</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Patients with DLT</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">10.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">20.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">40.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">81.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">160</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">240</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">360</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">500</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">19</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">650</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">850</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1100</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1375</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1650</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2000</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2600</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">3100</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">3700</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4900</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote1"><label/><p>DLT&#x0003d;dose-limiting toxicity. </p></fn><fn id="tbfnote2"><label>a</label><p>One patient treated at both dose levels.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap> summarises the dose escalation schedule, number of courses administered and number of patients with DLT at each dose level. Where the investigators felt that specific toxicities were not of sufficient clinical concern, dose escalation continued without the dose level being expanded. One patient experienced DLT at the highest dose level and dropped one dose level for the second course, and is therefore represented twice. The dose was escalated from 6 to 4900&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> over 19 dose levels. The first escalation (1.7-fold) followed the planned Fibonacci series, but the values of the area under the plasma concentration&#x02013;time curve (AUC) at the first dose level were much lower (1&#x0002f;30th) than those predicted from murine data. Therefore, the dose was doubled for subsequent escalations. A rise in plasma nitrate (one of the PD end points measured) in a patient at 160&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> suggested the possibility of having reached a PD threshold, and further escalations (1.2&#x02013;1.5-fold) were guided by toxicity and PK from both the UK and NZ trials. Dose escalation was not restricted by nonhaematological toxicities that technically met the protocol definition for DLT but were not considered of sufficient clinical significance (such as acute onset of tremor that resolved within one hour).</p></sec><sec><title>General toxicity</title><p>Toxicities of DMXAA were markedly different from those of many cytotoxic drugs, and many patients commented that it was easier to tolerate than chemotherapy. There was no significant drug-related neutropenia, thrombocytopenia or coagulopathy, and while anaemia and lymphocytopenia were common, they were judged unrelated to DMXAA in the majority of cases. <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Nonhaematological toxicity (drug-related<sup>a</sup>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="char" char="."/><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="14" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Maximum grade of toxicity per patient</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Nausea and&#x0002f;or vomiting</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Venous pain</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Malaise</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Hyper- or hypotension</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Flushing&#x0002f;sweating</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Acute neuro symptoms</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Dyspnoea</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>Dose (mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>No. of patients</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x02013;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3&#x02013;4</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x02013;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3&#x02013;4</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x02013;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3&#x02013;4</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x02013;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3&#x02013;4</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x02013;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3&#x02013;4</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x02013;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3&#x02013;4</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1&#x02013;2</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3&#x02013;4</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">10.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">20.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">40.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">81.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">160</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">240</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">360</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">500</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">650</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">850</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1100</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1375</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1650</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2000</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2600</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">3100</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">3700</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4900</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote3"><label>a</label><p>Almost certainly, probably or possibly related to DMXAA. Neuro&#x0003d;neurological.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap> summarises selected drug-related non-haematological toxicities, which established the MTD at 3700&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>. At lower dose levels, this drug was generally well tolerated, with a minority of patients experiencing mild drug-related toxicity. Acute symptoms included venous discomfort with the infusion (alleviated by application of a warm pad), increased tumour pain several hours after the drug infusion and one patient briefly developed small urticarial lesions. Delayed toxicities included &#x02018;flu-like&#x02019; symptoms (malaise, myalgia, fatigue, nausea, sweating) on days 2&#x02013;4 of each course, but no mucositis or alopecia occurred. Additional acute toxicities were more prevalent with increasing dose above 1100&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, with onset of symptoms during or shortly after the 20-min drug infusion. They were usually mild and invariably transient, generally resolving between a few minutes and 4&#x02009;h later, and included nausea and&#x0002f;or vomiting (for only a few minutes and not reliably prevented by ondansetron), sympathetic disturbance (sweating, warm flush, hypotension, hypertension, bradycardia or tachycardia), altered taste and neurological disturbance (visual disturbance, tremor, feeling light-headed and restless). Patients at the higher dose levels also commonly experienced a brief urge to urinate and&#x0002f;or defecate. One patient (treated at 1650&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) had pre-existing impairment of bladder control and was incontinent of urine immediately following DMXAA administration. Creatinine clearance (measured by two sequential 24-h urine collections in 12 patients) did not change following DMXAA administration at doses ranging from 1375 to 4900&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (paired <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003d;0.63).</p></sec><sec><title>Neurological toxicity</title><p>At 4900&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, acute neurological toxicity was considered dose limiting in all three patients, even though symptoms resolved completely within 2&#x02009;h. These included slurred speech (two patients), confusion and expressive dysphasia (one patient), moderate anxiety (one patient), severe visual disturbance (one patient), tremor (two patients) and urinary incontinence (one patient). Similar neurological toxicity was seen in one patient treated at 1650&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> on her second course only, attributed to an interaction between DMXAA and isocarboxazid, a monoamine oxidase inhibitor. The features were consistent with the &#x02018;serotonin syndrome&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib54">Sporer, 1995</xref>) and included difficulty concentrating, drowsiness, generalised tremor, occasional myoclonic jerks, hyper-reflexia, bradycardia and hypertension, all resolving within 6&#x02009;h.</p><p>Visual disturbance was first reported at 1375&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> and symptoms became more prevalent and intense with increasing dose. Symptoms at lower dose levels included altered colour vision, blurring (without impairment of visual acuity) and mild photophobia. Colour vision testing revealed acute deterioration in colour discrimination, resolving within 4&#x02009;h. Dose-limiting transient visual disturbance at 4900&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> included glittering of objects, harsh contrasts, jerky motion and strobe effects. Pattern and flash electroretinogram (ERG) showed an acute increase in latency and reduction in amplitude of certain retinal responses following DMXAA infusion with subsequent return to baseline over several hours, and a dose&#x02013;response relationship was observed. A patient who received six courses at 3700&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> showed subclinical deterioration of pre-infusion ERGs between courses 2 and 6.</p></sec><sec><title>Cardiorespiratory toxicity</title><p>Transient prolongation of the corrected cardiac QT interval was seen in all 13 patients evaluated at doses of 2000&#x02013;4900&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (median prolongation 52&#x02009;ms, range 38&#x02013;100&#x02009;ms). In six of nine patients with normal baseline QT<sub>c</sub> values, QT<sub>c</sub> became abnormally prolonged (&#x0003e;450&#x02009;ms in males, &#x0003e;470&#x02009;ms in females) after treatment with doses of DMXAA of &#x02a7e;3100&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib15">Committee for Proprietary Medicinal Products, 1997</xref>). The maximal QT<sub>c</sub> prolongation occurred during or within 15&#x02009;min of completion of the drug infusion with a return to baseline generally over 4&#x02013;6&#x02009;h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Change in corrected QT interval after DMXAA administration at 3700&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="88-6600992f2"/></fig>). QT<sub>c</sub> was prolonged beyond 500&#x02009;ms in four patients with baseline values of 430, 460, 461 and 501&#x02009;ms and in the first three patients, this lasted for less than 1&#x02009;h. No clear dose&#x02013;response relationship was observed and no ventricular tachyarrhythmia was seen.</p><p>Dyspnoea possibly related to DMXAA was documented in three patients treated at doses &#x02a7d;1100&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, but each patient had another more likely explanation. At higher doses, acute dyspnoea at rest occurred in four patients immediately following DMXAA infusion. In three of these patients (treated at 2600&#x02013;3700&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>), the dyspnoea after DMXAA was minimal, brief (5&#x02013;25&#x02009;min) and clinically insignificant. The fourth patient, with moderately severe chronic obstructive respiratory disease, became very breathless and anxious 15&#x02009;min after her first course at 4900&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>. Clinically, she had basal pulmonary inspiratory crackles but no bronchospasm. Oxygen saturation was normal on breathing air and the symptoms resolved in about 75&#x02009;min. On her second course, DMXAA was reduced to 3700&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (she is thus represented at two doses in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) and she again developed dyspnoea, lasting for about an hour. She had basal inspiratory crackles and a third heart sound (consistent with left ventricular failure) and these signs resolved within 2&#x02009;h.</p></sec><sec><title>Therapeutic response</title><p>A total of 60 patients were evaluable for response. One partial response was seen in a patient with metastatic squamous carcinoma of cervix treated at 1100&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> and previously treated with bleomycin, etoposide and cisplatin chemotherapy, then carboplatin. The response was unconfirmed because two small neck nodes increased in size transiently after the third course then subsequently regressed again and overall tumour response was maintained for eight courses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Tumour response in a patient with metastatic squamous carcinoma of cervix treated with DMXAA 1100&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>. Tumour size was calculated as the sum of the products of bidimensional measurements of three clinically measurable metastatic neck nodes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="88-6600992f3"/></fig>). No change was the best response in 22 patients (35&#x00025;) at dose levels from 6 to 3700&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> and the duration exceeded 12 weeks in five patients (8&#x00025;).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This phase I trial of DMXAA has demonstrated clinical antitumour activity and reduction in tumour blood flow at well-tolerated doses (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib23">Galbraith <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>). The MTD was established as 3700&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, and higher doses produced unusual, transient toxicities including confusion, slurred speech, tremor, restlessness and visual disturbance, as well as transient autonomic changes such as sweating, tremor, changes in blood pressure and heart rate. The results of the UK trial of DMXAA are published separately (Rustin <italic>et al</italic>, submitted to <italic>Br J Cancer</italic>), but there was a high degree of concordance with our results including toxicities, PK, PD and clinical activity (an unconfirmed partial response was also seen).</p><p>Clinical trials of FAA, which is structurally related to DMXAA, showed differences between the two drugs. While the clinical toxicities of DMXAA and FAA showed some similarities (warmth, flushing, sweating, fatigue, myalgia, nausea, vomiting and visual disturbance), the DLTs of FAA were remarkably different and included hypotension, diarrhoea, flushing, asthenia and fatigue (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib30">Kerr <italic>et al</italic>, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib59">Weiss <italic>et al</italic>, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib28">Kaye <italic>et al</italic>, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">Havlin <italic>et al</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib40">Olver <italic>et al</italic>, 1992</xref>). Prolongation of bleeding time was described (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib49">Rubin <italic>et al</italic>, 1987</xref>) and one patient presented with haemorrhage due to immune thrombocytopenia after five doses of FAA (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib17">Davis <italic>et al</italic>, 1988</xref>). Bleeding time was not measured in this DMXAA trial, but no significant disturbance of INR and APTT was seen, nor was any significant thrombocytopenia observed.</p><p>A number of other agents, including serotonin, some tubulin-binding agents and arsenic trioxide, selectively inhibit tumour blood flow (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib56">St&#x000fc;cker <italic>et al</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib12">Ching <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib35">Lew <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>). Combretastatin A-4 phosphate (CA4P), a tubulin-binding agent, has antivascular activity at doses well below the MTD in both preclinical and early clinical studies (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib51">Rustin <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>), comparable to those reported with DMXAA (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib33">Lash <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib23">Galbraith <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>). However, the blood flow-modifying effect of CA4P is not entirely tumour-selective (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib24">Griggs <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>), and it appears to be reversible except at high doses (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib2">Anderson <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib37">Murata <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). Some CA4P toxicities resembled those of DMXAA (including flushing, nausea, vomiting, tumour pain and QT<sub>c</sub> prolongation), but others (cardiac ischaemia and cerebellar ataxia) were notably different (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib22">Galbraith <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib19">Dowlati <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>).</p><p>Some toxicities observed with DMXAA resemble the &#x02018;serotonin syndrome&#x02019;, attributed to high levels of serotonin in the central nervous system (CNS). This syndrome most commonly occurs when two drugs are taken, which can each increase CNS serotonin and includes alterations in cognition, behaviour, autonomic nervous system function and neuromuscular activity (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib54">Sporer, 1995</xref>). Supportive evidence comes from two other aspects of this trial: firstly, a patient took a monoamine oxidase inhibitor prior to treatment with DMXAA at 1650&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> and developed clinical features of the serotonin syndrome; and secondly an acute increase in plasma prolactin levels seen in many patients treated with DMXAA at &#x02a7e;2000&#x02009;mg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (unpublished results). This occurs following production of serotonin in the CNS (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib57">Van de Kar <italic>et al</italic>, 1996</xref>). If subsequent studies provide further evidence that DMXAA increases CNS serotonin release, it would be prudent to avoid administering DMXAA to patients who are receiving other drugs that increase CNS serotonin levels (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib6">Brown <italic>et al</italic>, 1996</xref>). The mechanism underlying the acute release of CNS serotoninis not known, but serotonin release in plasma has been observed in this study (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib31">Kestell <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>), and is a feature of the antivascular activity of this drug in preclinical models (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib4">Baguley <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>).</p><p>The visual toxicities of DMXAA are not a feature of the serotonin syndrome, but the blurring, colour disturbance and photophobia have similarities to those reported with sildenafil (Viagra&#x000ae;, Pfizer, New York, NY, USA) (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib36">Marmor and Kessler, 1999</xref>). The latter's visual toxicities are thought to be due to inhibition of phosphodiesterase type 6 (PDE6), which exists exclusively in the retina and is responsible for modulating the transduction cascade of the photoreceptor response to light. Recent data have shown that DMXAA inhibited PDE6 <italic>in vitro</italic> at pharmacologically relevant concentrations (e.g. 50&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sc>M</sc>) (personal communication, L Kelland, Antisoma plc). It is reassuring in this regard that no long-term retinal sequela of sildenafil administration is known, including data from retinal histologic studies in dogs dosed with 65 times the maximum recommended human dose daily for 12 months (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib58">Wallis <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib36">Marmor and Kessler, 1999</xref>).</p><p>The significance of the observed QT<sub>c</sub> prolongation in these preliminary data is uncertain given its brevity, its possible relation to autonomic changes caused by the infusion and the population of patients potentially being treated with this agent. Moreover, the use of <italic>ad hoc</italic> heart rate correction formulae (such as Bazett's) may bias the result (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib3">Aytemir <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>). Therefore the QT<sub>c</sub> results in this trial must be regarded as indicative only. However, given the concern that QT interval prolongation may predispose to ventricular tachycardia (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib15">Committee for Proprietary Medicinal Products, 1997</xref>), it will be important to determine the dose&#x02013;response relationship of QT<sub>c</sub> prolongation before deciding on the dose of DMXAA for phase II and combination studies.</p><p>In conclusion, DMXAA is well tolerated over a wide dose range and has clinical and biological features distinct from those of other antivascular drugs in clinical development. Further clinical trials with this agent are clearly warranted, particularly in combination with other treatment modalities where synergistic interactions are observed in animal tumour models.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the patients who participated in this study and the staff at Auckland Hospital who assisted in the care and monitoring of these patients. This trial was supported in part by the Auckland Cancer Society, Auckland Healthcare Services Limited, Cancer Research UK and a grant from Parke-Davis Pharmaceuticals, Ann Arbor, MI, USA. This work has been presented in part at the annual meetings of the American Society of Clinical Oncology in 1997 and 2000.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Algire</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Legallais</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vascular reactions of normal and malignant tissues <italic>in vivo</italic>. II. The vascular reaction of normal and neoplastic tissues of mice to a bacterial polysaccharide from <italic>Serratia marcescens</italic> (<italic>Bacillus prodigiosus</italic>) culture filtrates</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>1947</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Natl Cancer Inst||8|53||bib1|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jap</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurement of tumour and normal tissue (NT) perfusion by positron emission tomography (PET) in the evaluation of antivascular therapy: results in the phase I study of combretastatin A4 phosphate (CA4P)</article-title><source>Proc Annu Meet Am Soc Clin Oncol</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>179</fpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Proc Annu Meet Am Soc Clin Oncol||19|179||bib2|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aytemir</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maarouf</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><name><surname>Waktare</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of formulae for heart rate correction of QT interval in exercise electrocardiograms</article-title><source>Pacing Clin Electrophysiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1397</fpage><lpage>1401</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Pacing Clin Electrophysiol||22|1397||bib3|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10527023</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kestell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased plasma serotonin following treatment with flavone-8-acetic acid, 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid, vinblastine, and colchicine&#x02013;relation to vascular effects</article-title><source>Oncol Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Oncol Res||9|55||bib4|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9167186</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bibby</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavone acetic acid&#x02013;an interesting novel therapeutic agent or just another disappointment</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1991</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||63|3||bib5|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1989662</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Skop</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mareth</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathophysiology and management of the serotonin syndrome</article-title><source>Ann Pharmacother</source><year>1996</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Ann Pharmacother||30|527||bib6|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8740336</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mountjoy</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thalidomide increases both intra-tumoural tumour necrosis factor-alpha production and anti-tumour activity in response to 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1999</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>716</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||80|716||bib7|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10360649</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carswell</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Old</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An endotoxin-induced serum factor that causes necrosis of tumors</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1975</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3666</fpage><lpage>3670</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Proc Natl Acad Sci USA||25|3666||bib8|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaplin</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumour vasculature as a target for cancer therapy</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1999</year><volume>80</volume><supplement>Suppl 1</supplement><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||80|57||bib9|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10466764</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of natural killer cell activity by the antitumour compound flavone acetic acid (NSC 347 512)</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer Clin Oncol</source><year>1987</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1047</fpage><lpage>1050</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Eur J Cancer Clin Oncol||23|1047||bib10|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3665989</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Crosier</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of tumor necrosis factor-alpha messenger RNA in human and murine cells by the flavone acetic acid analogue 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid (NSC 640488)</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>870</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||54|870||bib11|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8313372</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of tumour blood flow</article-title><source>Methods in Molecular Medicine, Vol. 25, Drug Targeting</source><year>1999</year><publisher-name>Totowa, NJ: Humana Press Inc.</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>26</lpage>Francis, GE, Delgado, C (eds), Chapter 9, pp</citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cliffe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combining bioreductive drugs (SR 4233 or SN 23862) with the vasoactive agents flavone acetic acid or 5,6-dimethylxanthenone acetic acid</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>1994</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys||29|373||bib13|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8195036</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coley-Nauts</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogatko</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of the influence of bacterial infection and bacterial products (Coley's toxins) on malignant tumours in man</article-title><source>Acta Med Scand</source><year>1953</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Acta Med Scand||145|5||bib14|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Committee for Proprietary Medicinal Products</collab></person-group><article-title>Points to consider: the assessment of the potential for QT interval prolongation by non-cardiovascular medicinal products</article-title><year>1997</year>CPMP&#x0002f;986&#x0002f;96:1-6</citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Council on Pharmacy and Chemistry</collab></person-group><article-title>Erysipelas and prodigiosus toxins (Coley)</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>1934</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>1067</fpage><lpage>1069</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'JAMA||103|1067||bib16|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Newlands</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Allain</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immune thrombocytopenia caused by flavone-8-acetic acid</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1988</year><volume>1</volume><supplement>8582</supplement><fpage>412</fpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Lancet||1|412||bib17|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeVore</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellerqvist</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wamil</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thurman</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Minton</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundell</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>York</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phase I study of the antineovascularization drug CM101</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Clin Cancer Res||3|365||bib18|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9815693</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dowlati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Petros</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stratford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jesberger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafie</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Overmoyer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Makkar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Stambler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Waas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewin</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>McCrae</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Remick</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A phase I pharmacokinetic and translational study of the novel vascular targeting agent combretastatin a-4 phosphate on a single-dose intravenous schedule in patients with advanced cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>3408</fpage><lpage>3416</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||62|3408||bib19|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12067983</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eggermont</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>ten Hagen</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolated limb perfusion for extremity soft-tissue sarcomas, in-transit metastases, and other unresectable tumors: credits, debits, and future perspectives</article-title><source>Curr Oncol Rep</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Curr Oncol Rep||3|359||bib20|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11389822</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finlay</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fray</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of flavone acetic acid on Lewis lung carcinoma: evidence for an indirect effect</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>1988</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Natl Cancer Inst||80|241||bib21|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3351960</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galbraith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lodge</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tozer</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Prise</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sena</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Padhani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rustin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combretastatin A4 phosphate (CA4P) reduces tumor blood flow in animals and man, demonstrated by MRI</article-title><source>Proc Annu Meet Am Soc Clin Oncol</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>278a</fpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Proc Annu Meet Am Soc Clin Oncol||20|278a||bib22|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galbraith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rustin</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lodge</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stirling</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jameson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hough</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gumbrell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Padhani</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid on human tumor microcirculation assessed by dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2002</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>3826</fpage><lpage>3840</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Oncol||20|3826||bib23|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228202</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griggs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hesketh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brindle</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combretastatin-A4 disrupts neovascular development in non-neoplastic tissue</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2001</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>832</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||84|832||bib24|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11259100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Havlin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Boldt</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Koeller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Hoff</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phase I clinical and pharmacokinetic trial of flavone acetic acid</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>1991</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Natl Cancer Inst||83|124||bib25|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1703237</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horsman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving conventional cancer therapy by targeting tumour vasculature</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1999</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>90</fpage>(P247)<!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||80|90||bib26|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanwar</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanwar</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Krissansen</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vascular attack by 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid combined with B7.1 (CD80)-mediated immunotherapy overcomes immune resistance and leads to the eradication of large tumors and multiple tumor foci</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1948</fpage><lpage>1956</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||61|1948||bib27|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11280751</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Clavel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodion</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Monfardini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>ten Bokkel Huinink</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagener</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gundersen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Renard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanglabbeke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phase-II trials with flavone acetic acid (NSC-347512, LM975) in patients with advanced carcinoma of the breast, colon, head and neck and melanoma</article-title><source>Invest New Drugs</source><year>1990</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>S95</fpage><lpage>S99</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Invest New Drugs||8|S95||bib28|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2380021</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavone acetic acid&#x02013;preclinical and clinical activity</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer Clin Oncol</source><year>1989</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1271</fpage><lpage>1272</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Eur J Cancer Clin Oncol||25|1271||bib29|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2680512</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassidy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Setanoians</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Soukop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Clavel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phase I and pharmacokinetic study of flavone acetic acid</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1987</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>6776</fpage><lpage>6781</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||47|6776||bib30|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3677106</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kestell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jameson</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Stratford</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Folkes</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurement of plasma 5-hydroxyindoleacetic acid as a possible clinical surrogate marker for the action of antivascular agents</article-title><source>Clin Chim Acta</source><year>2001</year><volume>314</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Clin Chim Acta||314|159||bib31|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11718691</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kligfield</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lax</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Okin</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>QT interval&#x02013;heart rate relation during exercise in normal men and women: definition by linear regression analysis</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1547</fpage><lpage>1555</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Am Coll Cardiol||28|1547||bib32|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8917270</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwi</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancement of the anti-tumour effects of the antivascular agent 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid (DMXAA) by combination with 5-hydroxytryptamine and bioreductive drugs</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1998</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>445</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||78|439||bib33|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9716024</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lejeune</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruegg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lienard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical applications of TNF-alpha in cancer</article-title><source>Curr Opin Immunol</source><year>1998</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Curr Opin Immunol||10|573||bib34|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9794839</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lew</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arsenic trioxide causes selective necrosis in solid murine tumors by vascular shutdown</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>6033</fpage><lpage>6037</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||59|6033||bib35|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10626785</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marmor</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sildenafil (Viagra) and ophthalmology</article-title><source>Surv Ophthalmol</source><year>1999</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Surv Ophthalmol||44|153||bib36|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10541153</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Horsman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative effects of combretastatin A-4 disodium phosphate and 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid on blood perfusion in a murine tumour and normal tissues</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Int J Radiat Biol||77|195||bib37|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11236926</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Dwyer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoemaker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaharko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grieshaber</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Plowman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Valeriote</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cradock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoth</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyland-Jones</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavone acetic acid (LM 975, NSC 347512), a novel antitumor agent</article-title><source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source><year>1987</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Chemother Pharmacol||19|6||bib38|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3545524</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Old</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumor necrosis factor (TNF)</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1985</year><volume>230</volume><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>632</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Science||230|630||bib39|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2413547</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olver</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A phase I and pharmacokinetic study of 12-h infusion of flavone acetic acid</article-title><source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source><year>1992</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Chemother Pharmacol||29|354||bib40|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1551173</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackensen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehr</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Seiz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Galanos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mertelsmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phase II trial of intravenous endotoxin in patients with colorectal and non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>1996</year><volume>32A</volume><fpage>1712</fpage><lpage>1718</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Eur J Cancer||32A|1712||bib41|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8983279</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pedley</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Boden</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Boden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Boxer</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Keep</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Begent</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ablation of colorectal xenografts with combined radioimmunotherapy and tumor blood flow-modifying agents</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>3293</fpage><lpage>3300</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||56|3293||bib42|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8764124</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pedley</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Boxer</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stribbling</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Begent</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancement of antibody-directed enzyme prodrug therapy in colorectal xenografts by an antivascular agent</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>3998</fpage><lpage>4003</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||59|3998||bib43|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10463598</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Philpott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of tumour necrosis factor-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> by single and repeated doses of the antitumour agent 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid</article-title><source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source><year>1995</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Chemother Pharmacol||36|143||bib44|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7767951</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Philpott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Crosier</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of tumour necrosis factor-alpha by cultured human peripheral blood leucocytes in response to the anti-tumour agent 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid (NSC 640488)</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1997</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>1586</fpage><lpage>1591</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||76|1586||bib45|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9413946</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pruijn</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>van Daalen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Holford</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of enhancement of the antitumour activity of melphalan by the tumour-blood-flow inhibitor 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid</article-title><source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source><year>1997</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>546</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Chemother Pharmacol||39|541||bib46|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9118467</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rewcastle</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Atwell</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Denny</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential antitumor agents. 61. Structure&#x02013;activity relationships for <italic>in vivo</italic> colon 38 activity among disubstituted 9-oxo-9H-xanthene-4-acetic acids</article-title><source>J Med Chem</source><year>1991</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Med Chem||34|217||bib47|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1992120</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rewcastle</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kestell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Denny</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Light-induced breakdown of flavone acetic acid and xanthenone analogues in solution</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>1990</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Natl Cancer Inst||82|528||bib48|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2313725</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ames</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schutt</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowie</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovach</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavone-8-acetic acid inhibits ristocetin-induced platelet agglutination and prolongs bleeding time</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1987</year><volume>2</volume><supplement>8567</supplement><fpage>1081</fpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Lancet||2|1081||bib49|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruegg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bamat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaubert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lejeune</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for the involvement of endothelial cell integrin alphaVbeta3 in the disruption of the tumor vasculature induced by TNF and IFN-gamma</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Nat Med||4|408||bib50|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9546785</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rustin</surname><given-names>GJS</given-names></name><name><surname>Galbraith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tozer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Baddeley</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Prise</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combretastatin A4 phosphate (CA4P) selectively targets vasculature in animal and human tumors</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>14</fpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Clin Cancer Res||5|14||bib51|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rustin</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Galbraith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stratford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Loadman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellenger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gumbrell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Folkes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Halbert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>5,6-Dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid (DMXAA), a novel antivascular agent: phase I clinical and pharmacokinetic study</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2003</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>1160</fpage><lpage>1167</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||88|1160||bib65|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12698178</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siim</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shalal-Zwain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruijin</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>McKeage</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Marked potentiation of the antitumour activity of chemotherapeutic drugs by the antivascular agent 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid (DMXAA)</article-title><source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source><year>2003</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Chemother Pharmacol||51|43||bib64|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12497205</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siim</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruijn</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shalal-Zwain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McKeage</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Marked potentiation of the antitumour activity of chemotherapeutic drugs by the antivascular agent 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid (DMXAA)</article-title><source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source><year>2002</year></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Calveley</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavone acetic acid (NSC 347512) induces haemorrhagic necrosis of mouse colon 26 and 38 tumours</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer Clin Oncol</source><year>1987</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1209</fpage><lpage>1211</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Eur J Cancer Clin Oncol||23|1209||bib53|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3653213</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sporer</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The serotonin syndrome. Implicated drugs, pathophysiology and management</article-title><source>Drug Saf</source><year>1995</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Drug Saf||13|94||bib54|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7576268</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spriggs</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer chemotherapy; experiences with TNF administration in humans</article-title><source>Tumor Necrosis Factors: The Molecules and Their Emerging Role in Medicine</source><year>1992</year><publisher-name>New York: Raven Press</publisher-name><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>406</lpage>Beutler B (ed) pp</citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>St&#x000fc;cker</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicaut</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Teisseire</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specific response to 5-HT2 agonists by arterioles linked to Meth A tumors in mice</article-title><source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>262</volume><fpage>H704</fpage><lpage>H709</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Am J Physiol||262|H704||bib56|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1558179</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van de Kar</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rittenhouse</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serotonergic regulation of renin and prolactin secretion</article-title><source>Behav Brain Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Behav Brain Res||73|203||bib57|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8788503</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Leishman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pullman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Graepel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heywood</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of sildenafil on retinal histopathology and electroretinogram (ERG) in dogs</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>S68</fpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Ophthalmic Res||30|S68||bib58|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelosi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulkes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Curt</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phase I and clinical pharmacology study of intravenous flavone acetic acid (NSC 347512)</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1988</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>5878</fpage><lpage>5882</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||48|5878||bib59|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3167843</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combination of the antivascular agent DMXAA with radiation and chemotherapy</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>2000</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>706</fpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys||46|706||bib60|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Siim</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancement of tumor radiation response by the antivascular agent 5,6-dimethylxanthenone-4-acetic acid</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>1998</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>905</fpage><lpage>908</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys||42|905||bib61|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9845119</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zwi</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Holdaway</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of immune effector cells in flavone acetic acid-induced injury to tumor cells in EMT6 spheroids</article-title><source>Oncol Res</source><year>1992</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Oncol Res||4|333||bib62|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1486217</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zwi</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blood flow failure as a major determinant in the antitumor action of flavone acetic acid (NSC 347512)</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>1989</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>1005</fpage><lpage>1013</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Natl Cancer Inst||81|1005||bib63|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2733044</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zwi</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Necrosis in non-tumour tissues caused by flavone acetic acid and 5,6-dimethylxanthenone acetic acid</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1990</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>932</fpage><lpage>934</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||62|932||bib66|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2257222</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


