<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7947108</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2033523</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Reduction of the radiation dose for intracranial germinoma: a prospective study.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shibamoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Oncology, Faculty of Medicine, Kyoto University, Japan.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>1994</year></pub-date><volume>70</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>984</fpage><lpage>989</lpage><abstract><p>Intracranial germinoma has usually been treated with radiation doses of 50 Gy or more, but it is unclear whether such doses are actually necessary to cure this radiosensitive tumour. At our institution, the standard radiation dose for intracranial germinoma was 60 Gy in the 1960s, but the dose has prospectively been reduced stepwise to 40-45 Gy. In this paper, the treatment outcome was assessed in 84 patients (47 with histologically confirmed disease and 37 diagnosed clinically in the post-computerised tomography era) enrolled in both prospective and retrospective series. The 5 and 10 years survival rates for all 84 patients were 88% and 83% respectively, and the corresponding relapse-free survival rates were 88% and 85%. The 10-year relapse-free survival rate was 88% for 31 patients receiving 19-47 Gy (median 42 Gy) to the primary tumour, 92% for 28 patients receiving 48-52 Gy (median 50 Gy), and 83% for 25 patients receiving 54-62 Gy (median 60 Gy), and there was no significant difference among the three groups. In-field local recurrence only developed in one patient who received 40 Gy over a protracted period and one patient who received 60 Gy. A tumour size &#x0003c; 3 cm and treatment in the post-computerised tomography era were associated with a better prognosis according to univariate analysis, while age, sex, tumour site, treatment volume, the radiation dose to both the primary and the spinal cord and the extent of surgical resection did not influence the prognosis. In contrast, none of these factors had a significant influence in multivariate analysis. In conclusion, intracranial germinomas &#x0003c; or = 4 cm in size can usually be cured with 40-45 Gy of radiation, thus avoiding the major adverse effects of brain irradiation.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00057-0206.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="984" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00057-0207.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="985" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00057-0208.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="986" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00057-0209.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="987" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00057-0210.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="988" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00057-0211.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="989" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

