<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7917935</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2033420</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Serum neuron-specific enolase (S-NSE) in progressive small-cell lung cancer (SCLC).</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Osterlind</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Oncology ONK 5074, Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen, Denmark.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>1994</year></pub-date><volume>70</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>761</lpage><abstract><p>Clinical decision making is based on results from qualitative and quantitative information. To provide quantitative data, various laboratory variables are widely used in the clinical evaluation of patients with small-cell lung cancer (SCLC). The tumour marker serum neuron-specific enolase (S-NSE) and the routine laboratory parameter serum lactate dehydrogenase (S-LDH) have been investigated, mostly separately. Few studies have compared their importance in SCLC, especially in progressive disease (PD). The present investigation was undertaken to evaluate S-NSE for diagnostic efficacy in PD and compare it with S-LDH. In 27 patients in a treatment trial of SCLC, regular follow-up laboratory values were prospectively obtained. Chemotherapy was given according to trial protocols, and all clinical evaluation followed the WHO recommendations. At re-evaluation all but three values had normalised (two S-NSE, one S-LDH). S-NSE at progression was increased in 93% of the patients and S-LDH in 59%. The efficacy of S-NSE to discriminate between response and PD was superior to S-LDH (0.92 vs 0.70). There was no additive effect of the two parameters in prediction of PD, and the discriminating power was higher for S-NSE than for S-LDH (P &#x0003c; 0.0008). The disease status-related marker increments in relation to upper reference limits, i.e. the signal-noise relation, were higher for S-NSE than for S-LD. Both of the markers carry information on PD. S-NSE is, however, clearly superior to S-LDH in reflecting disease status during therapy. This prompts us to conclude that S-NSE should replace S-LDH as prognostic factor and disease activity monitor in SCLC.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0189.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="759" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0190.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="760" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0191.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="761" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

