<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ViewNLM-v2.3.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Yonsei Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">YMJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Yonsei Medical Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0513-5796</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1976-2437</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Yonsei University College of Medicine</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15744806</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2823058</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3349/ymj.2005.46.1.61</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Diagnostic Value of Endoprobe for Small Esophageal Leiomyomas Derived from the Muscularis Mucosae</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Se-Joon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>Yong-Han</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Dong-Ki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Kwan-Sik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Sang-In</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1">Department of Internal Medicine, Institute of Gastroenterology, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff><author-notes><corresp>
Reprint address: requests to Dr. Kwan-Sik Lee, Department of Internal Medicine, Institute of Gastroenterology, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Yongdong Severance Hospital, 146-92 Dogok-dong, Gangnam-gu, Seoul 135-720, Korea. Tel: 82-2-3497-3314, Fax: 82-2-3463-3882, <email>leeks519@yumc.yonsei.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>10</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 The Yonsei University College of Medicine</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Esophageal leiomyoma derived from the muscularis mucosae (MM) is a rare condition, and the optimal modality for diagnosis and treatment is controversial. Endoscopic ultrasonography can provide an accurate image of esophageal layer structure, providing information on lesion suitability for potential endoscopic therapy. We attempted to investigate the diagnostic value of a transendoscopic balloon-tipped miniature ultrasonic endoprobe for small esophageal leiomyomas derived from MM. We resected 7 small esophageal leiomyomas derived from MM by endoscopic mucosal resection (EMR), all of which were diagnosed by a balloon-tipped endoprobe. The endosonographic and pathologic features of 7 cases of small esophageal leiomyomas derived from MM were compared. The balloon-tipped endoprobe clearly showed all 7 small esophageal leiomyomas derived from MM, even those under 5 mm in size (smallest lesion, 3.0 mm). The endosonographic characteristics of small esophageal leiomyomas derived from MM were a hypoechoic mass with smooth, regular, and a well-defined outer margin and homogenous inner echogram arising from the second hypoechoic layer. Complete resections were possible in all 7 cases by EMR without any complications. Tumor size was 3.0 - 13.5 mm (mean 7.8 mm) in maximum diameter. In all cases, endosonographic findings by endoprobe were exactly concordant with pathologic finding in determining the tumors depth in the esophageal wall, tissue origin and characteristics, growth pattern, and size. We detail the balloon-tipped endoprobe is a simple, convenient, and very useful in making accurate diagnosis of small esophageal leiomyomas derived from the MM and the appropriate applications of EMR.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Endoscopic ultrasonography</kwd><kwd>leiomyoma</kwd><kwd>esophagus</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The leiomyoma is the most common type of submucosal tumor of the esophagus.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> The diagnosis of esophageal leiomyoma is increasing now due to increased physician concern and the greater availability of endoscopic ultrasonography (EUS). Esophageal leiomyomas may arise from either the muscularis mucosae (MM) or muscularis propria (PM) layer of the esophagus, but the differentiation of origin may be difficult in small tumors by conventional EUS. As the high frequency ultrasonic endoprobe has developed, the detection of origin of small tumor seems to be easier.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref> Small esophageal leiomyomas derived from the MM seem to be less rare but debate persists about the best modality for diagnosis and treatment. Removal of esophageal leiomyomas from the MM may seem to be excessive in light of their benign nature, but patients can be relieved from anxiety, and the presence of a potential precancerous lesion can be abolished. When the tumor is confirmed to have arisen from the MM, it can be removed far more safely by endoscopy. It is often difficult to acquire accurate images of small-sized esophageal submucosal tumors due to luminal compression artifact and crude images by low frequency ultrasound of conventional EUS. Endoprobe provides accurate imaging of the layer structure of the esophagus and potential suitability for endoscopic therapy or not as it produces high frequency ultrasonic beams, and is easier to access the lesion than conventional EUS. Endoprobe can also help confirm the separation of layers after injection of saline into the submucosa.</p><p>Over two years, we have resected seven esophageal leiomyomas derived from the MM using the technique of endoscopic mucosal resection (EMR). In this study, we attempted to assess the efficacy of an endoprobe for small esophageal leiomyomas originating from the MM that were often difficult to assess with conventional EUS.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p>Over the past two years, EMR was performed on seven patients with esophageal leiomyomas derived from MM confirmed with endoprobe. We defined the indications for EMR as a hypoechoic tumor originating from the second hypoechoic layer of the esophagus with a size less than 15 mm in diameter.</p><p>The patients consisted of five males and two females, age ranged from 24 - 58 years (mean, 46). A routine endoscopy was performed to reveal the mucosal aspect of the tumor and to check for additional lesions in the upper gastrointestinal tract. In all patients, there were no mucosal abnormalities on the tumor surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p>After routine endoscopy, endoprobe technique was performed using an UM-2R (12 MHz) or UM-3R (20 MHz) ultrasonic probe with balloontipped catheter (MH-246R) through the forceps channel. The display unit was EU-M30 (Olympus Optical Co. Ltd., Tokyo, Japan).</p><p>By scanning the normal esophagus with a 20 MHz endoprobe, a seven layer image can be obtained: the first echogenic layer corresponding to the mucosa, the second an echolucent MM layer, the third an echogenic submucosa, the fourth an hypoechoic inner circular PM layer, the fifth a thin, echogenic intermuscular septum, the sixth a hypoechoic outer longitudinal PM layer, and the seventh a broad hyperechoic adventitia and periesophageal fat layer because there is no covering serosa in the esophagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><p>The principles of the EMR and its potential risks were explained to the patients and family, and informed consent was formally obtained. Standard routine EMR or EMR-using transparent cap (EMR-C) was performed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> summarizes the clinical and histologic features found in seven cases. All the patients had no symptoms related to the leiomyoma, and the lesions were found during checkup incidentally. The locations of the tumors in the esophagus were four in the upper third of the esophagus and three in the middle third.</p><p>Endoscopy revealed hemispherical bulging lesions with intact overlying mucosa measuring 4 to 15 mm in diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Balloon-tipped endoprobe clearly showed all 7 small esophageal leiomyomas derived from MM, even for tumors less than 5 mm in size (smallest lesion, 3.0 mm). All tumors were depicted by endoprobe as homogenous inner hypoechoic echograms, well-demarcated masses with smooth and regular outer margin derived from the second hypoechoic layer of the esophagus, and with an intact muscularis propria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><p>Complete resection was possible in all 7 cases by EMR or EMR-C without any severe complications. The size of the completely removed tumors ranged from 3.0 to 13.5 mm (mean 7.8 mm) in maximum diameter.</p><p>The resected tumors were of firm consistency, smoothly rounded, grayish-white or yellowish on section, without any degenerative changes. They were confirmed as the leiomyomas derived MM layer of the esophagus, as shown by contiguous lamina muscularis mucosae at their peripheral edges and the usual bundles of smooth muscle fibers, microscopically. There were very few mitotic figures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><p>After a follow-up of 3 months with repeated endoscopy, no recurrence was seen in all cases and the resected mucosal lesions were completely healed with only linear scarring contracted change remaining.</p><p>In all cases, endosonographic findings by endoprobe were exactly concordant with pathologic findings in determining the tumor's depth in the esophageal wall, tissues origin and characteristics, growth pattern, and size of esophageal leiomyoma derived from MM.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Leiomyoma is the most common type of esophageal benign tumor and may occur in the MM or PM layer of the esophagus.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref> Typically MM origin leiomyoma of the esophagus are intramural, single, round to oval protruding masses like a polyp less than 2 cm in diameter, covered with intact normal mucosa, and usually are found incidentally.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref> Tumor growth seems to be slow, however, the rate of growth, the period needed to observe a change, and size of tumor at risk of malignant transformation are uncertain. The leiomyomas derived from the MM layer of the esophagus usually protrude into the lumen and are likely to become polypoid or pedunculated due to the effects of the constant downward drag of food and peristalsis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref> Such MM originating polypoid leiomyomas are ideal candidates for endoscopic resection and can be removed safely with current modernized endoscopic resection methods. In our study, seven leiomyomas originating from the MM were all polypoid or pedunculated in shape suitable for endoscopic removal.</p><p>In recent years, EUS has improved the detection rate and differentiation of leiomyomas in the upper gastrointestinal tract.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref> EUS can determine the layer of origin, direction of growth, and histologic consistency of the tumor as it can demonstrate echogenic differences between the various submucosal tumors, reflecting their etiologic differences. Criteria for the identification of a leiomyoma derived from the MM of the esophagus are: 1) presence of hypoechoic mass of the second layer of the esophageal wall with well-defined boundaries, 2) homogenous internal echo pattern, and 3) normal overlying mucosa. EUS with high frequency ultrasonic probe is superior to other imaging modalities for detecting the origins of leiomyomas and estimating histologic characteristics of tumors,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> as a conventional EUS has difficulty capturing the precise images of small leiomyomas in the esophagus because of difficulty in direct visualization of the tumors and its poor imaging resolution with low frequency ultrasound. High frequency ultrasonic endoprobe can provide direct endoscopic visualization of a small tumor during ultrasonic scanning and it is easier to access a small mural esophageal lesion. A precise diagnosis of small esophageal leiomyoma derived from MM can be achieved by demonstrating fine layer structure and high endosonograhic - histologic concordance with high frequency ultrasonic endoprobe. It is valuable in assessing the origin and size of the tumor and for determining whether or not endoscopic resection is required.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref> In our study, a 3 mm sized small esophageal leiomyoma derived from MM, which was too small to be demonstrated with conventional EUS, was clearly diagnosed with balloon-tipped high frequency ultrasonic endoprobe. In all of our cases, endosonographic findings by endoprobe were exactly concordant with pathologic findings of resected tumors. Leiomyomas have a tendency toward continuous endoluminal growth and the possibility of malignant transformation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref> Preoperative pathological diagnosis of a smooth muscle cell tumor is impossible because the differentiation of benign and malignant smooth muscle tumors is mainly based on the mitotic figures of several fields of entire resected specimen. Esophageal leiomyomas derived from the MM in our study, showed a tendency to become more pedunculated as the size increased. The endoscopic resection of a small tumor, less than 2 cm in size, and limited to the mucosa or submucosa could be performed with negligible risk of perforation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref> Endoprobe is an important diagnostic method for smooth muscle tumors of the esophagus and the assessment of potential candidates for endoscopic resection. It is believed that endoprobe can have a great impact in the therapeutic decision-making in small esophageal leiomyomas because of its capacity to clearly define the size and layer of tumor origin.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref></p><p>In conclusion, balloon-tipped endoprobe is an easy and very convenient technique to scan the small MM-derived leiomyomas of the esophagus, even for tumors under 5 mm, useful in making an accurate diagnosis of esophageal leiomyoma derived from MM, and in decision-making for appropriate application of EMR.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attah</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajdu</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benign and malignant tumors of the esophagus at autopsy</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>1968</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5644217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lattuada</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zappa</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cioffi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Simone</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of leiomyoma of the esophagus with endoscopic ultrasonography</article-title><source>HepatoGastroenterology</source><year>1997</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9222681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kajiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Torii</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Uose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endoscopic aspiration lumpectomy of esophageal leiomyomas derived from the muscularis mucosae</article-title><source>Am J Gastroenterol</source><year>1995</year><volume>90</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>417</fpage><fpage>422</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7872281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tio</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tytgat</surname><given-names>GNJ</given-names></name><name><surname>den Hartog Jager</surname><given-names>FCA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endoscopic ultrasonography for the evaluation of smooth muscle tumors in the upper gastrointestinal tract: an experience with 42 cases</article-title><source>Gastrointest Endosc</source><year>1990</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2210274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faivre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bory</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulinier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benign tumors of oesophagus: Value of endoscopy</article-title><source>Endoscopy</source><year>1978</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">216542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Higashino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Osugi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokuhara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utility of endoscopic ultrasonography in assessing the indications for endoscopic surgery of submucosal esophageal submucosal tumors</article-title><source>Surg Endosc</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10064751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Parra-Blanco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis of submucosal tumor of the upper GI tract by endoscopic resection</article-title><source>Gastrointest Endosc</source><year>1999</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10502173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenblum</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leiomyoma of the esophagus</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><year>1984</year><volume>199</volume><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6696540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruns</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endoscopic electrosurgical polypectomies of the upper gastrointestinal tract</article-title><source>Am J Gastroenterol</source><year>1977</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">596354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endoscopic treatment of submucosal lesions of the gastrointestinal tract</article-title><source>Endoscopy</source><year>1992</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1587236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic value of endoscopic ultrasonography for gastrointestinal leiomyoma</article-title><source>World J Gastroenterol</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2088</fpage><lpage>2091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12970912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleischer</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endoscopic resection of gastrointestinal tumors</article-title><source>Endoscopy</source><year>1993</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8261992</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Endoscopic finding of case No. 4 demonstrates a submucosal tumor with intact overlying mucosa.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ymj-46-61-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>High frequency ultrasonic endosonographic finding of case No. 4 shows a clear homogenous hypoechoic mass derived from the second layer of the esophagus (M, mass; MM, lamina muscularis mucosae; SM, submucosa; PM, proper muscle).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ymj-46-61-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Microscopic finding of resected specimens demonstrates the leiomyoma derived from the muscularis mucosae of the esophagus. Uniform, interlacing bundles of spindle-like cells without any mitotic bodies are seen (H&#x00026;E stain, &#x000d7; 40).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ymj-46-61-g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of Patients with Esophageal Leiomyomas Derived from MM</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ymj-46-61-i001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>*</sup>by Yamada's Classification.</p><p>homo/hypo, homogenous/hypoechoic; EMR, endoscopic mucosal resection; EMR-C, EMR using transparent cap; MM, lamina muscularis mucosae.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>
