<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">HPB Surg</journal-id><journal-title>HPB Surgery</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0894-8569</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1607-8462</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">1610725</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2442942</article-id>
		<article-id pub-id-type="pii">S089485699259508X</article-id>
		<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/1992/59508</article-id>
	<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prospective Evaluation of Ultrasonic Surgical Dissectors in Hepatic Resection: A Cooperative Multicenter Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group>
		<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Millat</surname><given-names>Bertrand</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib>
		<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>Jean-Marie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib>
		<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Descottes</surname><given-names>Bernard</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib>
		<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Fingerhut</surname><given-names>Abe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib>
		<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fagniez</surname><given-names>Pierre-Louis </given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib>
	</contrib-group>
		<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>
			<addr-line>H&#x000f4;pital Antoine B&#x000e9;cl&#x000e8;re</addr-line>
			<addr-line>Clamart</addr-line>
			<country>France</country>
		</aff>
		<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>
			<addr-line>H&#x000f4;pital Louis Mourier</addr-line>
			<addr-line>Colombes</addr-line>
			<country>France</country>
		</aff>
		<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>
			<addr-line>H&#x000f4;piml Dupuytren</addr-line>
			<addr-line>Limoges</addr-line>
			<country>France</country>
		</aff>
		<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>
			<addr-line>Centre Hospitalier Intercommunal</addr-line>
			<addr-line>10 rue de Champ Gaillard</addr-line>
			<addr-line>Poissy Cedex</addr-line>
			<addr-line>78303</addr-line>
			<country>France</country>
		</aff>
		<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>
			<addr-line>H&#x000f4;pital Henry Mondor</addr-line>
			<addr-line>Creteil</addr-line>
			<country>France</country>
		</aff>
	<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>1992</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>8</month><year>1991</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>1991</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1992 Hindawi Publishing Corporation.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>1992</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/"><p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract>
		<p>Blood loss is the major cause of postoperative mortality and morbidity associated with hepatic resection.
A prospective multicenter study was conducted to determine if ultrasonic dissectors (USD) were useful
in hepatic resection and could reduce this hemorrhagic risk. Forty-seven hepatic resections were
performed in 42 consecutive patients during a two month period in 11 public, surgical centers.
Twenty-one patients had primary or secondary malignancies, six had benign tumors, two had biliary
cysts, one had cholangiocarcinoma, one had Caroli&#x02019;s disease, and 11 had hydatid cysts of the liver. Two
different USD devices were evaluated (CUSA System-Lasersonics and NIIC-DX 101 T). The hepatic
resections tested included a wide range of procedures. Each surgeon had the possibility of choosing
between the USD and his own usual technique for each operative step and according to local conditions.
The average volume of blood infused, irrespective of the underlying pathology or the procedure
performed, was 1.0 L (range 0-4.8 L). Fourteen patients required no transfusions. No operative or
immediate postoperative deaths were recorded. Five major complications, all unrelated to the use of the
USD, developed in three patients. Access to intra and extraparenchymal arterial and venous tributaries
and particularly the control of the hepatic veins were facilitated by USD. While transection of hepatic
parenchyma was neither easier nor faster than with conventional techniques, it was found to be less
hemorrhagic. Overall appraisal was expressed on an analog scale; the USD was found to be helpful or
very helpful in 75 percent of all resections. With regard to the pathology being treated, total or partial
excision of hydatid cysts was greatly enhanced by the use of the USD while this benefit was not found for
wedge resections of other hepatic lesions. With regard to user friendliness and maintenance, the
NIIC-DX 101 T device was preferred. We conclude that the USD facilitates formal hepatic resections.
Converging opinions emerging from various surgical centers reinforce this conclusion.</p>
	</abstract></article-meta></front></article>


