<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group|1</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9703289</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2063041</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intensive weekly chemotherapy for locally advanced gastric cancer using 5-fluorouracil, cisplatin, epidoxorubicin, 6S-leucovorin, glutathione and filgrastim: a report from the Italian Group for the Study of Digestive Tract Cancer (GISCAD).</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cascinu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Labianca</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Graziano</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pancera</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Frontini</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Luporini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Division of Medical Oncology, S. Salvatore Hospital, Pesaro, Italy.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>78</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><abstract><p>Local extension prevents curative resection in more than two-thirds of gastric cancer patients. Unfortunately, resectability is one of the main prognostic factors in these patients, and survival is longer when tumours are completely removed. Preoperative chemotherapy is an attractive concept for obtaining curative resection. Thirty-two locally advanced unresectable gastric cancer patients were enrolled in five Italian Group for the Study of Digestive Tract Cancer (GISCAD) centres. For 16 patients, surgical unresectability was based on computerized tomography scan evaluation of tumour size (four patients) and invasion of adjacent structures (12 patients), whereas in another 16 patients locally advanced disease was confirmed by laparotomy. They received weekly administration of cisplatin 40 mg m(-2), 5-fluorouracil 500 mg m(-2), epidoxorubicin 35 mg m(-2), 6S-stereoisomer of leucovorin 250 mg m(-2) and glutathione 1.5 g m(-2). From the day after to the day before each chemotherapy administration, filgrastim was administered by subcutaneous injection at a dose of 5 microg kg(-1). One cycle of therapy consisted of eight weekly treatments. Fifteen of 32 patients (47%) responded to chemotherapy, whereas 13 (41 %) had stable disease and four (12%) progressed on therapy. Of the 15 responding patients, 13 were completely resected after chemotherapy and two of them had a complete pathological response. Two clinically responding patients were found unresectable at operation because of peritoneal seeding. At a median follow-up from the start of treatment of 24 months (range 11-39 months), 10 of 13 resected patients are alive and eight are relapse free. Three patients died after 11, 12, and 14 months respectively. Toxicity was acceptable: side-effects consisted mainly of grade II National Cancer Institute common toxicity criteria (NCICTC) leucopenia and thrombocytopenia in ten patients. Neither treatment-related death nor surgical complications in patients undergoing surgery were observed. This weekly intensive regimen enabled resection in half of previously inoperable tumours with a moderate toxicity. It can be offered to patients with locally advanced unresectable gastric cancer to obtain curative resection.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00003-0114.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="390" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00003-0115.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="391" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00003-0116.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="392" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00003-0117.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="393" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

