<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7577483</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2033917</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intrapleural administration of interleukin 2 in pleural mesothelioma: a phase I-II study.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goey</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eggermont</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Punt</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Slingerland</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gratama</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oosterom</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oskam</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bolhuis</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stoter</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Medical Oncology, Rotterdam Cancer Institute (Daniel den Hoed Kliniek), The Netherlands.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>1995</year></pub-date><volume>72</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1283</fpage><lpage>1288</lpage><abstract><p>Twenty-three patients with pleural mesothelioma stage I-IIA were entered in a study of continuous daily intrapleural infusion of interleukin 2 (IL-2) for 14 days, repeated every 4 weeks. IL-2 was administered according to a groupwise dose escalation schedule (group A, 3 x 10(4); group B, 3 x 10(5); group C, 3 x 10(6); group D, 6 x 10(6); group E, 18 x 10(6); and group F, 36 x 10(6) IU day-1). Each group consisted of at least three patients. Intrapleural administration of IL-2 was associated with acceptable toxicity. All patients were treated on an outpatient basis except for the patients at dose levels E and F. Dose-limiting toxicity was observed at level F, 36 x 10(6) IU daily, and consisted of catheter infection, fever and flu-like symptoms. Intrapleural IL-2 levels were high (&#x0003e; 20,000 IU ml-1) at levels E and F, while serum levels in most patients were not or barely detectable (&#x0003c; 3-30 IU ml-1). Intrapleural IL-2 levels were up to 6000-fold higher than systemic levels. Intrapleural tumour necrosis factor alpha (TNF-alpha) levels varied greatly and did not correlate with IL-2 dosage. Intrapleural mononuclear cells (MNCs) displayed IL-2-induced lymphokine-activated killer (LAK) activity in all patients. Two patients were not evaluable for response owing to catheter-related problems which precluded the delivery of IL-2. Partial response (PR) occurred in 4 of 21 evaluable patients (19%; 95% confidence interval 5-42%) with a median time to progression of 12 months (range 5-37). Stable disease (SD) occurred in seven patients with a median time to progression of 5 months (range 2-7). There were no complete responses (CRs). The median overall survival was 15.6 months (range 3.0-43). No relationship between the dose of IL-2 and response rate was observed. We conclude that IL-2 given intrapleurally is accompanied with acceptable toxicity and has anti-tumour activity against mesothelioma. In view of the refractory nature of the disease IL-2 may be a treatment option for mesothelioma. A formal phase II study is warranted. Based on the observed toxicity, the lack of dose-response relationship and the immunomodulatory effects seen at relatively low-dose IL-2, the recommended dose for a phase II study is 3 x 10(6) IU day-1 using the present treatment schedule.</p><sec sec-type="scanned-figures"><title>Images</title><fig id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00045-0226-a" xlink:role="1286"/></fig></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00045-0223.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1283" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00045-0224.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1284" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00045-0225.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1285" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00045-0226.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1286" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00045-0227.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1287" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00045-0228.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1288" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

