<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Yale J Biol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">yjbm</journal-id><journal-title>The Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0044-0086</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1551-4056</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8748463</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2590840</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The effect of supplemental beta-carotene on immunologic indices in patients with AIDS: a pilot study.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fryburg</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Askenase</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Division of Endocrinology and Metabolism, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, Connecticut, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Apr</season><year>1995</year></pub-date><volume>68</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><abstract><p>Patients with the acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) are characterized by a decrease in the number of T helper cells, a defect that is linked to the impaired immunologic competence. Vitamin A and its dietary precursor, beta-carotene, increase absolute T helper cell counts as well as indices of T cell function in both human and animal models. To determine if short-term beta-carotene treatment affects T lymphocyte subsets in patients with AIDS, a single-blind, non-randomized clinical trial of beta-carotene was performed in seven patients with AIDS. Enrollment criteria included no evidence of: a) active opportunistic infection: b) greater than 1 kilogram change in weight in the month preceding enrollment; c) chronic diarrhea or malabsorption; and d) hepatic disease or significant anemia. Beta-carotene was given with meals in two divided doses of 60 mg/day for four weeks; this was followed by no therapy for six weeks. Samples for total white blood cell, lymphocyte and T lymphocyte subset counts were measured at baseline, at the end of four weeks of treatment and another six weeks after treatment had stopped. P24 antigen, beta-2 microglobulin and liver function tests were also measured. All subjects tolerated the treatment well without evidence of toxicity. In response to beta-carotene, total lymphocyte counts rose by 66 percent (.05 &#x0003c; p &#x0003c; .10), and CD4+ cells rose slightly, but insignificantly, in the entire group. In all three of the patients who had baseline CD4+ cells greater than 10/microliters, however, the mean absolute increase in CD4+ cells in response to beta-carotene was 53 +/- 10 cells/microliters (p &#x0003c; .01). Six weeks off beta-carotene treatment, the absolute CD4+ cell count returned to pretreatment levels (p &#x0003c; .01). No change was observed in CD8+ cells. P24 antigen and beta-2 microglobulin did not change during treatment. These preliminary observations suggest that short-term treatment with beta-carotene may increase CD4+ cell counts in patients with AIDS who have greater than 10 cells/microliters.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="yjbm00037-0022.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="19" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="yjbm00037-0023.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="20" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="yjbm00037-0024.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="21" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="yjbm00037-0025.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="22" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="yjbm00037-0026.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="23" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

