<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8624269</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2074415</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Metabolic effects of pamidronate in patients with metastatic bone disease.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vinholes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Purohit</surname><given-names>O. P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eastell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>YCRC Department of Clinical Oncology, Weston Park Hospital, University of Sheffield, UK.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>73</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1089</fpage><lpage>1095</lpage><abstract><p>We have evaluated the value of specific bone resorption markers in monitoring metastatic bone disease to define the duration of action of a single high-dose pamidronate infusion. Twenty patients received a single infusion of pamidronate 120 mg for painful bone metastases. Ten out of these 20 patients also received a second infusion. They were evaluated at baseline, 2, 4 and 8 weeks after each infusion. A composite pain questionnaire, serum and urine tests were carried out at these time points. Bone resorption markers measured included urinary calcium, hydroxyproline and two new markers: pyridinoline and deoxypyridinoline. Reference values were defined by 20 healthy controls matched by age and sex. Pamidronate induced a profound fall in bone resorption with a maximal effect within the first month after therapy. Changes in urinary calcium levels were confounded by a rise of 100% in the parathyroid hormone levels. Before treatment, pyridinoline and deoxypyridinoline were increased in 70% of patients, while urinary calcium was increased in only 40% of them. Thirteen patients had a &#x0003e; or = 50% fall in deoxypyridinoline levels and were considered as biochemical responders. These patients had a mean reduction in pain score of about 30% of baseline levels, which was significantly higher than the seven non-biochemical responders. In conclusion, urinary calcium is not a precise marker of bone resorption. Deoxypyridinoline seems to be the most specific bone resorption marker in cancer patients. Biochemical responders have the most benefit from pamidronate in terms of pain relief. This suggests that patients may benefit from more potent or repeated infusions of bisphosphonates.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00037-0069.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1089" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00037-0070.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1090" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00037-0071.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1091" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00037-0072.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1092" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00037-0073.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1093" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00037-0074.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1094" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00037-0075.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1095" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

