<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7779728</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2033845</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Phase II and pharmacokinetic study of lobaplatin in patients with relapsed ovarian cancer.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gietema</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Veldhuis</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guchelaar</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Willemse</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uges</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cats</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boonstra</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van der Graaf</surname><given-names>W. T.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sleijfer</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name></contrib><etal/></contrib-group><aff>Department of Medical Oncology, University Hospital Groningen, The Netherlands.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>1995</year></pub-date><volume>71</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1302</fpage><lpage>1307</lpage><abstract><p>In phase I studies, lobaplatin showed activity in ovarian cancer patients pretreated with platinum. A phase II trial with lobaplatin was performed in patients with refractory or relapsed ovarian cancer to define activity and pharmacokinetics. Twenty-two patients were treated with lobaplatin administered as an intravenous bolus every 4 weeks. Dependent on creatinine clearance (CRCL) patients received 30 or 50 mg m-2 lobaplatin as the starting dose. Twenty-two patients received 78 courses (median 3, range 1-6). In eight patients total platinum (TPt) in plasma and urine, free platinum (FPt) in plasma ultrafiltrate (both measured by atomic absorption spectrometry) and lobaplatin in plasma ultrafiltrate measured (by high-performance liquid chromatography) were measured. Toxicity was confined to mild nausea and vomiting, mild leucocytopenia (WHO grade 3 in 18% of the courses), and renal function-related thrombocytopenia (WHO grade 3/4 in 53% of the courses). A correlation was found between CRCL and reduction in platelet count (r = -0.77; P &#x0003c; 0.01). No renal toxicity was encountered. Five of 21 evaluable patients (24%) achieved a response (four complete remissions and one partial remission). Remissions occurred mainly in patients who relapsed more than 6 months after primary treatment. The median survival from start of lobaplatin treatment was 8 months. The mean areas under the curve (AUCs) were 4.2 +/- 0.5, 3.0 +/- 0.6, and 3.2 +/- 1.1 h mgl-1 for TPt, FPt and lobaplatin respectively. The free platinum fraction (FPt/TPt) was initially very high, indicating low protein binding. FPt was essentially present as intact lobaplatin. Four hours after infusion 54 +/- 5% and 24 h after infusion 74 +/- 3% of the lobaplatin dose was excreted in the urine. In conclusion, lobaplatin is a platinum compound with anti-tumour activity in patients with relapsed ovarian cancer, especially in those who have platinum-sensitive tumours. The main toxicity of lobaplatin is thrombocytopenia and its dose should be corrected according to renal function.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00052-0182.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1302" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00052-0183.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1303" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00052-0184.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1304" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00052-0185.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1305" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00052-0186.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1306" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00052-0187.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="1307" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

