<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><!-- Original-type: ra--><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10584882</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2374313</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6690829</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjc.6690829</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Regular Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Physical and psychological symptoms of quality of life in the CHART randomized trial in head and neck cancer: short-term and long-term patient reported symptoms</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>G O</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parmar</surname><given-names>M K B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>A J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><collab>on behalf of the C. H. A. R. T. Steering Committee</collab></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Cancer Division, Medical Research Council Clinical Trials Unit, 222 Euston Road, London NW1 2DA, UK</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>1999</year></pub-date><volume>81</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1196</fpage><lpage>1205</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>11</month><year>1998</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>15</day><month>04</month><year>1999</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>06</month><year>1999</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright 1999, Cancer Research Campaign</copyright-statement><copyright-year>1999</copyright-year><permissions><copyright-holder>Cancer Research Campaign</copyright-holder></permissions><abstract><p>The randomized multicentre trial of continuous hyperfractionated accelerated radiotherapy (CHART) versus conventional radiotherapy in patients with advanced head and neck cancer showed no good evidence of a difference in any of the major clinical outcomes of survival, freedom from metastases, loco-regional control and disease-free survival. Therefore an assessment of the effect of treatment on physical and psychological symptoms is vital to balance the costs and benefits of the two treatments. A total of 615 patients were asked to complete a Rotterdam Symptom Checklist and the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale, which cover a variety of physical and psychological symptoms, at a total of ten time points. The data consisted of short-term data (the initial 3 months) and long-term data (1 and 2 years). The short-term data was split into an exploratory data set and a confirmatory data set, and analysed using subject-specific and group-based methods. Differences were only claimed if hypotheses generated in the exploratory data set were confirmed in the confirmatory data set. The long-term data was not split into two data sets and was analysed using a group-based approach. There was evidence of significantly worse symptoms of pain at day 21 in those treated with CHART and significantly worse symptoms of cough and hoarseness at 6 weeks in those treated conventionally. There was also evidence to suggest a higher degree of decreased sexual interest at 1 year and sore muscles at 2 years in those treated with conventional radiotherapy. There is no clear indication that one regimen is superior to the other in terms of &#x02018;quality of life&#x02019;, generally the initially more severe reaction in the CHART group being offset by the longer duration of symptoms in the conventionally treated group. &#x000a9; 1999 Cancer Research Campaign</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>symptoms</kwd><kwd>head and neck cancer</kwd><kwd>radiotherapy</kwd><kwd>CHART</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front></article>


