<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7917917</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2033427</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A phase II study of regional 5-fluorouracil infusion with intravenous folinic acid for colorectal liver metastases.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>O'Gorman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McArdle</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>University Department of Surgery, Royal Infirmary, Glasgow, UK.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>1994</year></pub-date><volume>70</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><abstract><p>Regional chemotherapy, delivered via the hepatic artery, may significantly increase tumour response rates in patients with colorectal liver metastases. However, survival is limited by extrahepatic disease progression. We have developed a novel therapeutic approach for patients with metastases confined to the liver. In order to achieve high local response rates and also inhibit extrahepatic progression, 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) was infused intra-arterially at a dose previously calculated to achieve both high-dose regional therapy and adequate systemic levels. To enhance efficacy further, 5-FU was combined with high-dose systemic folinic acid (FA). Thirty-one patients were evaluated in a phase II study. 5-FU (1.5 g m2) was infused via a surgically implanted hepatic artery catheter over a 24 h period; FA (total 400 mg m-2) was infused intravenously during the initial and final 2 h. Treatments were given weekly for cycles of 6 weeks' duration. To date, median duration of treatment is 6 months and the median follow-up period is 17 months. The overall response rate was 48% with two complete and 13 partial responses. Predicted median time to progression is 8 months. The site of first progression was hepatic in 10 (42%) and extrahepatic in 14 (58%) patients. Seven patients developed local complications; one required emergency surgery. Side-effects were limited to grade 3 toxicity (four patients) or less. Predicted median survival is 19 months. This approach, which is associated with a high response rate and low systemic toxicity, warrants further evaluation. A phase III study is planned.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0107.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="677" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0108.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="678" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0109.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="679" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0110.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="680" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

