<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7841054</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2033601</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>EORTC (30885) randomised phase III study with recombinant interferon alpha and recombinant interferon alpha and gamma in patients with advanced renal cell carcinoma. The EORTC Genitourinary Group.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>De Mulder</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oosterhof</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bouffioux</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Oosterom</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vermeylen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sylvester</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Medical Oncology, University Hospital Nijmegen, The Netherlands.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>1995</year></pub-date><volume>71</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>375</lpage><abstract><p>In the treatment of renal cell carcinoma both complete (CRs) and partial remissions (PRs) have been obtained using recombinant (r) interferon alpha (IFN-alpha), with response rates ranging from 0 to 31% (mean 16%). rIFN-gamma is a potent immunostimulating agent, but the clinical experience of its use is limited and results are conflicting. In a phase II study with the combination of rIFN-alpha 2c (Boehringer Ingelheim) and rIFN-gamma (Genentech, supplied by Boehringer Ingelheim) in 31 eligible patients, a response rate of 25% was recorded. Based on this observation a randomised phase III study was initiated to investigate the possible advantage of the addition rIFN-gamma to rIFN-alpha 2c treatment. Treatment consisted of rIFN-alpha 2c 30 micrograms m-2 = 10 x 10(6) IU m-2 s.c. twice weekly in arm A and the same dose of rIFN-alpha combined with rIFN-gamma 100 micrograms m-2 = 2 x 10(6) IU m-2 in arm B. Eligibility criteria included documented progression of disease; patients with bone lesions only and overt central nervous system metastases were excluded. Between November 1988 and September 1990, 102 patients were entered into the study. An interim analysis showed a response in 7/53 (13%) patients (two CRs and five PRs) in the rIFN-alpha 2c monotherapy arm and in 2/45 (4%) (one CR and one PR) patients in the combination arm. This difference was not statistically significant (P = 0.17). The probability of missing an eventual 10% advantage for the combination is 0.001. The numbers are insufficient to rule out a negative effect of the addition of rIFN-gamma. The dose intensity of IFN-alpha 2c for the two treatment arms was the same. The addition of rIFN-gamma does not improve the response rate of rIFN-alpha 2c monotherapy. A possible detrimental effect cannot be excluded.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00048-0159.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="371" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00048-0160.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="372" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00048-0161.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="373" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00048-0162.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="374" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00048-0163.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="375" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

