<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ViewNLM-v2.3.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1229-845X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1976-555X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Korean Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17993748</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2868150</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4142/jvs.2007.8.4.353</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Clinical pharmacokinetics of norfloxacin-glycine acetate after intravenous and oral administration in pigs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Zhi-Qiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>Byung-Chol</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Jong-Choon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>Kyu-Shik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Myung-Heon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>Hyo-In</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>Mi-Hyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Seung-Chun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>College of Veterinary Medicine, Kyungpook National University, Daegu 702-701, Korea.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Lee Gil Ya Cancer and Diabetes Institute, Gachon University of Medicine and Science, Incheon 406-840, Korea.</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>College of Veterinary Medicine, Chonnam National University, Kwangju 500-757, Korea.</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>National Veterinary Research and Quarantine Service, Anyang 430-824, Korea.</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>College of Veterinary Medicine, Chungnam National University, Daejeon 302-305, Korea.</aff><author-notes><corresp>
Corresponding author: Tel: +82-53-950-5964; Fax: +82-53-950-5955, <email>parksch@knu.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2007 The Korean Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year></permissions><abstract><p>The pharmacokinetics and dosage regimen of norfloxacin-glycine acetate (NFLXGA) was investigated in pigs after a single intravenous (i.v.) or oral (p.o.) administration at a dosage of 7.2 mg/kg body weight. After both i.v. and p.o. administration, plasma drug concentrations were best fitted to an open two-compartment model with a rapid distribution phase. After i.v. administration of NFLXGA, the distribution (t<sub>1/2&#x003b1;</sub>) and elimination half-life (t<sub>1/2&#x003b2;</sub>) were 0.36 &#x000b1; 0.07 h and 7.42 &#x000b1; 3.55 h, respectively. The volume of distribution of NFLXGA at steady state (Vd<sub>ss</sub>) was 4.66 &#x000b1; 1.39 l/kg. After p.o. administration of NFLXGA, the maximal absorption concentration (C<sub>max</sub>) was 0.43 &#x000b1; 0.06 &#x000b5;g/ml at 1.36 &#x000b1; 0.39 h (T<sub>max</sub>). The mean absorption (t<sub>1/2ka</sub>) and elimination half-life (t<sub>1/2&#x003b2;</sub>) of NFLXGA were 0.78 &#x000b1; 0.27 h and 7.13 &#x000b1; 1.41 h, respectively. The mean systemic bioavailability (F) after p.o. administration was 31.10 &#x000b1; 15.16%. We suggest that the optimal dosage calculated from the pharmacokinetic parameters is 5.01 mg/kg per day i.v. or 16.12 mg/kg per day p.o.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>norfloxacin</kwd><kwd>pharmacokinetics</kwd><kwd>pig</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Fluoroquinolones are a group of synthetic antimicrobial agents that are highly potent and exhibit a broad spectrum of activity against a variety of mycoplasmas and Gram-negative bacteria, and some Gram-positive bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Norfloxacin is one of the first modern fluoroquinolone antimicrobial agents featuring a fluorine atom in position 6 and a piperazinyl or pyrrolidinyl substituent in position 7 of the quinoline nucleus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Norfloxacin-glycine acetate (NFLXGA), a newly formulated norfloxacin that exerts its antibacterial effect by breaking double-stranded DNA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], has been widely used for both prevention and therapeutic treatment of bacterial infections in humans and animals.</p><p>The quinolones bear both an acidic group (carboxylic acid) and a basic group (tertiary amine). This association gives them amphoteric properties. Their lipid solubility is low, except between pH 6 and 8. Within this range they have low water solubility and are prone to precipitate under more acidic conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. In order to overcome this problem, we made a new salt form, NFLXGA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. NFLXGA has a high solubility in water and it did not precipitate under acidic conditions ranging from pH 4 to 7 over a 6 month period (data not shown)</p><p>The pharmacokinetics of norfloxacin have been studied in various animals including dogs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], pigs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], chickens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], calves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] and laboratory animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. The optimal dose range of the drug has been suggested to be 5-22 mg/kg body weight in these animals, on the basis of the minimal inhibition concentration (MIC) and the maximal norfloxacin concentration (C<sub>max</sub>) in blood following drug administration. In our previous studies, we reported the pharmacokinetics of NFLXGA in flounder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], horse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] and rabbits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>].</p><p>In recent years, it has been suggested that the optimal dosage should be set in terms of pharmacokinetic-pharmacodynamic (PK/PD) relationships [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. The pharmacokinetics of NFLXGA after oral administration has not been established in pigs. Therefore, the present study was designed to provide the clinical pharmacokinetics of norfloxacin following intravenous (i.v.) and oral (p.o.) administration in pigs and to determine the optimal dosage on the basis of the PK/PD parameters.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals</title><p>Six male pigs weighing 60 &#x000b1; 5 kg were used in this study. The animals were reared and maintained at the Chungnam National University Farm. They were housed indoors and fed with a drug-free commercial pellet diet and water <italic>ad libitum</italic>. The Animal Ethics Committee of the Veterinary Faculty at Chungnam National University approved the study.</p></sec><sec><title>Treatment</title><p>The study was carried out in a two-period crossover manner with animals randomly divided into two groups of three pigs. In period 1, three pigs received NFLXGA (Daesung Microbiologicals, Korea) i.v. over 40 sec at a dose of 7.2 mg/kg whilst three other pigs received the same dose of norfloxacin p.o. The formulation of NFLXGA consisted of norfloxacin (0.75 parts), acetic acid (0.15 parts) and glycine (0.1 part) based on mass. After an interval of 21 days, the treatments were reversed, i.e., pigs that previously received NFLXGA i.v. were administered the drug p.o., and those that initially received NFLXGA p.o. were administered the drug i.v. in period 2.</p></sec><sec><title>Blood sampling</title><p>5 ml blood samples were collected from the jugular vein directly into tubes before (0 h) and 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24 h following drug administration. The serum samples were separated by centrifugation at 8,000 g for 5 min and were stored at -70&#x02103; (for up to one week) until determination of the norfloxacin concentration.</p></sec><sec><title>Norfloxacin analysis</title><p>The amount of norfloxacin was measured by high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) using the method described previously by Park et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Briefly, 1 ml serum was deproteinated with 1 ml 20% cold trichloroacetic acid in methanol. The mixture was vortexed for 1 min and centrifuged for 5 min at 15,000 g. 20 &#x000b5;l of each supernatant was injected into a HPLC system equipped with a reverse phase column (particle size 10 &#x000b5;m; 30 cm &#x000d7; 3.6 mm) and measured at a UV wavelength of 278 nm. The mobile phase was composed of 20% citric acid, 0.01 M phosphate buffer containing 1 mM heptane sulfonic acid and acetonitrile (800 : 1 : 200 = v/v/v) and the pH was adjusted to 3.0 with phosphoric acid. The validated limit of norfloxacin quantification for this method was 0.05 &#x000b5;g/ml. The extraction recoveries were greater than 80% and the coefficient of variation was less than 10% indicating high reproducibility.</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis and dosage regimen</title><p>All pharmacokinetic parameters were derived using the WinNonlin software package (SCI, USA). The individual serum concentration data following administration were analyzed by nonlinear least-squares regression analysis. The best fit was achieved with a two-compartment model for both i.v. and p.o. administration. As a result, the serum concentration time curves of norfloxacin after a single i.v. or p.o. dose were fitted to the following equations:</p><p><italic>C</italic><sub>i.v.</sub> = <italic>A</italic>e<sup>-&#x003b1;t</sup> + <italic>B</italic>e<sup>-&#x003b2;t</sup></p><p><italic>C</italic><sub>p.o.</sub> = <italic>A</italic>e<sup>-&#x003b1;t</sup> + <italic>B</italic>e<sup>-&#x003b2;t</sup> - <italic>C</italic>e<sup>-kat</sup></p><p>where (<italic>C</italic><sub>i.v.</sub>) and (<italic>C</italic><sub>p.o.</sub>) are the concentrations in serum at time <italic>t</italic> after i.v. and p.o. administration respectively; <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> are the zero-time serum drug concentration intercepts of biphasic i.v. and p.o. disposition curves; <italic>C</italic> is the zero-time serum drug concentration intercept of the absorption phase after p.o. administration; e is the base of the natural logarithm; &#x003b1; is the hybrid rate constant of the slope of distribution phase; &#x003b2; is the hybrid rate constant of the slope of elimination phase; and <italic>k</italic><sub>a</sub> is the hybrid rate constant of the slope of absorption. Following p.o. administration, the bioavailability <italic>F</italic> was calculated according to the equation:</p><p>F (%) = (AUC<sub>p.o.</sub>/AUC<sub>i.v.</sub>) &#x000d7; (&#x003b2;<sub>p.o</sub>/&#x003b2;<sub>i.v.</sub>) &#x000d7; 100%.</p><p>The equations used for calculating dosage in pigs were as follows:</p><p>Dose<sub>iv</sub> = C<sub>ave</sub> &#x000d7; Clearance = C<sub>ave</sub> &#x000d7; Vd<sub>ss</sub> &#x000d7; (0.693/t<sub>1/2&#x003b2;</sub>);</p><p>Dose<sub>po</sub> = Dose<sub>iv</sub>/F.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>The concentrations-time curves of norfloxacin following single i.v. and p.o. administration of 7.2 mg NFLXGA/kg body weight to pigs are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>. Concentration versus time data were analyzed to achieve the best fit with a two-compartment model after both routes of administration in all pigs. The pharmacokinetic parameters are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>15 min after i.v. and p.o. administration of NFLXGA, the serum concentrations of norfloxacin were 5.22 &#x000b1; 1.40 &#x000b5;g/ml and 0.18 &#x000b1; 0.08 &#x000b5;g/ml, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>.). Thereafter, serum norfloxacin concentrations were maintained in all animals for up to 24 h at more than 0.05 &#x000b1; 0.03 &#x000b5;g/ml (i.v.) and 0.03 &#x000b1; 0.02 &#x000b5;g/ml (p.o.). The distribution rate constant was 1.96 &#x000b1; 0.36 h after i.v. administration with a distribution half-life (<italic>t</italic><sub>1/2&#x003b1;</sub>) of 0.36 &#x000b1; 0.07 h.</p><p>The serum concentration of norfloxacin reached a maximum level (C<sub>max</sub>) of 0.43 &#x000b1; 0.06 &#x000b5;g/ml at 1.36 &#x000b1; 0.39 h (T<sub>max</sub>), and the absorption half-life (<italic>t</italic><sub>1/2ka</sub>) was 0.78 &#x000b1; 0.27 h after p.o. administration in pigs. The mean elimination half-lives (<italic>t</italic><sub>1/2&#x003b2;</sub>) after i.v. and p.o. administration were 7.42 &#x000b1; 3.55 h and 7.13 &#x000b1; 1.41 h respectively, and there are no significant differences. The systemic bioavailability (F) after oral administration of NFLXGA was 31.10 &#x000b1; 15.16%.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The mean elimination half-life (t<sub>1/2&#x003b2;</sub>) after i.v. administration of NFLXGA in the present study was estimated to be 7.42 &#x000b1; 3.55 h. This is longer than the t<sub>1/2&#x003b2;</sub>in rabbits (3.93 &#x000b1; 1.54 h) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] or horses (5.44 &#x000b1; 1.36 h) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], and also longer than that found in the previous studies of norfloxacin in pigs (3.65 &#x000b1; 0.16 h) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] and dogs (3.56 h) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], and that of norfloxacin nicotinate in swine (2.1 h) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] and donkeys (3.51 &#x000b1; 0.49 h) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. It is however a little shorter than that seen in chickens (8.0 &#x000b1; 0.3 h) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The volume of distribution at steady state (Vd<sub>SS</sub>, 4.66 &#x000b1; 1.39 l/kg) was higher than the previously reported value (2.21 &#x000b1; 0.21 l/kg) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], and the ratio of <italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub>21</sub> was 3.58. All of these findings suggested that the drug was well distributed and retained in the tissues. After p.o. administration of NFLXGA, the mean elimination half-life (<italic>t</italic><sub>1/2&#x003b2;</sub>) was 7.13 &#x000b1; 1.41 h, similar to that obtained after i.v. administration. It has been reported that the systemic bioavailability (F) of norfloxacin is only 30 to 40% after p.o. administration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. In the present study, F was calculated to be about 31.10%, which is lower than the values determined in rabbits (40%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>], and in broiler chickens (57.0%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], but is significantly higher than the oral bioavailability of norfloxacin nicotinate in donkeys with F values of 9.6% and 6.4% for the 10 and 20 mg/kg doses respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. In pigs, however we could not find the optimal dosage using PK and PD parameters.</p><p>The optimal dosage of drug can be determined with the equation provided by Toutain et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], which is related to PK and PD parameters. In addition, Schentag stated previously that the AUC/MIC (AUIC) ratio of quinolones should be more than 125 to prevent selective pressure that leads to the overgrowth of resistant bacterial sub-populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. The MIC of norfloxacin has been shown to be below 0.12 &#x000b5;g/ml for <italic>Escherichia coli, Salmonella spp., Klebsiella pneumonia, Klebsiella oxytoca</italic> and <italic>Proteus vulgaris</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Therefore, a desired average serum norfloxacin concentration of 0.48 &#x000b5;g/ml was selected by quadrupling the average MIC values in the present study. We suggest that the appropriate dosage of 5.01 mg/kg for i.v. and 16.12 mg/kg for p.o. per day or 2.51 mg/kg for i.v. and 8.06 mg/kg for p.o. per 12 h would provide a serum concentration in pigs high enough to inhibit bacteria with a MIC less than 0.12 &#x000b5;g/ml. However, NFLXGA should not be considered the drug of choice for pigs infected with pathogenic bacteria, such as <italic>Streptococcus spp</italic>. (MIC, 6.25 &#x000b5;g/ml), <italic>Staphylococcus spp.</italic> (MIC, 1.56 &#x000b5;g/ml), <italic>Rhodococcus spp</italic>. (MIC, 6.26 &#x000b5;g/ml), and <italic>Bordetella spp</italic>. (MIC, 3.12 &#x000b5;g/ml) showing more than 0.25 &#x000b5;g/ml of MIC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This study was supported by Technology Development Program for Agriculture and Forestry, Ministry of Agriculture and Forestry (105036-3) and the Regional Industry Technology Support Business (Daegu). Dr. Zhi-Qiang Chang was supported by Brain Korea 21 program.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Rashood</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Khamis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Sayed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Bella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Yamani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioequivalence evaluation of norfloxacin 400 mg tablets (Uroxin and Noroxin) in healthy human volunteers</article-title><source>Biopharm Drug Dispos</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11180196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anad&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Larra&#x000f1;aga</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics and tissue residues of norfloxacin and its N-desethyl- and oxo-metabolites in healthy pigs</article-title><source>J Vet Pharmacol Ther</source><year>1995</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7674459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anad&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Larra&#x000f1;aga</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Velez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bringas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics of norfloxacin and its N-desethyl- and oxo-metabolites in broiler chickens</article-title><source>Am J Vet Res</source><year>1992</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>2084</fpage><lpage>2089</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1466505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauze</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Weise</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics of norfloxacin in dogs after single intravenous and single and multiple oral administrations of the drug</article-title><source>Am J Vet Res</source><year>1990</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1065</fpage><lpage>1070</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2389884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzeng</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, antibacterial and cytotoxic evaluation of certain 7-substituted norfloxacin derivatives</article-title><source>J Med Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>3809</fpage><lpage>3812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11020298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freddo</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalla Costa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of norfloxacin free interstitial levels in skeletal muscle by microdialysis</article-title><source>J Pharm Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>2433</fpage><lpage>2440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12379929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilfillan</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelak</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bland</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Malatesta</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gadebusch</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetic studies of norfloxacin in laboratory animals</article-title><source>Chemotherapy</source><year>1984</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6237890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gips</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Soback</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Norfloxacin pharmacokinetics in lactating cows with sub-clinical and clinical mastitis</article-title><source>J Vet Pharmacol Ther</source><year>1999</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10447831</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gips</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Soback</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Norfloxacin nicotinate pharmacokinetics in unweaned and weaned calves</article-title><source>J Vet Pharmacol Ther</source><year>1996</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8735421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>San Andr&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>San Andr&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Waxman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of ruminal distribution on norfloxacin pharmacokinetics in adult sheep</article-title><source>J Vet Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2001</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11555178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><source>Quinolone Antimicrobial Agents</source><year>1995</year><edition>2nd ed</edition><publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Society of Microbiology Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laczay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Semj&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative studies on the pharmacokinetics of norfloxacin in chickens, turkeys and geese after a single oral administration</article-title><source>J Vet Pharmacol Ther</source><year>1998</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9597656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lavy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziv</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intravenous disposition kinetics, oral and intramuscular bioavailability and urinary excretion of norfloxacin nicotinate in donkeys</article-title><source>J Vet Pharmacol Ther</source><year>1995</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7629923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical pharmacokinetics of the newer antibacterial 4-quinolones</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source><year>1988</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3282749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Comparative pharmacokinetic profiles of a newly formulated norfloxacin glycine acetate in various animal species</source><year>1996</year><publisher-loc>Korea</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chungnam National University</publisher-name><comment>Ph.D Dissertation</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative pharmacokinetics and tissue distribution of norfloxacin-glycine acetate in flounder, (<italic>paralichthys olivaceus</italic>) at two different temperatures</article-title><source>J Vet Med Sci</source><year>1996</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8916010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical pharmacokinetics of norfloxacin-glycine acetate after intravenous and intramuscular administration to horses</article-title><source>Res Vet Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12507569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative pharmacokinetic profiles of two norfloxacin formulations after oral administration in rabbits</article-title><source>J Vet Med Sci</source><year>1998</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9637308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yielding</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> susceptibility of selected veterinary bacterial pathogens to ciprofloxacin, enrofloxacin and norfloxacin</article-title><source>Can J Vet Res</source><year>1990</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2306672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schentag</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial action and pharmacokinetics/pharmacodynamics: the use of AUIC to improve efficacy and avoid resistance</article-title><source>J Chemother</source><year>1999</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10678784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shem-Tov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziv</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gips</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tissue distribution and binding to plasma proteins of norfloxacin nicotinate after intramuscular administration in pigs</article-title><source>Zentralbl Veterinarmed B</source><year>1994</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7839746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toutain</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Castillo</surname><given-names>JRE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bousquet-Melou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pharmacokinetic-pharmacodynamic approach to a rational dosage regimen for antibiotics</article-title><source>Res Vet Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12204627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gahan</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Filippich</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bredhauer</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Duckworth</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction of norfloxacin with divalent and trivalent pharmaceutical cations. <italic>In vitro</italic> complexation and in vivo pharmacokinetic studies in the dog</article-title><source>J Pharm Sci</source><year>1996</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8863267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wentland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Siporin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Heifetz</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Domagala</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure-activity relationships of fluoroquinolones</article-title><source>The New Generation of Quinolones</source><year>1990</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Marcel Dekker</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Serum concentration of norfloxacin following i.v. (&#x025b2;) or p.o. (&#x025a0;) administration of 7.2 mg NFLXGA per kg body weight (n = 6).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvs-8-353-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Parmacokinetic parameters that describe the disposition of norfloxacin-glycine acetate (7.2 mg/kg body weight) after intravenous and oral administration in six pigs</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvs-8-353-i001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The results were expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD (n = 6). <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>, zero-time serum concentration intercepts of biphasic i.v. and p.o. disposition curves; &#x003b1;, hybrid rate constants of the slope of distribution; &#x003b2;, hybrid rate constants of the slope of elimination; AUC, the area under the concentration-time curves; <italic>t</italic><sub>1/2ka</sub>, the absorption half-life; <italic>t</italic><sub>1/2&#x003b1;</sub>, the distribution half-life; <italic>t</italic><sub>1/2&#x003b2;</sub>, the elimination half-life; <italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub>21</sub>, first-order transfer rate constants for drug distribution from the central compartment to the peripheral compartment and from the peripheral compartment to the central compartment; C<sub>max</sub>, maximum concentration; T<sub>max</sub>, time to reach the maximum concentration; MRT, mean residence time; CLB, serum clearance; AUMC, total area under the moment curve; Vd<sub>SS</sub>, steady-state volume of distribution; F, bioavailability.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>
