<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ViewNLM-v2.3.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608390</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2816309</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2004.19.6.812</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Alpha-Adducin Gly460Trp Polymorphism and Essential Hypertension in Korea</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>Min-Ho</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Eun-Kyung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Hee-Nam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Kyeong-Soo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>Hae-Sung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kweon</surname><given-names>Sun-Seog</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Jin Su</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1">Department of Preventive Medicine, College of Medicine, Seonam University, Gwangju, Korea.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>*</label>Department of Preventive Medicine, Chonnam National University Medical School, Gwangju, Korea.</aff><aff id="A3"><label>&#x02020;</label>Genomic Research Center of Hematopoietic Diseases, Chonnam National University Hospital, Gwangju, Korea.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Address for correspondence: Eun Kyung Chung, M.D. Department of Preventive Medicine, Chonnam National University Medical School, 5 Hak-dong, Dong-gu, Gwangju 501-191, Korea. Tel: +82.62-220-4170, Fax: +82.62-233-0305, <email>sehyukmom@hanmail.net</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>814</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Previous studies have suggested that the Gly460Trp polymorphism of the alpha-adducin gene (<italic>ADD-1</italic>) is associated with salt sensitivity and primary hypertension. The results of linkage or association studies of <italic>ADD-1</italic> of different populations are controversial. This study investigated the relationship between the Gly460Trp polymorphism of <italic>ADD-1</italic> and essential hypertension in a Korean population. The subjects (n=903) were participants in a population-based study in Jangseong County, Korea. The Gly460Trp polymorphism of <italic>ADD-1</italic> was determined using a polymerase chain reaction method. The frequency of the 460Trp allele was 59.4% in normotensives and 61.1% in hypertensives (<italic>p</italic>=0.523). The frequencies of the genotypes did not differ significantly between the hypertensive and normotensive groups (16.3% Gly/Gly, 45.8% Gly/Trp, and 38.0% Trp/Trp in normotensives; 16.2% Gly/Gly, 45.8% Gly/Trp, and 38.0% Trp/Trp in hypertensives; <italic>p</italic>=0.928). After adjusting for other risk factors, Gly/Trp and Trp/Trp were not associated with hypertension (OR 1.00, 95% CI 0.65-1.53, Gly/Trp vs. Gly/Gly; OR 1.22, 95% CI 0.79-1.90, Trp/Trp vs. Gly/Gly). These findings suggest that the Gly460Trp polymorphism of <italic>ADD-1</italic> is not associated with hypertension.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Hypertension</kwd><kwd>Adducin</kwd><kwd>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Essential hypertension is currently seen as a multifactorial disease caused by multiple susceptibility genes, which are modulated by various environmental factors. Alpha-adducin (ADD-1) is a ubiquitously expressed cytoskeletal protein that appears to be involved in cell-to-cell contact (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>), cell membrane ion transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>), and signal transduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Abnormalities of membrane sodium transport in the kidney play an important role in hypertension. Cusi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>) reported that the Gly460Trp polymorphism of <italic>ADD-1</italic> was associated with a salt-sensitive form of hypertension. However, subsequent study results have been inconsistent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). There is little information on its relation to hypertension in the Korean population. Therefore, we examined whether the Gly460Trp polymorphism of <italic>ADD-1</italic> was associated with hypertension in a Korean population.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Subjects</title><p>The study subjects were 903 individuals who participated in a population-based study in Jangseong County, Korea, in August 2000. Informed consent for participation was obtained from all subjects. The participants completed a standard questionnaire on demographic characteristics, cigarette smoking, and alcohol consumption. Body mass index (BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup>) was calculated from height and weight measurements. Blood pressures were measured using a common protocol with a Dinamap automated blood pressure reading device (Johnson &#x00026; Johnson, New Jersey, U.S.A.). Two separate readings were taken. Our analysis is based on the average systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP). Hypertension was considered present if the average of two blood pressure measurements exceeded 140 mmHg systolic or 90 mmHg diastolic, or if the subjects were currently on antihypertensive medication.</p></sec><sec><title>Genotyping</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted from peripheral blood using an AccuPrep Genomic DNA Extraction Kit (Bioneer, Seoul, Korea) according to the manufacturer's protocol. The Gly460-Trp polymorphism of <italic>ADD-1</italic> was detected using a mutagenically separated polymerase chain reaction (PCR) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). Briefly, two allele-specific primers of different lengths (FP-614G: 5' GGGGCGACGAAGCTTCCGAGGTAG-3' and FP-614T: 5' GCTGAACTCTGGCCCAGGCGACGAAGCTTCCGAGGATT-3') and a nonselective complementary strand primer (RP-614, 5' CCTCCGAAGCCCCAGCTACCCA-3') were used in a single-tube reaction assay. We confirmed the validity of the method for several samples using direct DNA sequencing. Five microliters of product was loaded per well onto a 10% polyacrylamide gel (19:1) using a microtiter array diagonal gel electrophoresis system (MADGE, MadgeBio, Grantham &#x00026; Southampton, U.K.) and electrophoresed at 100 V for 100 min in 1&#x000d7;Tris-borate-EDTA (TBE). The MADGE system uses a horizontal polyacrylamide gel to separate the MS-PCR product in a 96-well format (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). The PCR products were 220 and 234 bp for the 460Gly and 460Trp alleles, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The between-group demographic and blood pressure data were compared using Student's unpaired t-test for continuous data and the &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test for categorical data. Allele frequencies were estimated by gene counting. Agreement between the genotype frequencies and Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium expectations was tested using the &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test. To adjust for the contribution of confounding factors, we performed a multiple logistic regression. Statistical analysis was performed using Stata 8.0 (Stata Corp., College Station, Texas, U.S.A.).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>The genotype distribution did not deviate significantly from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium expectations (Gly/Gly, 16.3%; Gly/Trp, 47.6%; Trp/Trp, 36.1%; <italic>p</italic>=0.79). <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> presents the baseline characteristics of all the subjects. Age, weight, height, body mass index, SBP, and DBP differed significantly between the hypertensive and normotensive groups. Sex, smoking habit, alcohol intake, and history of diabetes mellitus did not differ between the two groups. The frequency of the 460Trp allele was 59.4% in normotensives and 61.1% in hypertensives (<italic>p</italic>=0.523). The genotype frequency did not differ significantly between the hypertensive and normotensive subjects (<italic>p</italic>=0.928). After adjusting for age, sex, body mass index, smoking, alcohol intake, and history of diabetes mellitus, the odds ratio for hypertension associated with the presence of the Gly/Trp and Trp/Trp genotypes compared with the Gly/Gly were 1.00 (0.65-1.53) and 1.22 (0.79-1.90), respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this cross-sectional study, we investigated the association between an alpha-adducin gene polymorphism and essential hypertension in a Korean population. We found that the Gly460Trp polymorphism of <italic>ADD-1</italic> is not associated with essential hypertension. To our knowledge, this is the first report examining the relationship between <italic>ADD-1</italic> Gly460Trp gene polymorphism and hypertension in a sample from a general Korean population.</p><p>The frequency of the 460Trp allele varies in different populations. In this study, the frequency of the 460Trp allele was 59.4% in normotensives and 61.1% in hypertensives. These frequencies are very similar to those in Japanese (52-66%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>) and Chinese (42-56%) populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). However, the frequency of the 460Trp allele is low in white populations (18% in Italy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>), 20% in France (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>), and 27% in Scotland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>)) and very low (6%) in black South Africans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). It is generally accepted that the frequency of a given variant allele in a population is determined by the biological fitness it confers in the presence of a given environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). To achieve the functional characteristics needed to cope with an adverse environment, populations pick up the appropriate allele from the available genetic pool (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we could not detect any association between the Gly460Trp gene polymorphism and blood pressure. Cusi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>) suggested that alpha-adducin was associated with a salt-sensitive form of hypertension. Subsequent studies have reported inconsistent results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). There are a number of possible explanations for this inconsistency. The major consideration may be ethnic differences. In Asian studies, positive associations between the Gly460Trp gene polymorphism of <italic>ADD-1</italic> and blood pressure were found in three (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>) of five studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>) conducted in Japanese populations and in two (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>) of four (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) in Chinese populations.</p><p>The mechanism by which ADD-1 increases blood pressure is not known. ADD-1 is thought to regulate ion transport via changes in the actin cytoskeleton (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Adducin is thought to stimulate Na<sup>+</sup>-K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase, promoting sodium re-absorption by renal tubular cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). Trp/Trp individuals with this alteration in renal sodium handling will have increased sensitivity of blood pressure to sodium intake and are at increased risk for developing low-renin hypertension (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p><p>In summary, we failed to reveal a significant association between the Gly460Trp gene polymorphism of <italic>ADD-1</italic> and hypertension in a Korean population.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p>This study was supported financially by Chonnam National University in the program, 2000.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Keefe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adducin: Ca++-dependent association with sites of cell-cell contact</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1989</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2503523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tripodi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Valtorta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Torielli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chieregatti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Salardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Trusolino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Menegon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchisio</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hypertension-associated point mutations in the adducin alpha and beta subunits affect actin cytoskeleton and ion transport</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>1996</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>2815</fpage><lpage>2822</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8675693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mische</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooseker</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Erythrocyte adducin: a calmodulin-regulated actin-bundling protein that stimulates spectrinactin binding</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1987</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>2837</fpage><lpage>2845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3693401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cusi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlassina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Azzani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Casari</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Citterio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Devoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Glorioso</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanzani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Manunta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Righetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stella</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Troffa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zagato</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymorphisms of alpha-adducin and salt sensitivity in patients with essential hypertension</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1997</year><volume>349</volume><fpage>1353</fpage><lpage>1357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9149697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cusi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association and linkage analysis of alpha-adducin polymorphism: is the glass half full or half empty?</article-title><source>Am J Hypertens</source><year>2000</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10912763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rust</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Funke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Assmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutagenically separated PCR (MS-PCR): a highly specific one step procedure for easy mutation detection</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1993</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>3623</fpage><lpage>3629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8367277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nabika</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yazaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lack of association between the alpha-adducin locus and essential hypertension in the Japanese population</article-title><source>Hypertension</source><year>1998</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>730</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9495254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Burley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beilby</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A high-throughput MS-PCR method on MADGE gels for ANG II type-1 receptor A1166C polymorphism</article-title><source>Physiol Genomics</source><year>1999</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11015563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsuya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takiuchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Higaki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogihara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>No association between alpha-adducin 460 polymorphism and essential hypertension in a Japanese population</article-title><source>Am J Hypertens</source><year>1998</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>502</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9607391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymorphism of alpha-adducin and hypertension</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1997</year><volume>350</volume><fpage>369</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9251667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hozawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsuya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohkubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Motone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Higaki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hisamachi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogihara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alpha-adducin Gly460Trp polymorphism is associated with low renin hypertension in younger subjects in the Ohasama study</article-title><source>J Hypertens</source><year>2002</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1779</fpage><lpage>1784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12195119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranade</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsuing</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name><name><surname>Olshen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Curb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzau</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Risch</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lack of evidence for an association between alpha-adducin and blood pressure regulation in Asian populations</article-title><source>Am J Hypertens</source><year>2000</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>704</fpage><lpage>709</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10912757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alpha-adducin gene polymorphism is associated with essential hypertension in Chinese: a case-control and family-based study</article-title><source>J Hypertens</source><year>2003</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1861</fpage><lpage>1868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14508192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamitani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Foy</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrap</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human alpha-adducin gene, blood pressure, and sodium metabolism</article-title><source>Hypertension</source><year>1998</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9674650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barlassina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Samani</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodwiss</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Candy</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Radevski</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Citterio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cusi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alpha-adducin polymorphism in hypertensives of South African ancestry</article-title><source>Am J Hypertens</source><year>2000</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10912759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsujita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymorphism of alpha-adducin in Japanese patients with essential hypertension</article-title><source>Hypertens Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9582105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>QN</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alpha-Adducin gene and essential hypertension in China</article-title><source>Clin Exp Hypertens</source><year>2001</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11710759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Is Gly460Trp variant of alpha-adducin associated with essential hypertension in the Hans of Chinese population]</article-title><source>Zhonghua Yi Xue Yi Chuan Xue Za Zhi</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11110979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adducin: a physical model with implications for function in assembly of spectrin-actin complexes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>18990</fpage><lpage>18996</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7642559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manunta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlassina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adducin in essential hypertension</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1998</year><volume>430</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9678591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeunemaitre</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollenberg</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-renin hypertension, altered sodium homeostasis, and an alpha-adducin polymorphism</article-title><source>Hypertension</source><year>2002</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11847182</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of normotensive and hypertensive groups</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-19-812-i001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values shown are the mean&#x000b1;SD. BMI, body mass index; SBP, systolic blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; DM, diabetes mellitus.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Association between alpha-adducin Gly460Trp polymorphism and hypertension</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-19-812-i002"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>*</sup>Adjusted by age, sex, body mass index, alcohol intake, smoking, and history of diabetes mellitus.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>
