<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7917927</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2033402</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Double modulation of 5-fluorouracil with interferon alpha 2a and high-dose leucovorin: a phase I and II study.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wrigley</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Slevin</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>ICRF Department of Medical Oncology, St Bartholomew's Hospital, London, UK.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>1994</year></pub-date><volume>70</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><abstract><p>Twenty-nine patients with adenocarcinomas of gastrointestinal or unknown primary, and three with advanced neuroendocrine tumours, were entered into a study of bolus plus infusional 5-fluorouracil (FUra) modulated with high-dose leucovorin (LV) and recombinant interferon alpha 2a (IFN-alpha). Successive cohorts of &#x0003e; or = 4 patients received IFN-alpha at 1.5, 3, 4.5, 6 and 9 MU on alternate days throughout the treatment period. The FUra/LV regimen consisted of: LV 200 mg m-2 i.v. infusion over 2 h, FUra 400 mg m-2 i.v. bolus then FUra 400 mg m-2 i.v. infusion over 22 h, all repeated on day 2, on a 14-day cycle. FUra was given at 75% dose for the first course, increasing (in the absence of WHO grade &#x0003e; or = 2 toxicity) to 87.5% for the second and 100% for subsequent courses up to a maximum of 12. The maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of IFN-alpha was 6 MU on alternate days, with 7/8 patients at 9 MU requiring dose reductions. At 6 MU IFN-alpha, the MTD of FUra was not exceeded at 100% (i.e. 400 mg m-2 bolus and infusion, days 1 and 2), and FUra-related toxicities (mucosal, haematological, dermatological) were extremely mild. Twenty-nine patients were assessable for tumour response, among whom WHO criteria partial responses were seen in 7/14 with colorectal, 1/4 with gastric, 0/1 with pancreatic, 1/3 with neuroendocrine and 3/6 with unknown primaries. Median response duration was 51 weeks. Minor responses and stable disease were seen in a further six patients. Median survival of patients with advanced adenocarcinomas was 9 months, with 33% surviving beyond 18 months. This schedule offers a safe way of co-administering FUra, LV and IFN-alpha. The addition of IFN-alpha, while causing significant independent toxicity, does not significantly increase the dose-limiting mucosal toxicities of FUra/LV. Further investigation is required to determine the contribution of IFN-alpha to the anti-tumour activity of the combination.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0149.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="719" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0150.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="720" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0151.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="721" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0152.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="722" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0153.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="723" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

