<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7917928</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2033410</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Lack of effect of interferon alpha 2a upon fluorouracil pharmacokinetics.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Joel</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Slevin</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Medical Oncology, St Bartholomew's Hospital, London, UK.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>1994</year></pub-date><volume>70</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>724</fpage><lpage>728</lpage><abstract><p>The disposition of 5-fluorouracil (FUra) was studied in 19 colorectal cancer patients during treatment with FUra and high-dose leucovorin (LV) with or without interferon alpha 2a (IFN-alpha). All received LV 200 mg m-2 over 2 h, then FUra 400 mg m-2 over 5 min then FUra 400 mg m-2 over 22 h, repeated on day 2, on a 14 day cycle. Nine patients also received IFN-alpha 6 MU every 48 h, starting at least 2 weeks before the study. Series of 14 blood samples were assayed for FUra by reversed-phase high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC). Minimum Akaike information criterion estimation was used to determine the simplest effective pharmacokinetic model. This consisted of a single compartment with first-order (linear) and Michaelis-Menten (non-linear) components to drug elimination. This model gave r2 &#x0003e; 0.98 in 19/20 data sets. With the Michaelis constant (KM) set at 15 microM, values were derived for the volume of distribution (Vd), the maximum rate of non-linear elimination (Vmax) and the first-order elimination rate constant (K1.e). Mean (+/- s.d.) values in control (no IFN-alpha) patients were: Vd 10.4 (+/- 1.9) l m-2, Vmax 182 (+/- 59) mumol l-1 h-1 and k1.e 4.35 (+/- 0.58) h-1. No significant differences were detected in patients receiving IFN-alpha, in whom the equivalent mean values were Vd 10.0 (+/- 0.9) l m-2, Vmax 141 (+/- 27) mumol l-1 h-1 and k1.e 3.96 (+/- 0.5) h-1. Mean trapezoidal AUC0-22 h was similar in the two groups (control patients 116 microM h, IFN-alpha patients 125 microM h). No significant correlations with renal or hepatic function were detected. These results, while not inconsistent with previous reports of a reduced rate of FUra elimination at higher IFN-alpha doses, suggest that any clinical effect of this moderate dose of IFN-alpha on FUra toxicity or activity is due to modulation at target cells, not to pharmacokinetic interaction.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0154.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="724" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0155.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="725" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0156.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="726" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0157.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="727" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00056-0158.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="728" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

