<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">369589</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2009823</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Size of cancer clinical trials and stopping rules.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>1978</year></pub-date><volume>38</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>766</lpage><abstract><p>A recent international survey on the size of clinical trials in cancer showed the frequent problem of slow patient accrual, which remains a major hindrance to progress. The survey also revealed that, although the design of most trials specified a fixed number of patients, subsequent experience revealed a much more flexible approach, with analysis of results, say, every 4--6 months. Conventional sequential methods are hardly ever used and unfortunately most trials proceed without any predetermined stopping rules. Some trial organizers use repeated significance tests on accumulating data as a guide to the detection of treatment differences, an approach that can be adapted to a more rigorous statistical framework as a "group sequential design". The major statistical principle involved is that the more often one analyses the data the greater is the probability of achieving a statistically significant result, even when the two treatments are equally effective. Group sequential designs require the adoption of a more stringent significance level to allow for repeated testing. If one intends up to 10 repeated analyses of the data, only a treatment difference significant at the 1% level would merit a decision to stop the trial. For any trial to implement a stopping rule successfully there must also be prompt feedback and processing of response and survival data ready for up-to-date analysis. Such efficiency is often lacking. The repeated presentation of interim results of a trial to participating investigators can seriously affect their future reaction, especially if there are interesting but non-significant differences. Thus, some secrecy about ongoing results is advisable if trials are to achieve an unbiased conclusion.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00158-0106.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="757" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00158-0107.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="758" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00158-0108.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="759" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00158-0109.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="760" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00158-0110.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="761" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00158-0111.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="762" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00158-0112.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="763" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00158-0113.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="764" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00158-0114.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="765" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="brjcancer00158-0115.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="766" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

