<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ViewNLM-v2.3.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Yonsei Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">YMJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Yonsei Medical Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0513-5796</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1976-2437</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Yonsei University College of Medicine</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15988805</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2815810</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3349/ymj.2005.46.3.347</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effectiveness of Real-Time Quantitative PCR Compare to Repeat PCR for the Diagnosis of Charcot-Marie-Tooth Type 1A and Hereditary Neuropathy with Liability to Pressure Palsies</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Jong Rak</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Woon Hyoung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sunwoo</surname><given-names>Il Nam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Eun Kyung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Chang Hoon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Jong-Baeck</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Neurology, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Konkuk University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Reprint address: requests to Dr. Jong-Baeck Lim, Departments of Laboratory Medicine, Yonsei University College of Medicine, 134 Shinchon-dong, Seodaemoon-gu, Seoul 120-752, Korea. Tel: 82-2-361-5865, Fax: 82-2-313-0956, <email>jlim@yumc.yonsei.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>352</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 The Yonsei University College of Medicine</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The majority of cases of Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 1A (CMT1A) and of hereditary neuropathy with a liability to pressure palsies (HNPP) are the result of heterozygosity for the duplication or deletion of peripheral myelin protein 22 gene (PMP22) on 17p11.2. Southern blots, pulsed-field gel electrophoresis (PFGE), fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) and polymorphic marker analysis are currently used diagnostic methods. But they are time-consuming, labor-intensive and have some significant limitations. We describe a rapid realtime quantitative PCR method for determining gene copy number for the identification of DNA duplication or deletion occurring in CMT1A or HNPP and compare the results obtained with REP-PCR. Six patients with CMT1A and 14 patients with HNPP [confirmed by Repeat (REP)-PCR], and 16 patients with suspicious CMT1A and 13 patients with suspicious HNPP [negative REP-PCR], and 15 normal controls were studied. We performed REP-PCR, which amplified a 3.6 Kb region (including a 1.7 Kb recombination hotspot), using specific CMT1A-REP and real-time quantitative PCR on the LightCycler system. Using a comparative threshold cycle (Ct) method and &#x003b2;-globin as a reference gene, the gene copy number of the PMP22 gene was quantified. The PMP22 duplication ratio ranged from 1.35 to 1.74, and the PMP22 deletion ratio from 0.41 to 0.53. The PMP22 ratio in normal controls ranged from 0.81 to 1.12. All 6 patients with CMT1A and 14 patients with HNPP confirmed by REP-PCR were positive by real-time quantitative PCR. Among the 16 suspicious CMT1A and 13 suspicious HNPP with negative REP-PCR, 2 and 4 samples, respectively, were positive by real-time quantitative PCR. Real-time quantitative PCR is a more sensitive and more accurate method than REP-PCR for the detection of PMP22 duplications or deletions, and it is also faster and easier than currently available methods. Therefore, we believe that the real-time quantitative method is useful for diagnosing CMT1A and HNPP.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 1A</kwd><kwd>HNPP</kwd><kwd>peripheral myelin protein 22 gene</kwd><kwd>real-time quantitative PCR</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The majority of Charcot-Marie-Tooth 1(CMT1) patients possess DNA rearrangements, which are the molecular causes of their disease. A 1.5-Mb tandem duplication, the CMT1A duplication, accounts for approximately 70 percent of CMT1 cases, and a deletion of the same 1.5-Mb region in chromosome 17p11.2 is found in &#x0003e;85 percent of patients with HNPP. The CMT1A duplication and HNPP deletion result from unequal crossing-over and reciprocal homologous recombination involving a 24-Kb repeat-CMT1A-REP-which flanks the 1.5-Mb region. A meiotic recombination hotspot occurs within CMT1A-REP. The majority of the <italic>de novo</italic> duplication and deletion events occur during male germ cell meiosis. The CMT1A and HNPP phenotypes result from a gene dosage effect. CMT1A is due to trisomic overexpression of the peripheral myelin protein-22 gene (PMP22) whereas HNPP results from the monosomic underexpression of PMP22. Moreover, in rare cases PMP22 point mutations can cause disease in patients without the CMT1A duplication or the HNPP deletion.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></p><p>In molecular genetic testing for the CMT1A duplication and the HNPP deletion, several approaches are available. Molecular diagnosis by hybridization-based methods include; Southern blotting,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref> quantitative photostimulated luminescence (PSL) imaging,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref> and pulse-field gel electrophoresis (PFGE).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref> Less frequently used methods include fluorescence-in situ hybridization (FISH),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref> polymorphic markers,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref> repeat (REP-) PCR,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref> and endpoint quantitative PCR.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref> But, these methods have several disadvantages for the diagnosis of CMT1A and HNPP.</p><p>In this study, we describe a rapid real-time quantitative PCR devised to assess gene copy number for the identification of DNA duplication or deletion occurring in CMT1A or HNPP, and we compare the results obtained with REP-PCR.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Subjects and DNA extraction</title><p>Six patients with CMT1A and 14 patients with HNPP (confirmed by REP-PCR), 16 suspicious CMT1A and 13 suspicious HNPP patients with negative REP-PCR, and 15 normal controls were studied. Genomic DNA was extracted from EDTA-treated blood using the MagNa Pure LC DNA isolation kit and instrument (Roche), according to the manufacturer's instructions. DNA analysis was carried out with 'informed consent'.</p></sec><sec><title>REP-PCR</title><p>REP-PCR was performed as denscribed by Stronach et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref> The method amplifies a 3.6 Kb region, including the recombination 1.7 Kb hotspot, from specific CMT1A-REP. A schematic of the method is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Real-time quantitative PCR</title><p>Primers and probes used for real-time quantitative PCR were designed using LightCycler Probe Design Software version 1.0 (Roche). The amplified fragment (202 bp), including exon 5 of the PMP22 gene, was obtained using forward primer 5'-ACC CAG TGC ATC CAA C-3' and reverse primer 5'-ATC CAT AGC ACC ATT TCA AAG-3'. The sequence of the sensor probe was 5'-CGG CTT GTG GCA TTG GCA-Fluorescein-3', and the sequence of the anchor probe 5'-LCRed 640-CTT GCC CTT ACA GGT GGA GTA TCT-3'. The primers and probes of the &#x003b2;-globin gene in LightCycler Control DNA kit (Roche) were used as reference. Amplification was carried out using the LightCycler FastStart DNA Master Hybridization Probe kit (Roche) in a standard PCR containing; 0.5&#x000b5;mol/L of each primer and 0.2&#x000b5;mol/L of each probe in a 20&#x000b5;L final volume containing 2&#x000b5;L of sample. The cycling program consisted of an initial denaturation at 95&#x02103; for 10 min, and 45 cycles of 95&#x02103; for 10 sec, 58&#x02103; for 10 sec, and 72&#x02103; for 9 sec. Amplifications of PMP22 and &#x003b2;-globin were performed simultaneously in each capillary tube. Each test was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec><title>Calculating the gene copy number</title><p>Using a comparative threshold cycle (Ct) method, as previously described by Livak,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref> and &#x003b2;-globin as a reference gene, the gene copy number by PMP22 gene duplication or deletion was quantified and calculated.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>The amplification curves for PMP22 and the &#x003b2;-globin gene are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>. The Ct values of PMP22 and of the &#x003b2;-globin gene were almost the same in the normal sample, whereas the Ct values of PMP22 in CMT1A and HNPP were decreased or increased, respectively, versus that of &#x003b2;-globin in the amplification curve. The PMP22 duplication ratio in two CMT1A patients, confirmed by REP-PCR, ranged from 1.35 to 1.74, the PMP22 deletion ratio in 14 patients with HNPP, as confirmed by REP-PCR, ranged from 0.41 to 0.53 and the PMP22 ratio in the controls ranged from 0.81 to 1.12 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The standard deviations of Ct were 0.22, 0.18 and 0.24 in CMT1A, HNPP and controls, respectively. Six patients with CMT1A and the 14 patients with HNPP, as confirmed by REP-PCR, were positive by real-time quantitative PCR. Among the 16 suspicious CMT1A and 13 suspicious HNPP patients, with a negative REP-PCR, 2 and 4 samples, respectively, were positive by realtime quantitative PCR. Therefore, the real-time quantitative PCR method can be more detected 50% (2/4) of the CMT1A patients and 22.2% (4/18) of the HNPP patients with cross-over in CMT1A-REP. The measured copy numbers of the 15 normal controls, and in the 2 CMT1A and 14 HNPP patients are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>. No overlap of copy number was found between CMT1A or HNPP patients and the controls.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>At least nine loci for CMT1 and four for CMT2 have been identified by genetic linkage studies. Six of the genes associated with CMT1, and recently one gene for CMT2, has been identified. Although at least eight loci are associated with the aCMT1 phenotype, 70 to 90% of patients possess the causative CMT1A duplication. Deletion of the same genomic segment that is duplicated in CMT1A leads to a clinically distinct neuropathy-HNPP.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> Recombination events occur within the 1.7 Kb hotspot located between an <italic>EcoR</italic>I site, unique to the proximal CMT1A-REP, and a <italic>Nsi</italic>I site, unique to distal CMT1A-REP. It has been reported that the recombination rate in hotspot region ranges from 75 to 87% in a population-dependent manner.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> In the present study, the recombination rate in the hotspot region was about 73% (16/22), which is similar to that obtained in other populations.</p><p>Several methods for detecting the CMT1A duplication and the HNPP deletion are available currently. Recently, the real-time quantitative PCR method has been used to detect haploidy and triploidy in genetic diseases and cancer.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref> Detection of the PMP22 duplication and deletion by real-time quantitative PCR using TaqMan probes has been know as a fast method allowing to be diagnosed in 2 hr. However, specific probes are requiredin real-time quantitative PCR using TaqMan probes.</p><p>In the present study, this method also can be more found 27% (6/22) of duplication and deletion and is more sensitive than REP-PCR. However, many more samples should be tested for CMT1A duplication ratio. For mutation studies in the PMP22 gene, P0 gene (CMT1B), connexin32 gene (CMT1X),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref> or another subtype of CMT is needed in samples without duplication or deletion.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref> One case of CMT1A patient with 1.87 of gene copy number was presumed homozygote duplication, but it should be confirmed by other reference method e.g. FISH.</p><p>The reaction efficiencies varied in the different experiments, thus it may not be possible to obtain similar efficiencies for both control and target markers. This limitation also affects highly accurate systems such as the LightCycler instrument. But the gene dosage test in the method described is feasible and more accurate. In this study, the mean CV of the Ct value of the PMP22 and &#x003b2;-globin genes was &#x0003c; 2.0% in between run. Therefore, it appears that results of real-time quantitative PCR were accurate and reproducible.</p><p>In conclusion, real-time quantitative PCR is both more sensitive and more accurate than REP-PCR in terms of the detection of PMP22 duplications or deletions. It is also faster and easier than other currently available methods and clearly differentiates gene dose. Therefore, real-time quantitative PCR method may be useful for diagnosing CMT1A and HNPP, and may be applied to the diagnosis of any disease caused by gene dosage changes.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lupski</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Scriver</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaudet</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sly</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charcot-Marie-Tooth peripheral neuropathies and related disorders</article-title><source>The metabolic &#x00026; molecular bases of inherited disease</source><year>2001</year><edition>8th ed</edition><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name><fpage>5759</fpage><lpage>5788</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lupski</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>de Oca-Luna</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Slaugenhaupt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pentao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzzetta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Trask</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNA duplication associated with Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 1A</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1991</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1677316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacMillan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Upadhyaya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 1a (CMT1a): evidence for trisomy of the region p11.2 of chromosome 17 in south Wales families</article-title><source>J Med Genet</source><year>1992</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1552536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raeymaekers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmerman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jonghe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoogendijk</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Baas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The HMSN Collaborative Research Group: Duplication in chromosome 17p11.2 in Charcot-Marie-Tooth neuropathy type 1a (CMT 1a)</article-title><source>Neuromuscul Disord</source><year>1991</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1822787</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raeymaekers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmerman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>van Hul</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jonghe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><collab>HMSN Collaborative Research Group</collab><article-title>Estimation of the size of the chromosome 17p11.2 duplication in Charcot-Marie-Tooth neuropathy type 1a (CMT1a)</article-title><source>J Med Genet</source><year>1992</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1552545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rennert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochan</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Normalized Southern hybridization to enhance testing for Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease, type 1A</article-title><source>Mol Diagn</source><year>1996</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10330199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoogendijk</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hensels</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabreels-Festen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabreels</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jonghe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>De novo mutation in hereditary motor and sensory neuropathy type I</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1992</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>1081</fpage><lpage>1082</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1349106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoogendijk</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabreels-Festen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hensels</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Joosten</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabreels</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Allelic heterogeneity in hereditary motor and sensory neuropathy type Ia (Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 1A)</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>1993</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1010</fpage><lpage>1015</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8492918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikegami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chance</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyosawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobue</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Facilitated diagnosis of CMT1A duplication in chromosome 17p11.2-12: analysis with a CMT1A-REP repeat probe and photostimulated luminescence imaging</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><year>1997</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9195231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chance</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lensch</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pentao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Roa</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Two autosomal dominant neuropathies result from reciprocal DNA duplication/deletion of a region on chromosome 17</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>1994</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8004087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pentao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinault</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupski</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 1A duplication appears to arise from recombination at repeat sequences flanking the 1.5-Mb monomer unit</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1992</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>292</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1303282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timmerman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofgren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>le Guern</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jonghe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular genetic analysis of the17p11.2 region in patients with hereditary neuropathy with liability to pressure palsies (HNPP)</article-title><source>Hum Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8557256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roa</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunaratne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubinsky</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Duplication of the PMP 22 gene in 17p partial trisomy patients with Charcot-Marie-Tooth type-1 neuropathy</article-title><source>Hum Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>642</fpage><lpage>649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8655146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Spikes</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupski</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis of CMT1A duplications and HNPP deletions by interphase FISH: implications for testing in the cytogenetics laboratory</article-title><source>Am J Med Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9096765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmerman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofgren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeitune</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prenatal diagnosis of Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 1A (CMT1A) using molecular genetic techniques</article-title><source>Prenat Diagn</source><year>1995</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8532623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haupt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schols</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Przuntek</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Epplen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymorphisms in the PMP-22 gene region (17p11.2-12) are crucial for simplified diagnosis of duplications/deletions</article-title><source>Hum Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>688</fpage><lpage>691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9150743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stronach</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofgren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmerman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel PCR-based diagnostic tools for Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 1A and hereditary neuropathy with liability to pressure palsies</article-title><source>J Peripher Nerv Syst</source><year>1999</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10442687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayasaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clustering of CMT1A duplication breakpoints in a 700-bp interval of the CMT1A-REP repeat</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><year>1998</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9482573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poropat</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of gene dosage at the PMP22 and androgen receptor loci by quantitative PCR (comments)</article-title><source>Clin Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>724</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9554482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stogbauer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiebusch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofgren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmerman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>van Broeckhoven</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PCR-based strategy for the diagnosis of hereditary neuropathy with liability to pressure palsies and Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 1A</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>1998</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>760</fpage><lpage>763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9521270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Comparative Ct method. ABI Prism 7700 Sequence Detection System. User Bulletin No. 2</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>PE Applied Bio-systems</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekici</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rautenstrauss</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new quantitative PCR multiplex assay for rapid analysis of chromosome 17p11.2-12 duplications and deletions leading to HMSN/HNPP</article-title><source>Eur J Hum Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12634865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorentzos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennerson</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapid and definitive test for Charcot-Marie-Tooth 1A and hereditary neuropathy with liability to pressure palsies using multiplexed real-time PCR</article-title><source>Genet Test</source><year>2003</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12885335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rapid Detection of duplication/deletion of the PMP 22 gene in patients with Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 1A and hereditary neuropathy with liability to pressure palsy by real-time quantitative PCR using SYBR Green I Dye</article-title><source>J Korean Med Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14555828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of HER2/neu status by real-time quantitative PCR in breast cancer</article-title><source>Yonsei Med J</source><year>2002</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12089741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Haites</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Broeckhoven</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in the peripheral myelin genes and associated genes in inherited peripheral neuropathies</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9888385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Visser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Broeckhoven</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>Hereditary motor and sensory neuropathy or Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 1A and 1B</source><year>1997</year><edition>2nd ed</edition><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Royal Soc Med, London/Eur Neuromuscular Centre, Royal Society of Medicine Press</publisher-name><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Schematic method of REP-PCR. The junctional CMT1A-REPs shown exhibit crossing-over within the 3.2 Kb region.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ymj-46-347-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Amplification curves of PMP22 and of the &#x003b2;-globin gene in HNPP (A), normal (B) and CMT1A (C) subjects. In normal sample, the Ct values of PMP22 and of the &#x003b2;-globin gene were almost the same (middle), whereas the Ct values of PMP22 in HNPP and CMT1A were increased (upper) or decreased (lower), respectively, versus that of &#x003b2;-globin in the amplification curve.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ymj-46-347-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Measured copy numbers of the PMP22 gene per haploid genome in 15 normal controls (&#x025a0;), 6 CMT1A (&#x025b2;) and 14 HNPP (&#x025c6;). No overlap of gene copy number between each groups.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ymj-46-347-g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Peripheral Myelin Protein 22 (PMP22) Duplication and Deletion Ratios Detected by Real Time Quantitative PCR in CMT1A and HNPP and in Normal Controls, Confirmed by REP PCR</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ymj-46-347-i001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>*</sup>Standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>
