<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><!-- Original-type: cl--><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15054451</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2409683</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6601711</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjc.6601711</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A phase I trial of cytotoxic T-lymphocyte precursor-oriented peptide vaccines for colorectal carcinoma patients</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shomura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sasatomi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Une</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamana</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Todo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><sup>1</sup>First Department of Surgery, Hokkaido University School of Medicine, Sapporo, Japan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><sup>2</sup>Department of Immunology, Kurume University School of Medicine, Fukuoka, Japan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><sup>3</sup>Department of Surgery, Kurume University School of Medicine, Fukuoka, Japan</aff><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>Author for correspondence: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:yuchan@med.hokudai.ac.jp">yuchan@med.hokudai.ac.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>03</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>30</day><month>03</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>05</day><month>04</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>90</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1334</fpage><lpage>1342</lpage><history><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>01</month><year>2004</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright 2004, Cancer Research UK</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><permissions><copyright-holder>Cancer Research UK</copyright-holder></permissions><kwd-group><kwd>peptide</kwd><kwd>cancer vaccine</kwd><kwd>immunotherapy</kwd><kwd>colon cancer</kwd><kwd>CTL</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Recent advances in molecular biology and cellular immunology have resulted in identification of various antigens and epitopes recognised by human histocompatibility leukocyte antigen (HLA)-class-I-restricted cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTLs) from various cancers (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib2">Bruggen <italic>et al</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib1">Brichard <italic>et al</italic>, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib16">Kawakami <italic>et al</italic>, 1994a</xref>, <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib15">1994b</xref> <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib7">Fisk <italic>et al</italic>, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib31">Peoples <italic>et al</italic>, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib33">Robbins <italic>et al</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib4">Correale <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib5">Correale <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>). Many clinical trials of peptide-based immunotherapy have shown an increased immune response to the vaccinated peptides (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib34">Rosenberg <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib22">Marchand <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib14">Jager <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib8">Gajewski <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib9">Gjertsen <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib20">Lau <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib41">Valmori <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). However, these initial clinical studies have produced few clinical responses in the various types of cancer treated including melanoma and colorectal cancer (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib6">Finn and Lotze, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib24">Miyagi <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib35">Sadanaga <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). This failure could be in part due to the insufficient and late stages of CTL induction by the current regimen, in which pre-vaccination screening of suitable peptides for each patient among a large number of candidate peptides is not conducted. As a result, vaccination in the present study began with immune priming. This standard regimen could be effective in preventing infectious disease. However, the main goal of a cancer vaccine is treatment of malignant disease. The time-lag necessary for priming of an antitumour response should be seriously considered, as the expected survival of most advanced cancer patients under these regimens is 3&#x02013;9 months (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib3">Cole and Rodu, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib24">Miyagi <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). Therefore, the development of a new regimen of therapeutic vaccine is needed (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib6">Finn and Lotze, 2001</xref>). One regimen might include pre-vaccination measurement of peptide-specific CTL precursors in the circulation, followed by vaccination of only CTL-reactive peptides (CTL precursor-oriented vaccine). We have previously reported 14 vaccine candidate peptides that can induce HLA-A24-restriced and tumour-specific CTL in cancer patients (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib10">Gomi <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib18">Kikuchi <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib43">Yang <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib12">Harashima <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib17">Kawano <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">Nakao <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib27">Nishizaka <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>). We have also shown that most cancer patients have peptide-specific CTL precursors for some of these peptides, and that peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) stimulated with positive peptides show HLA-class-I-restricted and tumour-specific cytotoxicity (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib13">Hida <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib21">Maeda <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib39">Suzuki <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>). In the present study, patients with advanced stages of colorectal cancer were immunised with up to four peptides identified in pre-vaccination measurement of peptide-specific CTL precursors to evaluate the toxicities and responses to CTL precursor-oriented peptide vaccination.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Patients and eligibility criteria</title><p>The study protocol was approved by the Institutional Ethical Review Boards of Hokkaido University and Kurume University, respectively. Complete written informed consent was obtained from all of patients at the time of enrolment. According to the protocol, patients were required to be HLA-A24 positive, and to have a histologically confirmed lesion of colorectal carcinoma. Eligibility criteria included an age of 85 years or less, serum creatinine of less than 1.4&#x02009;mg&#x02009;dl<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, bilirubin of less than 1.5&#x02009;mg&#x02009;dl<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, a platelet count of 100&#x02009;000&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> or more, haemoglobin of 8.0&#x02009;g&#x02009;dl<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> or more, and total WBC of 3000&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> or more. Hepatitis B surface antigen, Hepatitis C antigen, and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) were required to be negative. The patients, who had been untreated for at least 4 weeks before the study, had an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status of 0&#x02013;2. The treatment was carried out at the First Department of Surgery, Hokkaido University School of Medicine (patients 1&#x02013;9) and the Department of Surgery, Kurume University School of Medicine (patient 10) from November 2000 through April 2002. All immunological analyses were carried out at the Department of Immunology, Kurume University School of Medicine.</p></sec><sec><title>Screening of peptide-specific CTL precursors</title><p>A volume of 30&#x02009;ml of peripheral blood was obtained pre- and post- (3rd, 6th, and 9th) vaccination, and PBMCs were isolated by means of Ficoll&#x02013;Conray density gradient centrifugation, as reported previously (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib24">Miyagi <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). A previously reported method was used to detect peptide-specific CTL precursors in PBMCs (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib13">Hida <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib39">Suzuki <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>). Briefly, PBMCs (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>&#x02009;cells&#x02009;well<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) were incubated with 10&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sc>M</sc> of a peptide in wells of u-bottom-type 96-well microculture plates (Nunc, Roskilde, Denmark) in 200&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l of culture medium. The culture medium consisted of 45&#x00025; RPMI-1640 medium, 45&#x00025; AIM-V&#x000ae; medium (GIBCO BRL), 10&#x00025; FCS, 100&#x02009;U&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of interleukin (IL)-2, and 0.1&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sc>M</sc> MEM nonessential amino-acid solution (GIBCO BRL). Every 3 days, half of the medium was removed and replaced with new medium containing a corresponding peptide (20&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sc>M</sc>). The assay was performed in quadruplicate. After a 12-day incubation, the cultured cells in one well were divided into four wells, two of which were used for corresponding peptide-pulsed C1R-A2402 cells, and the other two of which were used for HIV peptide (RYLRQQLLGI)-pulsed C1R-A2402 cells. The HLA-A24-binding HIV peptide was used as a negative control. After an 18-h incubation period, the supernatants were collected and the level of interferon (IFN)-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> was determined by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) (limit of sensitivity: 10&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The background response to HIV peptide-pulsed C1R-A2402 cells was subtracted from the value. Assessment of peptide-specific CTL precursors was performed based on two parameters, the <italic>P</italic>-value by the Student's <italic>t</italic>-test and IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production, as described in legends of <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Tables 2</xref> and <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. According to the results of this test, up to four positive peptides were selected for each patient, utilised in a skin test, and then, if negative, injected as a vaccination. The screening of peptide-specific CTL precursors was performed by the same method after the 6th vaccination to evaluate the effects of immunisation.</p></sec><sec><title>Peptides and vaccination</title><p>The peptides utilised in the present study were prepared under conditions of Good Manufacturing Practice using a Multiple Peptide System (San Diego, CA, USA). Montanide ISA-51, an incomplete adjuvant, was manufactured by Seppic, Inc (Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA). The peptides were supplied in vials containing 3&#x02009;mg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sterile solution for injection. A 3&#x02009;mg portion of peptide with sterile saline was added in a 1&#x02009;:&#x02009;1 volume to Montanide ISA-51, then mixed in a Vortex mixer (Fisher, Inc, Alameda, CA, USA). The resulting emulsion was injected subcutaneously into the lateral thigh using a glass syringe. Patients were vaccinated every 14 days for a total of three injections to measure the toxicity. For the patients with no toxicity, the vaccinations were repeated biweekly up to 15 times with informed consent from each patient.</p></sec><sec><title>Delayed-type hypersensitivity (DTH) skin test</title><p>Skin tests were performed using 50&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g of each peptide injected intradermally in a volume of 100&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l using a tuberculin syringe and a 27-gauge needle. Saline was a negative control for assessment of DTH. At least 7&#x02009;mm of induration or erythema read 48&#x02009;h after injection was needed to score the skin test as positive (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib26">Nestle <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Assay of cytotoxicity</title><p>Cytotoxic activity was measured using a standard 6-h <sup>51</sup>Cr-release assay (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib10">Gomi <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib24">Miyagi <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). Cryopreserved PBMCs were thawed and cultured in the medium consisting of 45&#x00025; RPMI-1640 medium, 45&#x00025; AIM-V&#x000ae; medium (GIBCO BRL), 10&#x00025; FCS, 100&#x02009;U&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of IL-2, and 0.1&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sc>M</sc> MEM nonessential amino-acid solution (GIBCO BRL). On the 14th day of culture, the cells were harvested and served for the assay. To avoid the bias of bioassays, PBMCs harvested at different times from a single patient were thawed at the same time. SW620 (HLA-A24<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>, colon adenocarcinoma), COLO201 (HLA-A24<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, colon adenocarcinoma), and PHA-blastoid T cells (HLA-A24<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>) were used as target cells (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;well<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), and 50-fold unlabelled K562 cells were added into wells to decrease nonspecific killing activity.</p></sec><sec><title>Purification of CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> or CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells</title><p>CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> or CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells were positively isolated from peptide-stimulated PBMCs using the CD8 Positive Isolation Kit (DYNAL, Oslo, Norway) or the CD4 Positive Isolation Kit (DYNAL) according to the manufacturer's instructions. In both cases, the percentage of purified CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> or CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells was more than 90&#x00025; (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>Kinetics of peptide-specific CTL precursors</title><p>To detect the kinetics of peptide-specific CTL precursor frequency in patient 1, PBMCs from before and after vaccination were incubated at 100 cells per well of a 96-well u-bottom microculture plate in the presence of feeder cells without the peptides. Cells from each well were harvested on the 14th day of culture and tested for their ability to produce IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> by recognition of peptide-pulsed CIR-A2402 cells in duplicate assay. The well was considered positive if it contained effector cells producing much higher than 100&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and also statistically significant levels (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 by the Student's <italic>t</italic>-test) of IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> in response to CIR-A2402 cells preloaded with a corresponding peptide as compared with those in response to the HIV peptide-pulsed CIR-A2402 cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Detection of serum immunoglobulin G (IgG) levels</title><p>An ELISA was used to detect the serum IgG levels specific to the peptides administered, as reported previously (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib24">Miyagi <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). Briefly, the peptide (20&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g&#x02009;well<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)-immobilised plate was blocked with Block Ace (Yukijirushi, Tokyo, Japan), washed, and 100&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l&#x02009;well<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of serum samples diluted with 0.05&#x00025; Tween 20-Block Ace were added to the plate. After a 2-h incubation, the plate was washed and further incubated for 2&#x02009;h with an 1&#x02009;:&#x02009;1000-diluted rabbit anti-human IgG (DAKO, Glostrup, Denmark). The plate was washed, after which 100&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l of 1&#x02009;:&#x02009;100-diluted goat anti-rabbit Ig-conjugated horseradish peroxidase-dextran polymer (En Vision, DAKO) was added to each well, and the plate was incubated for 40&#x02009;min. After washing, 100&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l&#x02009;well<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of tetramethyl-benzidine substrate solution (KPL, Guildford, UK) was added, and the reaction was stopped by the addition of 1&#x02009;<sc>M</sc> phosphoric acid. To estimate peptide-specific IgG levels, the optical density values of each sample were compared with those of serially diluted standard samples, and the values are shown as the optical density. The specificity of the ELISA was tested as follows. Serum samples (1&#x02009;:&#x02009;100 diluted) were incubated in wells precoated with corresponding or irreverent peptides to absorb the peptide-specific IgG. After a 2-h incubation at room temperature, samples were transferred to new wells precoated with the sample peptide used in the first absorption, and this protocol was repeated for a total of three times. The samples were then subjected to peptide-specific IgG ELISA.</p></sec><sec><title>Evaluation of treatment response</title><p>All known sites of disease were evaluated by CT-scan or X-ray examination pre- and post-vaccinations (the 3rd, 6th, 9th, and 12th). Patients were assigned a response category according to the response evaluation criteria in solid tumours, a revised version of the WHO criteria published in the WHO Handbook for reporting results of cancer treatment in June 1999.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Demographics of the patients</title><p>In all, 10 patients with advanced colorectal carcinomas were enroled in this phase I study. Demographic details of the patients are shown in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Patient characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Patient</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Age</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Sex</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Primary site</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Metastasis site</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Previous treatment<sup>a</sup></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>P.S.<sup>b</sup></bold></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>No. of vaccination received<sup>c</sup></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02002;1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">67</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">M</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Transverse colon</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Liver, para-aortic lymph node</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">S. C</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02002;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">38</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">F</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Transverse colon</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Liver, peritoneum (intrapelvic)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">S. C</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02002;3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">67</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">M</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Ascending colon</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Lung, liver</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">S. C</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02002;4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">78</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">M</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Rectum</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Liver</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">S. C. M</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02002;5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">70</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">F</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Sigmoid colon</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Lung, liver</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">S. C</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02002;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">72</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">M</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Rectum</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Liver</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">S</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02002;7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">67</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">M</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Sigmoid colon</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Lung</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">S. C</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02002;8</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">44</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">M</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Sigmoid colon</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Lung, liver</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">S. C</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02002;9</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">46</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">M</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Ascending colon</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Peritoneum (intrapelvic)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">S. C</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">28</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">F</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Sigmoid colon</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Peritoneum (intrapelvic)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">S. C</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">8</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote1"><label>a</label><p>S &#x0003d; surgery; C &#x0003d; chemotherapy; M &#x0003d; percutaneous microwave coagulation therapy.</p></fn><fn id="tbfnote2"><label>b</label><p>P.S. &#x0003d; performance status by ECOG score.</p></fn><fn id="tbfnote3"><label>c</label><p>The initial protocol consisted of three vaccinations; additional vaccinations were subsequently performed to patients who showed a favourable clinical course after they provided further informed consent.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>. The median patient age was 67 years (range 28&#x02013;78). All patients had liver, lung, peritoneum, or lymph node metastases. All patients underwent surgical resection of the primary lesion; nine had failed previous chemotherapy. All 10 patients completed the first three vaccinations within the protocol under informed consent, and all of them received more vaccinations (6&#x02013;15) under additional informed consent.</p></sec><sec><title>Screening of peptide-specific CTL precursors</title><p>All tumour-related antigens were identified by screening of a cDNA library from tumour cells using tumour-reactive CTLs. The peptides used for this study have the potential to induce HLA-A24-restricted and tumour-specific CTL activity in PBMCs of HLA-A24<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> cancer patients (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib18">Kikuchi <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib43">Yang <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib10">Gomi <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib12">Harashima <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib17">Kawano <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">Nakao <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib27">Nishizaka <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>). Pre-vaccination PBMCs were provided for screening of the CTL precursors reactive to the 14 candidate peptides, followed by selection of peptides based on evaluation of the results with the criteria shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Pre-vaccination screening of peptide-specific CTL precursors</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="10" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Patients</bold><hr/></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Peptide</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Sequence</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>1</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>2</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>3</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>4</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>5</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>6</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>7</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>8</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>9</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>10</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Positive case</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Vaccinated case</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART1 690</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">EYRGFTQDF</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;AA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART2 93</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">DYSARWNEI</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;AB</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART2 161</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AYDFLYNYL</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;AA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART2 899</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SYTRLFLIL</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02022;B</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART3 109</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">VYDYNCHVDL</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;B</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART3 315</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AYIDFEMKI</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;C</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;C</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CyB 84</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">KFHRVIKDF</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02022;A</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CyB 91</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">DFMIQGGDF</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;C</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 208</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">HYTNASDGL</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;C</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;B</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;AAA</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 488</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">TFDYLRSVL</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;AB</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;AAAA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;AB</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 488</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">DYLRSVLEDF</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;AA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ART1 170</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">EYCLKFTKL</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02022;B</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02022;A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02022;A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02022;AA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ART4 13</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AFLRHAAL</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02022;C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0&#x0002f;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ART4 75</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">DYPSLSATDI</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x025cb;B</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x0002f;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x0002f;10</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote4"><label/><p>White circles indicate that the peptide was positive for the CTL precursor induction assay and was injected. Black circles indicate that the peptide was positive for the CTL precursor induction assay but was not administrated due to immediate-type hypersensitivity by skin test. The assay was performed in quadruplicate and the background response to the HIV peptide was subtracted from the value. The result was evaluated by the following criteria: A, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 and IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production &#x0003e;50&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; B, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 and 50&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> &#x0003e;IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production &#x0003e;25&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>: C, 0.05&#x0003c;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.1 and IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production &#x0003e;25&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The classification is shown by letters of the alphabet, and each character represents the results of each well. For example, ABC means that three wells were judged as A, B, and C, and one well was negative.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>. The assay was performed in quadruplicate. After a 12-day incubation, the cultured cells in one well were separated into four wells, two of which were used for corresponding peptide-pulsed C1R-A2402 cells, and the other two of which were used for HIV peptide-pulsed C1R-A2402 cells. The HLA-A24-binding HIV peptide was used as a negative control. The assessment of peptide-specific CTL precursors was performed based on two parameters, the <italic>P</italic>-value by the Student's <italic>t</italic>-test and IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production, as shown in the table legend. When these peptides were found to induce immediate-type hypersensitivity by a skin test, a fifth peptide was vaccinated if it proved negative in the skin test. SART2<sub>899</sub>, CyB<sub>91</sub>, ART1<sub>170</sub>, and ART4<sub>13</sub> were positive for immediate-type hypersensitivity in all patients tested and were not injected at all. As a result, five patients were injected with four peptides, three patients with three peptides, and two with two peptides. The vaccinated peptides for each patient are shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. It is noteworthy that the profiles of the vaccinated peptides varied greatly among the 10 patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Toxicities</title><p>All 10 patients were evaluated for toxicity; the overall toxicities are shown in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Toxicities associated with the peptide vaccination</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>Grade<sup>a</sup></bold><hr/></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Toxicities</bold></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>I</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>II</bold></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>Total</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Anorexia</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dermatologic</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">7</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Diarrhoea</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Fatigue</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Fever</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Nausea</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Vomiting</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote5"><label>a</label><p>Toxicities are based on the NIH Common Toxicity Criteria.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>. The vaccinations were generally well-tolerated, but almost all patients (eight out of 10) had grade I or II local redness and swelling at the injection sites. Fever with mild flu-like symptoms was observed in four patients (grade I or grade II), although this symptom was transient and no medication was needed. Grade I fatigue or nausea was observed in two patients, and grade I anorexia, diarrhoea, or vomiting was observed in one. No vaccine-related grade III or IV toxicity was observed (data not shown). There was no clinical evidence of an autoimmune reaction as determined by symptoms, physical examination, or laboratory test.</p></sec><sec><title>Cellular immune responses</title><p>Post-vaccination (6th) PBMCs showed increased amounts of peptide-specific IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production compared to pre-vaccination PBMCs in five out of 10 patients (1, 2, 5, 6, and 10), as described in <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>
 <table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p content-type="table-title">Summary of response to the peptide vaccination</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Peptide-specific CTL<sup>a</sup></bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>Ab to peptide</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>DTH</bold><hr/></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Clinical response&#x0002f;</bold></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Patient</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Peptide</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Pre</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Post</bold></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>Pre</bold></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>Post<sup>b</sup></bold></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>Pre</bold></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><bold>Post<sup>b</sup></bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>Time to progression (months)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART3 109</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">7&#x02009;mm (9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">PR&#x0002f;7&#x0003c;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 208</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ArArA</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0002b; (6)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">10&#x02009;mm (6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 488</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Ar</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0002b; (9)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">10&#x02009;mm (6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART3 109</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">B</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0002b; (6)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SD&#x0002f;7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 208</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AAAA</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 486</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AB</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0002b; (9)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CyB 91</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">PD&#x0002f;3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 488</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ART4 75</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CyB 91</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">PD&#x0002f;3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 208</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">7&#x02009;mm (3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 486</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AAAA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">7&#x02009;mm (3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 488</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">7&#x02009;mm (3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART3 109</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ArB</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">PD&#x0002f;4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 208</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0002b; (9)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART3 109</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ArBC</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0002b; (6)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">PD&#x0002f;3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ART4 75</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">B</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">B</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART3 109</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0002b; (6)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">10&#x02009;mm (3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">PD&#x0002f;4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART3 315</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CyB 91</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 208</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART1 690</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">PD&#x0002f;4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART2 93</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AB</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART2 161</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 208</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">B</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART1 690</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">PD&#x0002f;4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART2 161</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART3 109</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 486</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AB</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0002b;(6)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SART3 315</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">C</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ArAA</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0002b;(6)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">PD&#x0002f;3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CyB 91</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 208</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AAA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">lck 486</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbfnote6"><label>a</label><p>The CTL precursor induction assay was performed in quadruplicate, and the background response to the HIV peptide was subtracted from the value. The result was evaluated by the following criteria: Ar (armed response), P&#x0003c;0.1 and IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production &#x0003e;500&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; A, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 and IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production &#x0003e;50&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>: B, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 and 50&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> &#x0003e;IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production &#x0003e;25&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; C, 0.05&#x0003c;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.1 and IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production &#x0003e;25&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The classification is shown by letters of the alphabet, and each character represents the results of each well. For example, ArBC means that three wells were judged as Ar, B, and C, and one well was negative.</p></fn><fn id="tbfnote7"><label>b</label><p>The number in the parenthesis represents the vaccination when anti-peptide IgG or DTH was detected for the first time.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>. Representative results of patients 1 and 2 are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Assay of peptide-specific CTL precursors. (<bold>A</bold>) Pre- and post- (6th) vaccination PBMCs were provided for screening of reactivity to each of the 14 peptides listed in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> in the quadruplicate assays. Representative results of patients 1 and 2 are shown in this figure. The peptide-stimulated PBMCs were cultured with C1R-A2402 cells that were preloaded with the corresponding peptide (open bar) or the HIV peptide (closed bar). The level of IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> in the supernatant was determined by ELISA. The result was evaluated by the classification shown in the legend of <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. Each alphabet character represents the result of each well. (<bold>B</bold>) Pre- and post- (6th) vaccination PBMCs from patient 2 were stimulated <italic>in vitro</italic> with the SART3<sub>109</sub> peptide. The peptide-stimulated PBMCs were harvested, and positively isolated CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> or CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells were cultured in triplicate with C1R-A2402 cells that were preloaded with the SART3<sub>109</sub> peptide (open bar) or the HIV peptide (closed bar). The level of IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> in the supernatant was determined by ELISA. <sup>&#x0002a;</sup>Statistically significant at <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="90-6601711f1"/></fig>. In patients 1 and 2, CTL response to the lck<sub>208</sub> was apparently induced after the 6th vaccination. In five other patients, peptide-specific CTL response decreased. We further tested the reactivity of purified CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> or CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells in response to the administered peptides. The pre- or post-6th vaccination PBMCs from patient 2 were <italic>in vitro</italic> stimulated, and purified CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> or CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells were tested for their reactivity to the SART3<sub>109</sub> peptide-pulsed C1R-A2402 cells. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>, purified CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells from the post-vaccination PBMCs of patient 2 produced IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> in an antigen-specific manner, although no definite IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production specific to the SART3<sub>109</sub> peptide was observed when unseparated post-6th PBMCs from patient 2 were used (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). Purified CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells failed to produce IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> in a peptide-specific manner. On the other hand, no peptide-specific IL-4 production was observed in the case with purified CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> or CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells (data not shown).</p><p>We next examined cytotoxicity of pre- and post- (3rd, 6th, and 9th) vaccination PBMCs from eight patients against SW620 (HLA-A24<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> colon tumour cells), COLO201 cells (HLA-A24<sup>&#x02212;</sup> colon tumour cells), and PHA-activated T cells (HLA-A24<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Cytotoxicity before and after the peptide vaccination. Pre- and post-vaccination PBMCs from eight patients were incubated for 14 days with IL-2 alone without any peptides in culture, followed by measurement of cytotoxicity against SW620 cells (HLA-A24<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> colon cancer cell line), COLO201 cells (HLA-A24<sup>&#x02212;</sup> colon cancer cell line), and PHA-activated T cells (HLA-A24<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>) by a 6-h <sup>51</sup>Cr-release assay at an <italic>E</italic>&#x0002f;<italic>T</italic> ratio of 40&#x0002f;1. The assay was performed in triplicate, and the mean and s.d. are shown. <sup>&#x0002a;</sup>Statistically significant at <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="90-6601711f2"/></fig>). Tumour-related antigens from which all peptides used in this study were derived are nonmutated self-antigens overexpressed in tumour cells, including SW620 and COLO201 (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib38">Shichijo <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib43">Yang <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib10">Gomi <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib12">Harashima <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib17">Kawano <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">Nakao <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib27">Nishizaka <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>). As shown in four cases of patients 2, 3, 7, and 9, cytotoxicity against HLA-A24<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> SW620 increased after peptide vaccination compared to that against HLA-A24<sup>&#x02212;</sup> COLO201. In the other four cases, no definite increase in cytotoxicity was observed after the peptide vaccination. No cytotoxicity against HLA-A24<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> PHA-blastoid T cells was detected in any case. These results indicate that the peptide vaccination resulted in augmented CTL activity in four out of eight patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Serum IgG specific to peptides</title><p>No IgG reactive to any of the vaccinated peptides was detected in pre-vaccination sera from any of the 10 patients (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Significant levels of anti-peptide IgG reactive to SART3- or lck-derived peptides became detectable in the post-vaccination sera of seven patients. Detail results are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>IgG reactive to the vaccinated peptides. (<bold>A</bold>) Pre- and post-vaccination sera from patient 1 were serially diluted and the levels of IgGs reactive to three administered peptides were determined by ELISA. (<bold>B</bold>) Pre- and post-vaccination sera from patients 2, 5, 6, 7, 9, and 10 were serially diluted and the levels of IgGs reactive to corresponding peptides were determined by ELISA. (<bold>C</bold>) Diluted sera of patient 1 after the 9th vaccination were cultured in the indicated peptide-coated wells and the levels of IgGs reactive to corresponding peptides were determined by ELISA. <sup>&#x0002a;</sup>Statistically significant at <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="90-6601711f3"/></fig>. In patient 1, IgGs reactive to the lck<sub>208</sub> and the lck<sub>488</sub> peptides were induced after the 6th and 9th vaccinations, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). A similar result was observed in six other patients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). It is noteworthy that three patients who showed strong peptide-specific CTL response (criteria Ar) after the peptide vaccination were also positive for antipeptide IgG to the corresponding peptides (patient 1 for lck<sub>208</sub> and lck<sub>488</sub>, patient 6 for SART3<sub>109</sub>, and patient 10 for SART3<sub>315</sub>). In addition, the IgG response to the lck<sub>208</sub> peptide in post-vaccination sera of patient 1 was neutralised by absorption with a corresponding peptide, but not with the lck<sub>408</sub> peptide, whereas the opposite was observed in the case of the IgG response to the lck<sub>488</sub> peptide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). This peptide-specific absorption demonstrates the validity of the ELISA system.</p></sec><sec><title>DTH skin test</title><p>No DTH reaction against peptides was observed before vaccination in any patient, while peptide-specific DTH reactions were observed in three patients after the peptide vaccination (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). In patient 1, DTH reactions to lck<sub>208</sub> and lck<sub>488</sub> were observed after the 6th vaccination, and DTH against SART3<sub>109</sub> became detectable after the 9th vaccination. Patient 4 exhibited a DTH reaction against lck<sub>208</sub>, lck<sub>486</sub>, and lck<sub>488</sub> after the 3rd vaccination. Patient 7 exhibited a DTH reaction against SART3<sub>109</sub> after the 3rd vaccination.</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical results</title><p>The clinical responses of each patient are summarised in <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. CT scans of patient 1 pre- and post-vaccination are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Clinical and immunological responses to the peptide vaccination. (<bold>A</bold>) CT scans show tumour regression of the liver metastasis after the peptide vaccination. The size of the liver metastasis (S8) is described. (<bold>B</bold>) CTL activity before and after vaccinations. Cytotoxicity to SW620 cells (HLA-A24<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> colon cancer cell line), COLO201 cells (HLA-A24<sup>&#x02212;</sup> colon cancer cell line), and PHA-activated T cells (HLA-A24<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>) was tested by a 6-h <sup>51</sup>Cr-release assay at an <italic>E</italic>&#x0002f;<italic>T</italic> ratio of 40&#x0002f;1. Values are the means of triplicate assay. <sup>&#x0002a;</sup>Statistically significant at <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05. (<bold>C</bold>) Peptide-specific CTL activity before and after the peptide vaccinations. Cytotoxicity to CIR-A2402 cells preloaded with the lck<sub>208</sub> or the control HIV peptide was tested by a 6-h <sup>51</sup>Cr-release assay at an <italic>E</italic>&#x0002f;<italic>T</italic> ratio of 40&#x0002f;1. <sup>&#x0002a;</sup>Statistically significant at <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05. (<bold>D</bold>) Kinetics of peptide-specific CTL precursors. Pre- and post- (3rd, 6th, and 9th) vaccination PBMCs were incubated at 100 cells per well in a 96-well round-microculture plate in the presence of feeder cells. The number of wells producing a significant level of IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> in a peptide-specific manner among 96 wells is shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="90-6601711f4"/></fig>. In all, 48&#x00025; regression (27&#x02013;14&#x02009;mm) of liver metastasis was observed in patient 1. This patient had para-aortic lymph node metastasis at a diameter of less than 20&#x02009;mm; it showed no change after the peptide vaccination (data not shown). Because his clinical response was considered a partial response (PR), this patient was analysed more in detail. The kinetic analysis of tumour cell lysis in patient 1 indicates that increased CTL activity to the SW620 cells became detectable in post-vaccination PBMCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). The cytotoxicity against lck<sub>208</sub> peptide-loaded CIR-A2402 cells became significant after the 3rd and 6th vaccinations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). While no peptide-specific IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production was detected in any of the 96 wells containing 100&#x02009;cells&#x02009;well<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of pre-vaccination PBMCs, SART3<sub>109</sub>-specific IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production was detected in two, two, and four wells among 96 wells containing post-vaccination (3rd, 6th, and 9th) PBMCs, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>). Production of lck<sub>208</sub>-specific IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production was detectable in three and four wells among 96 wells containing the 6th and 9th vaccination PBMCs, while lck<sub>488</sub>-specific IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production could be observed in one and two wells among 96 wells containing the 6th- and 9th-vaccination PBMCs, respectively. The patient has subsequently been treated only by vaccination (SART3<sub>109</sub>, lck<sub>208</sub>, and lck<sub>488</sub>) for 7 months as an outpatient, and is still doing well. Patient 2 had intrapelvic metastasis, and the disease has remained stable (s.d.) for 6 months. The eight other patients showed progressive disease (PD) 2&#x02013;4 months after starting the vaccinations, although all have been treated as outpatients and their quality of life has been evaluated as quite high.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Patients undergoing this regimen received 3&#x02009;mg of peptides biweekly for up to four peptides. All of the peptides used were derived from nonmutated self-antigens involved in cellular proliferation (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib18">Kikuchi <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib10">Gomi <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib43">Yang <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib12">Harashima <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib17">Kawano <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib25">Nakao <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib27">Nishizaka <italic>et al</italic>, 2000</xref>). However, there was no grade III or IV adverse effect, which is consistent with previous observations in studies of peptide-based vaccinations. Most of the patients received the vaccination as outpatients, and the performance status remained very good throughout the treatment periods. Therefore, in terms of safety, this regimen of CTL precursor-oriented peptide vaccine could be recommended as a cancer vaccine suitable for further clinical trials.</p><p>Another aim of our study was to assess the clinical response to the vaccination. In our limited number of case, we observed one PR and one s.d. continuing for more than 6 months. Both of these cases were treated with three kinds of SART3- and lck-derived peptides, suggesting that the combined use of these peptides might constitute a promising vaccine strategy for advanced colorectal carcinomas, thus encouraging us to plan a phase II trial utilising these peptides.</p><p>Vaccination-induced immunity was evaluated in this study by several different methods, including IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production in response to peptides, a standard 6-h <sup>51</sup>Cr-release assay, measurement of antipeptide antibody, and DTH responses. An elevated immune response to lck<sub>208</sub> and lck<sub>488</sub> was detected in post-vaccination PBMCs by all of the methods used in the samples of patient 1, who showed PR. This patient's PBMCs also reacted to the SART3<sub>109</sub> peptide, as measured by frequency analysis of cellular responses to peptides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>) and also by DTH test (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). These results indicate that the patient's PBMCs reacted to all three vaccinated peptides after the peptide vaccination. Post-vaccination PBMCs from patient 2, who had a long s.d., responded to lck<sub>208</sub> peptide alone, and the post-vaccination sera became positive for both the SART3<sub>109</sub> and lck<sub>486</sub> peptides, although no DTH response was observed (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Besides patient 1, positive DTH response was observed in only two patients (4 and 7), with PD, but their post-vaccination PBMCs showed no increase in cellular responses to the administered peptides. On the other hand, besides patients 1 and 2, IgG reactive to the administered peptides became detectable in the post-vaccination sera of five other patients (5, 6, 7, 9, and 10) with PD. Although the post-vaccination PBMCs of patients 6 and 10 showed an increase in cellular responses to SART3<sub>109</sub> and SART3<sub>315</sub>, respectively, no augmentation of peptide-specific cellular response was observed in other cases. Neither a cellular nor humoral immune response to administered peptides was detectable in the remaining two patients (3 and 8), who also had PD. These results suggest that vaccination-induced immunity varies considerably among patients. However, we recently reported that the <italic>in vivo</italic> induction of IgG reactive to administered peptides is positively correlated with clinical response or the survival of patients with prostate, lung, gastric, or gynaecological cancer (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib23">Mine <italic>et al</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib28">Noguchi <italic>et al</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib36">Sato <italic>et al</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib40">Tsuda <italic>et al</italic>, 2004</xref>). This may be the case with patients 1 and 2, who showed PR and s.d., respectively, because IgGs reactive to two different peptides were induced only in these two patients. We have no clear answer regarding the role of peptide-specific IgG in antitumour immune response, and are now grappling with this theme.</p><p>In addressing the mechanism for peptide-specific IgG induction after peptide vaccination, one possibility is that 9-mer or 10-mer peptide-recognizing CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells were involved in this phenomenon. In general, <italic>in vivo</italic> generation of antigen-specific IgG requires a cytokine from helper T cells (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib29">Parker, 1993</xref>). Although peptides binding to MHC class II molecules have been suggested to be 12&#x02013;25 amino acids in length, the core sites anchored to MHC class II molecules are sufficient even at a length of about nine amino acids (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib32">Rammensee <italic>et al</italic>, 1995</xref>). Indeed, we recently observed that peptide vaccination with a 9-mer peptide could induce peptide-specific and HLA-DR-restricted CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib11">Harada <italic>et al</italic>, 2004</xref>). CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T-cell help is required during the generation and maintenance of effective anti-tumour CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cell-mediated immunity. The requirement of CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T-cell help to initiate and sustain a CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T-cell response has been well established and has led to the development of antitumour vaccines that attempt to induce both T-cell subsets (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib19">Knutson <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). The <italic>in vivo</italic> induction of IgG reactive to administered peptides may be indirect evidence of the involvement of CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T lymphocytes.</p><p>We recently developed a culture system to evaluate CTL precursors against many peptides using a limited number of PBMCs from cancer patients (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib13">Hida <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>); the same culture system was applied to this study. The main reason why we assessed peptide-specific CTL precursors based on two parameters, the <italic>P</italic>-value and IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production, was that the levels of IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> produced by peptide-specific CTLs varied among quadruplicate wells. This finding might be due to the small number of cells (10<sup>5</sup>&#x02009;cells&#x02009;well<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) that were initially placed in each well. It is possible that one well may have contained peptide-specific CTL precursors, whereas another may have contained none. We concluded that each well should be individually estimated to screen for the presence of peptide-specific CTL precursors.</p><p>Recent reports revealed that a Th2 response is predominant in cancer patients (<xref ref-type="other" rid="bib30">Pellegrini <italic>et al</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib42">Vita <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="bib37">Sheu <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>). Therefore, we examined the level of IL-4 during peptide stimulation <italic>in vitro</italic>, but the level of IL-4 production was generally low, and no peptide-specific IL-4 production was observed. In contrast, the level of IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> production was constantly substantial. Probably, the <italic>in vitro</italic> culture of PBMCs in the presence of IL-2 could preferentially activate natural killer cells, and natural killer cell-derived IFN-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> might provide an optimal condition for Th1 type cells.</p><p>In conclusion, vaccination of colorectal cancer patients with peptides by the CTL precursor-oriented method was a well-tolerated outpatient treatment and induced antigen-specific immunity as well as a clinical response. Even though only a small number of selected patients were treated, the encouraging clinical response demands further studies of CTL precursor-oriented vaccine in other human cancers.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to express our gratitude to the patients who participated in this study and to the oncologists who referred their patients to us. This work was supported in part by Grants from the Ministry of Education, Science, Sport, Culture, and Technology of Japan (11178101 to KI), and the Ministry of Health, Labor, and Welfare of Japan (H2-genome-003, 11-16, and H12-cancer-004 to KI)</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brichard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000f6;lfel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000f6;lfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Plaen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Leth&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Boon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The tyrosinase gene codes for an antigen recognized by autologous cytotoxic T lymphocytes on HLA-A2 melanoma</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1993</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>495</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Exp Med||178|489||bib1|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8340755</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruggen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Traversari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chomez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lurquin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Plaen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Eynde</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Boon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A gene encoding an antigen recognized by cytotoxic T lymphocytes on a human melanoma</article-title><source>Science (Washington DC)</source><year>1991</year><volume>254</volume><fpage>1643</fpage><lpage>1647</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Science (Washington DC)||254|1643||bib2|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Descrictive epidemiology: cancer statistics</article-title><source>Cancer Principles &#x00026; Practice of Oncology</source><year>2001</year><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>230</lpage>Vincent Jr TD, Samuel H, Rosenberg SA (eds) 6th Edition pp</citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Correale</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Walmsley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieroda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaremba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> generation of human cytotoxic T lymphocytes specific for peptides derived from prostate-specific antigen</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>1997</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Natl Cancer Inst||89|293||bib4|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9048833</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Correale</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Walmsley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaremb</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Generation of human cytotoxic T lymphocyte lines directed against prostate-specific antigen (PSA) employing a PSA oligoepitope peptide</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1998</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>3186</fpage><lpage>3194</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunol||161|3186||bib5|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9743387</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A decade in the life of tumor immunology</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>760</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Clin Cancer Res||7|759||bib6|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11309319</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Blevins</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioannides</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of an immunodominant peptide of HER2&#x0002f;neu proto-oncogene recognized by ovarian tumor-specific cytotoxic T lymphocytes line</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>2109</fpage><lpage>2117</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Exp Med||181|2109||bib7|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7539040</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gajewski</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fallarino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunization of HLA-A2<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> melanoma patients with MAGE-3 or MelanA peptide-pulsed autologous peripheral blood mononuclear cells plus recombinant human interleukin 12</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><supplement>Suppl</supplement><fpage>895s</fpage><lpage>901s</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Clin Cancer Res||7|895s||bib8|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11300489</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gjertsen</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Buanes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosseland</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladhaug</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Soreide</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interdermal ras peptide vaccination with granulocyte&#x02013;macropharge colony-stimulating factor as adjuvant: clinical and immunological responses in patients with pancreatic adenocarcinoma</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2001</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Int J Cancer||92|441||bib9|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11291084</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Niiya</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishizaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A cyclophilin B gene encodes antigenic epitopes recognized by HLA-A24-restricted and tumor-specific cytotoxic T lymphocytes</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1999</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>4994</fpage><lpage>5004</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunol||163|4994||bib10|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10528204</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gohara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsueda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> evidence that peptide vaccination can induce HLA-DR-restricted CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells reactive to a class I tumor peptide</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2004</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>2659</fpage><lpage>2667</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunol||172|2659||bib11|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14764741</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harashima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasatomi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyagi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition of the Lck tyrosine kinase as a tumor antigen by cytotoxic T lymphocytes of cancer patients with distant metastases</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><year>2000</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Eur J Immunol||31|323||bib12|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11180095</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takasu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple culture protocol to detect peptide-specific cytotoxic T lymphocyte precursors in the circulation</article-title><source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Immunol Immunother||51|219||bib13|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12012109</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnjatic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Stockert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Karbach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieckenberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Arand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Old</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Knuth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of primary NY-ESO-1 immunity: CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T lymphocyte and antibody responses in peptide-vaccinated patients with NY-ESO-1<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> cancers</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>12198</fpage><lpage>12203</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Proc Natl Acad Sci USA||97|12198||bib14|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliyahu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Appella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a human melanoma antigen recognized by tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes associated with <italic>in vitro</italic> tumor rejection</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1994b</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>6458</fpage><lpage>6462</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Proc Natl Acad Sci USA||91|6458||bib15|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliyahu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivoltini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yannelli</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of the immunodominant peptides of the MART-1 human melanoma antigen recognized by the majority of HLA-A2 restricted tumor infiltrating lymphocytes</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1994a</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>352</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Exp Med||180|347||bib16|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7516411</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a new endoplasmic reticulum-resident protein recognized by HLA-A24-restricted tumor infiltrating lymphocytes of lung cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>3550</fpage><lpage>3558</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||60|3550||bib17|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10910068</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsunaga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shichijo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Idnetification of a SART-1-derived peptides capable of inducing HLA-A24-restricted and tumor-specific cytotoxic T lymphocytes</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>1999</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Int J Cancer||81|459||bib18|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10209962</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knutson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiffman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Disis</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunization with a HER2&#x0002f;neu helper peptide vaccine generates HER2&#x0002f;neu CD8 T-cell immunity in cancer patients</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2001</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>484</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Clin Invest||107|477||bib19|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11181647</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuniyoshi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bade</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phase I trial of intravenous peptide-pulsed dendritic cells in patients with metastatic melanoma</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2001</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunol||24|66||bib20|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Niiya</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamana</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Todo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of peptide-specific CTL-precursors in peripheral blood lymphocytes of cancer patients</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2002</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>804</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Br J Cancer||87|796||bib21|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12232766</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baren</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Weynants</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brichard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreno</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tessier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmiani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Arienti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Humblet</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourlond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanwijck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lienard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauduin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Masucci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De Greve</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Atzpodien</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brasseur</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulie</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Bruggen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Boon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumor regressions observed in patients with metastatic melanoma treated with an antigen peptide encoded by MAGE-3 and presented by HLA-A1</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>1999</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Int J Cancer||80|219||bib22|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9935203</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouhara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Azuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rikimaru</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishikori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukehiro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aizawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirouzu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamana</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunological evaluation of CTL precursor-oriented vaccines for advanced lung cancer patients</article-title><source>Cancer Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Science||94|548||bib23|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824881</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyagi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasatomi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Okouchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Isomoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirouzu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamana</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of cellular immune responses to tumor cells and peptides in colorectal cancer patients by vaccination with SART3 peptides</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>3950</fpage><lpage>3962</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Clin Cancer Res||7|3950||bib24|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751487</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shichijo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Imaizumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsunaga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a gene coding for a new squamous cell carcinoma antigen recognized by the CTLs</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2000</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>2565</fpage><lpage>2574</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunol||164|2565||bib25|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10679095</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nestle</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name><name><surname>Alijagic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilliet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Grabbe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dummer R Burg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schadendorf</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccination of melanoma patients with peptide- or tumor lysate-pulsed dendritic cells</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Nat Med||4|328||bib26|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9500607</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishizaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Oizumi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shichijo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new tumor-rejection antigen recognized by cytotoxic T lymphocytes infiltrating into a lung adenocarcinoma</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>4830</fpage><lpage>4837</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||60|4830||bib27|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10987294</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suetsugu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomiyasu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Suekane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of cellular and humoral immune responses to tumor cells and peptides in HLA-A24 positive hormone-refractory prostate cancer patients by peptide vaccination</article-title><source>Prostate</source><year>2003</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Prostate||57|80||bib28|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12886526</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>T cell-dependent B-cell activation</article-title><source>Ann Rev Immunol</source><year>1993</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Ann Rev Immunol||11|331||bib29|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8476565</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Berghella</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Beato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cicia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Adorno</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Casciani</surname><given-names>CU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dysregulation in TH1 and TH2 subsets of CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells in peripheral blood of colorectal cancer patients and involvement in cancer establishment and progression</article-title><source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source><year>1996</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Immunol Immunother||42|1||bib30|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8625361</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peoples</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Geodegebuure</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Linehan</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshino</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Eberlein</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast and ovarian cancer-specific cytotoxic T lymphocytes recognized the same HER2&#x0002f;neu-derived peptide</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1995</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>432</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Proc Natl Acad Sci USA||92|432||bib31|'--></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rammensee</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Frige</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevanovic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MHC ligands and peptide motifs</article-title><source>Immunogenetics</source><year>1995</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Immunogenetics||41|178||bib32|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7890324</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Gamil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Loftus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Appella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A mutated <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-catenin gene encodes a melanoma-specific antigen recognized by tumor infiltrating lymphocytes</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1996</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>1185</fpage><lpage>1192</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Exp Med||183|1185||bib33|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8642260</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartzentruber</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marincola</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Topalian</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Restifo</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiess</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunderlich</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkhurst</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Seipp</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Einhorn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunologic and therapeutic evaluation of a synthetic peptide vaccine for the treatment of patients with metastatic melanoma</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Nat Med||4|321||bib34|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9500606</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadanaga</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagashima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mashino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tahara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takesako</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiyoshi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dendritic cell vaccination with MAGE peptide is a novel therapeutic approach for gastrointestinal carcinomas</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>2277</fpage><lpage>2284</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Clin Cancer Res||7|2277||bib35|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11489802</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shomura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Akasaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamana</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Todo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunological evaluation of peptide vaccination for patients with gastric cancer based on pre-existing cellular response to peptide</article-title><source>Cancer Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>802</fpage><lpage>808</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Sci||94|802||bib36|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12967479</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheu</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lien</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predominant Th2&#x0002f;Tc2 polarity of tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes in human cervical cancer</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2001</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>2972</fpage><lpage>2978</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunol||167|2972||bib37|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11509647</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shichijo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takasu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Niiya</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A gene encoding antigenic peptides of human squamous cell carcinoma recognized by cytotoxic T lymphocytes</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Exp Med||187|277||bib38|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9449708</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of peptide-specific cytotoxic T lymphocyte precursors used for specific immunotherapy of pancreatic cancer</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2002</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Int J Cancer||98|45||bib39|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11857384</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukehiro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ushijima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamana</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccination with pre-designated or evidence-based peptides for patients with recurrent gynecologic cancers</article-title><source>J Immunother</source><year>2004</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'J Immunother||27|60||bib40|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14676634</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valmori</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutoit</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio-Goboy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lienard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillaume</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frequent cytotoxic T-cell responses to peptide MAGE-A10<sub>254&#x02013;262</sub> in melanoma</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||61|509||bib41|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11212242</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vita</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Orditura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Galizia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Infusino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Auriemma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serum interleukin-10 levels in patients with advanced gastrointestinal malignancies</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>1999</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>1936</fpage><lpage>1943</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer||86|1936||bib42|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10570416</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shichijo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasatomi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takasu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a gene coding for a protein possessing shared tumor epitopes capable of inducing HLA-A24-restricted cytotoxic T lymphocytes in cancer patients</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>4056</fpage><lpage>4063</lpage><!--PubMed citation query: 'Cancer Res||59|4056||bib43|'--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10463607</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


