<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9681808</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054502</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Digital infrared thermographic imaging in patients with gastroesophageal reflux disease.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><email>leesi96@yumc.yonsei.ac.kr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nah</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Y. E.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. I.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>I. S.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Internal Medicine, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><abstract><p>We performed a thermographic study to observe any possible interaction between the esophageal acid perfusion and the temperature changes of skin surface in patients with gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD). Twenty-seven patients with GERD were categorized as group I(globus symptoms with posterior laryngitis) and group II (heartburn and/or regurgitation symptoms). Patients and 6 healthy volunteers underwent Bernstein test (BT) and digital infrared thermographic imaging (DITI) simultaneously. The positive rate for BT in group I and group II was 22.2% and 55.6%, respectively, and the DITI positive rate was 55.6% for group I and 50.0% for group II. None of healthy control were positive in BT or DITI. All subjects with DITI positive were hypothermic. The overall accordance rate between DITI and BT was 69.7%. All group I patients showed a diffuse type, while in group 11, 4 patients showed diffuse type and 5 patients showed localized type (p&#x0003c;0.05). In patients with DITI (+)/BT (-), 83.3% showed diffuse type, whereas equal numbers of diffuse and localized type were noted in patients with DITI (+)/BT (+). In conclusion, add contact with a sensitive mucosa leads to an activation of the sympathetic nervous system in some patients with GERD, inducing skin surface hypothermia.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

