<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">3077056</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3053669</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Multicenter report on dialysis and transplantation in Korea, 1986. Korean Society of Nephrology.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Dept. of Internal medicine, Catholic University Medical College, Seocho-ku, Seoul.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>1988</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><abstract><p>Since 1981, the Korean Society of Nephrology began annual report on renal replacement therapy in Korea. The annual number of new patients receiving dialysis treatment in 1986 increased to 957 patients (23.3 per million population) from 825 patients (20.4 per million population) in 1985. And the total number of patients on replacement therapy increased from 1,508 patients (37.3 per million population) to 2,534 patients (61.7 per million population). 1,340 patients (32.6 per million population) of these patients were on hemodialysis, 573 patients (13.9 per million population) on continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis (CAPD) and 621 patients (15.1 per million population) on functioning renal graft as of December 31, 1986. The common causes of renal failure of new patients were chronic glomerulonephritis (41.6%) followed by diabetic nephropathy (12.6%), nypertensive nephrosclerosis (7.8%), chronic pyelonephritis (2.5%) and others. The annual mortality rate decreased from 21.9% in 1981 to 13.5 in 1986. The common causes of death in patients on dialysis therapy were cardiac (32.8%), vascular (14.7%), infective (14.7%) and social problems (11.2%) in the order of frequency. Recently, the number of patients requiring dialysis is rapidly increasing due to expanded medical insurance support for dialysis and improved economic status of our country. Therefore, it is necessary to draw up counterplan for a rapid growth of the number of new patients.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

