<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9288629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054216</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Expression of HuD (a paraneoplastic encephalomyelitis antigen) mRNA in lung cancer.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Pathology Division, College of Medicine, Dankook University, Chungnam, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>1997</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><abstract><p>HuD, one of the Hu antigens (HuD and HuC), was recognized in the sera of small cell lung cancer (SCLC) patients with antibody-associated paraneoplastic encephalomyelitis/peripheral sensory neuropathy (PEM/PSN). Three forms of HuD mRNA, 197, 156, 110 nucleotides are made by alternative splicing at 868-909 residues and an additional 3'-splice site. To determine the diagnostic value of the HuD expression for small cell lung cancer, we examined 4 SCLC cell lines, 9 surgically resected SCLCs, and 12 surgically resected non-SCLCs using the reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction with the HuD-specific primer pairs that spanned the putative alternative 3'-splicing site and direct DNA sequencing. None of the patients were associated with PEM/PSN. A single RNA transcript (156 nucleotides) among three forms (110, 156, 197 nucleotides) of the HuD gene was an alternatively spliced at 868-909 residues in SCLC cell lines. Expression of the HuD gene was stronger in three classic cell lines, but not in a variant cell line. Two of 9 SCLCs (22%) and 3 of 12 non-SCLCs (25%) expressed only the major RNA transcript (156 nucleotides) of the HuD gene, which was alternatively spliced in the same fashion as the cell line. These results revealed that no aberrant alternative splicing occurred in SCLC not associated with PEM/PSN and the expression of HuD gene was not specific for a particular histologic subtype of human lung cancer.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

