<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9288632</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054218</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Analysis of clonality by X chromosome inactivation in uterine cervix cancer.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Juhng</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Pathology, Chonnam University Medical School, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>1997</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><abstract><p>The determination of a unicellular or a multicellular origin of a tumor is an important due for understanding its etiology. To investigate this issue, we performed clonality assay of cervix cancer using polymerase chain reaction based on highly polymorphic locus of the androgen receptor gene, in which methylation of DNA correlates with inactivation of X chromosome. DNA samples were obtained from formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded tissue of 20 invasive epidermoid carcinomas and 10 carcinoma in situ. Seven of ten carcinoma in situ, heterozygous for the androgen receptor locus, were monoclonal pattern. Among twenty invasive epidermoid carcinomas, eighteen of which showed heterozygous, twelve were monoclonal pattern and six were polyclonal pattern. We conclude that carcinoma in situ arises from a single cell. In invasive epidermoid carcinoma, most cases were monoclonal, although some cases were polyclonal. These suggest that invasive carcinoma of the cervix does not always arise from a single cell, but may arise from several cells with different mechanisms.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

