<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8924231</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3053885</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Preliminary experiences with intraoperative radiation therapy (IORT) for the treatment of brain tumors.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Y. G.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Neurosurgery, Korea University College of Medicine, Seoul.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>1995</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><abstract><p>Ten brain tumor patients underwent wide resection of the tumor followed by Intraoperative Radiation Therapy (IORT) at the first surgery or at the second salvage surgery after failure of conventional external beam irradiation. Two patients(1 meningioma, 1 glioblastoma multiforme) were treated at the first surgery and 8 patients(3 anaplastic astrocytoma, 3 glioblastoma multiforme, 1 meningioma, 1 gliosarcoma) were treated after salvage surgery. The IORT doses were ranged from 15-25 Gy depending on the tumor volume and previous radiation therapy. The neurological status(Karnofsky performance status) was improved in 4 cases, not changed in 6 cases after IORT. There were several complications after IORT; radiation necrosis, communicating hydrocephalus, wound infection, and abnormal CT findings such as diffuse low density area in an around operation site. The radiation necrosis was confirmed by operation in a recurrent meningioma patient 12 months after IORT. At follow-up, ranging from 1 to 16 months, there was no deaths. Based on our limited experiences, the IORT might be one of the adjuvant therapeutic modalities especially for the malignant brain tumors and unresectable huge meningioma.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

