<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10576154</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054450</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Survival improvement with combined radio-chemotherapy in the primary central nervous system lymphomas.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>I. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C. I.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Therapeutic Radiology, Seoul National University College of Medicine, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>1999</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>570</lpage><abstract><p>The benefits of radio-chemotherapy in HIV-negative primary central nervous system (CNS) lymphomas were analyzed in 40 patients, who received radiotherapy to the brain or craniospinal axis with the total dose of 4460-5940 cGy to the primary tumor. Radiotherapy was followed by systemic chemotherapy, mainly with the cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine and prednisolone (CHOP) regimen, in 16 of the patients. Follow-up ranged from four to 95 months with a median of 15 months. The relapse rate was 72.5%, and 83% of the relapses occurred within the radiation field. Median survival was 19 months and the two-year survival rate was 41%. Survival was significantly influenced by treatment method and radiation dose when measured by univariate analysis; median survival and the two-year survival rate was 29 months and 63% after radio-chemotherapy, while 13.5 month and 29% after radiotherapy alone (p= 0.027), and 22 months and 49% with doses of 50 Gy or more, but 12.5 months and 13% with doses less than 50 Gy (p=0.009). However, statistical significance was lost in multivariate analysis. These results might suggest the short-term efficacy of radio-chemotherapy, however, cautious observation is needed to confirm long-term effects.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

