<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JSLS</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JSLS</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jsls</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jsls</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSLS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JSLS : Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1086-8089</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1938-3797</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Miami, FL</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9876753</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3015295</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Scientific Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Post-Laparoscopic Vomiting in Females versus Males: Comparison of Prophylactic Antiemetic Action of Ondansetron versus Metoclopramide</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dabbous</surname><given-names>Aliya</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Itani</surname><given-names>Mohammad</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kawas</surname><given-names>Nicole</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Karam</surname><given-names>Violette</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aouad</surname><given-names>Marie</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baraka</surname><given-names>Anis</given-names></name><degrees>MD, FRCA</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khoury</surname><given-names>Samar Jabbour</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Khoury</surname><given-names>Ghattas</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><aff>Departments of Anesthesiology and Surgery, American University of Beirut Medical Center, Beirut - Lebanon.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Address reprint request to: Ghattas Khoury, MD, <addr-line>Associate Clinical Professor, Departement of Surgery, American University of Beirut Medical Center, Box B-37, P.O. Box 113-6044, Beirut, Lebanon</addr-line>. Fax: <fax>961-1-346946</fax></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jul-Sep</season><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 1998 by JSLS, Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>1998</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons, Inc.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="jsls-2-3-273.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background and Objectives:</title><p>The incidence of postoperative vomiting in patients undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy is compared in females versus males. The report also compares the prophylactic action of ondansetron versus metoclopramide.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>A total of 85 American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) I and II patients were enrolled in the study. Patients were divided into two groups according to sex: Group I 53 females, and Group II 32 males. After anaesthetic induction, subjects received intravenously either 4 mg ondansetron or 10 mg metoclopramide.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The incidence of vomiting as well as the frequency of emetic episodes over 24 hours were analyzed in each group using X2 analysis. Data analysis revealed a significantly higher incidence (P&#x0003c;0.05) of postoperative emesis in females 10:53 (18.9%) as compared to males 0:32 (0%). In the male group, no patient vomited postoperatively, whether prophylactic ondansetron or metoclopramide was used. While the incidence of emesis in the female group was lower (P&#x0003c;0.05) in the ondansetron group (17.6%) than the metoclopramide group (29.6%).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>These results may indicate prophylactic antiemetic therapy in female patients undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy; ondansetron appears to be superior to metoclopramide.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Laparoscopic cholecystectomy</kwd><kwd>Vomiting</kwd><kwd>Sex</kwd><kwd>Ondansetron</kwd><kwd>Metoclopramide</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) has been called the &#x0201c;Big Little Problem.&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> It can often be the main cause of prolonged hospital stay. Recent studies have shown the general incidence of postoperative emesis to be in the 20-30% range,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref></sup> while the incidence of post-laparoscopic vomiting is 35%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup> Previous investigators have reported a significantly higher incidence of vomiting after non-laparoscopic surgery in females as compared to male adults, including postmenopausal females until the age of 70 years,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref></sup> suggesting a hormonal pharmacologic basis for the susceptibility of females to vomiting. Drugs used in the prevention of postoperative vomiting include antihistaminics, anticholinergics, dopamine receptor antagonists, and 5HT3 antagonists. The purpose of this study is to compare in patients undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy the incidence of vomiting in females versus males, and to compare the prophylactic antiemetic action of ondansetron (a selective 5HT3 antagonist) versus metoclopramide (a dopamine receptor antagonist).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><p>The study was approved by our hospital research committee. Approved consent was taken from the patients preoperatively. American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) Class I and II patients scheduled for laparoscopic cholecystectomy were chosen. A total of 85 patients were enrolled in the study. The following data were collected on all patients: age, weight, history of diabetes, motion sickness, previous postoperative nausea or vomiting, as well as days since the last menstrual period (LMP) in females. Also, anaesthetic techniques, duration of surgery, and postoperative analgesia were recorded. The patients were then divided into two groups according to sex. Group I consisted of 53 females, and Group II consisted of 32 males. A random number was used to assign prospectively each patient to receive after induction of anesthesia either ondansetron 4 mg (A), or metoclopramide 10 mg (B). The staff caring for these patients were blinded to the study drug received.</p><p>All patients were premedicated with meperidine 75 mg, atropine 0.6 mg and promethazine 25 mg intramuscularly 45 minutes prior to the induction of anesthesia. After standard monitoring (EKG, noninvasive blood pressure and oximetry) was applied, all patients were induced with thiopentone 5 mg/kg, fentanyl 2 &#x003bc;g/kg and vecuronium 0.1 mg/kg. Following induction of anesthesia, patients received randomly either ondansetron 4 mg (A) or metoclopramide 10 mg (B). Anesthesia was maintained by N<sub>2</sub>0:0<sub>2</sub> mixture (2:1) and supplementary doses of vecuronium. All patients had a nasogastric tube inserted intraoperatively that was removed at the end of surgery. The duration of operation was recorded and neuromuscular blockade was reversed by a mixture of neostigmine 0.05 mg/kg and atropine 0.02 mg/kg. In the recovery room, an independent blinded observer recorded emetic episodes, vital signs, oxygen saturation and pain scores for two hours postoperatively. Drugs administered, such as narcotics or antiemetics, were also recorded.</p><p>After two hours, patients were discharged to the floor, where they were followed up to 24 hours by another independent observer; the number of patients who vomited was recorded in each group. The degree of pain and medications administered were also recorded. The incidence of emetic episodes over 24 hours were analyzed in each group, using X2 analysis at 95% confidence interval. P&#x0003c;0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>Laparoscopic cholecystectomy during the study period was more frequent in females than in males.</p><p>There were no differences between study groups with respect to age, anaesthetic technique, duration of operation, diabetes, days since the last menstrual period in females, or history of previous postoperative nausea and vomiting as well as the need for postoperative analgesics (<bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref></bold>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Demographic Data.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="none"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">FEMALE</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">MALE</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ondansetron (A)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metoclopramide (B)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ondansetron (A)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metocloramide (B)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (yrs)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.3 &#x000b1; 16.6</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3 &#x000b1; 13.4</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.1 &#x000b1; 12.7</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.5 &#x000b1; 9.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (kg)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.3 &#x000b1; 10.7</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.1 &#x000b1; 11.6</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.5 &#x000b1; 18.0</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.3 &#x000b1; 18.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">History of Motion sickness</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">History of Diabetes</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of days sinceLMP</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-45 (16 &#x000b1; 14)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-30 (13.2 &#x000b1; 9.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PREVIOUS ANAESTHESIA</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without nausea &#x00026; vomiting</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With nausea &#x00026; vomiting</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of surgery (min.)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.6 &#x000b1; 22.9</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.9 &#x000b1; 28.7</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.3 &#x000b1; 17.8</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115.8 &#x000b1; 28.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Need for analgesics</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOTAL</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>All recorded episodes of vomiting were associated with the forceful expulsion of gastric contents; none of the data represents an episode of retching. As shown in <bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref></bold>, the incidence of emesis was significantly higher in the female group than in the male group (P&#x0003c;0.05). In the male group, no patient vomited postoperatively, whether prophylactic ondansetron or metoclopramide was used. In the female group, the incidence of postoperative emesis was significantly lower (P&#x0003c;0.05) in the ondansetron group than the metoclopramide group (<bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref></bold>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Incidence of Vomiting.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="none"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Number</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vomiting</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Vomiting</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Males</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Incidence of Vomiting.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="none"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Females</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Number</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vomiting</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Vomiting</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ondansetron (A)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metoclopramide (B)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The present study shows in patients undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy that females have a significantly higher incidence of postoperative vomiting than males. This finding confirms the gender difference that exists between adult males and females below the age of 70 years, that was published many years ago by Bellville<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> in patients undergoing non-laparoscopic surgery under general anesthesia. Variations in serum gonadotropin (or other hormonal) levels may be a factor in the higher incidence of postoperative vomiting in females. Gonadotropin level is known to rise at menopause for several years before falling, which coincides with the age of 70 years when the gonadotropin level falls. At this age, the incidence of vomiting in females approaches that seen in males.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> In males, our report shows that the incidence and severity of vomiting is low, whether metoclopramide or ondansetron is used as a prophylactic antiemetic. However, in females, where there is a higher incidence of vomiting, prophylactic administration of ondansetron appears to be superior to metoclopramide.</p><p>The low incidence of vomiting in the present study, as compared to previous studies, may be attributed to the fact that we considered only patients who vomited, and did not include nausea, which can be subjective. Also, our patients were premedicated with promethazine and atropine. Atropine premedication has been shown to decrease the incidence of vomiting,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref></sup> and promethazine (an antihistaminic with both antidopaminergic and antimuscarinic action) has been also shown to decrease the incidence of postoperative vomiting.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></sup></p><p>Postoperative vomiting is multifactorial in origin; both the type of anesthesia and surgery, duration of surgery, along with postoperative pain or analgesic (narcotics) contribute to its etiology. The mechanisms can be either central or peripheral.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref></sup> There are four major neurotransmitters which play a role in mediating the emetic response: dopaminergic, histaminergic (H1), cholinergic muscarinic and 5HT3.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref></sup> Therefore, drugs used for the prevention of postoperative vomiting are usually antihistaminics, anticholinergics, and dopamine receptor antagonists.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref></sup> However, these drugs possess clinically significant untoward side-effects (sedation, dry mouth, dysphoria and extrapyramidal symptoms) which often may limit their use, especially in ambulatory surgery.</p><p>Ondansetron, a selective antagonist of 5HT3 receptors, has been effectively used for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced emesis. Chemotherapy-induced emesis is secondary to the release 5HT3 from the shedding of the mucosa of the gut during chemotherapy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref></sup> Also, ondansetron has been shown in many recent studies to be effective for the prevention of nausea and vomiting in high risk operations such as laparoscopic surgery,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref></sup> post-strabismus repair in children<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref></sup> and gynecologic surgery,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref></sup> with little side effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref></sup> Metoclopramide, on the other hand, blocks dopamine receptors at the chemoreceptor trigger zone (CTZ); also, it increases lower esophageal sphincter tone and enhances gastric and small bowel motility.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref></sup> However, metoclopramide failed to reduce the incidence of PONV after major gynecologic surgery<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref></sup> and laparoscopic surgery.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref></sup> The short duration of action of metoclopramide may explain its lack of efficacy in preventing PONV.</p><p>The present report has shown that prophylactic ondansetron is superior to metoclopramide in patients undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy. Intra-abdominal operations are more associated with postoperative vomiting than extra-abdominal operations. Manipulations and traction on the gut during abdominal surgery discharge vagal and splanchnic afferents to the central nervous system.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref></sup> In addition to this mechanism, surgical manipulation of the intestine also induces release of 5HT3 from the enterochromaffin cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref></sup> That is why ondansetron, a selective 5HT3 antagonist, can be the antiemetic of choice following intra-abdominal surgery.</p><p>In conclusion, the incidence of post-laparoscopic cholecystectomy vomiting is significantly higher in females than in males. Because of the high incidence of vomiting in females, prophylactic antiemetic therapy may be indicated. Ondansetron prophylaxis appears to be superior to metoclopramide.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References:</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The big little problem</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg.</source>
<year>1991</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1831014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellville</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bross</surname><given-names>IDJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Howland</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Postoperative nausea and vomiting IV: factors related to postoperative nausea and vomiting</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiology.</source>
<year>1960</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>186</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13798618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beattie</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindbad</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The incidence of post-operative nausea and vomiting in women undergoing laparoscopy is influenced by the day of the menstrual cycle</article-title>. <source>CanJAnaesth.</source>
<year>1991</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>298</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahalan</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehder</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Multicenter study of general anesthesia: II. Results</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiology.</source>
<year>1990</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>262</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2405739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burtles</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pecket</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Postoperative vomiting. Some factors affecting its incidence</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth.</source>
<year>1964</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13413032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellville</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Postanesthetic nausea and vomiting</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiology.</source>
<year>1961</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>773</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13866942</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patasky</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitz</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Leckry</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Nausea and vomiting following ambulatory surgery</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg.</source>
<year>1988</year>;<volume>67</volume><issue>suppls</issue>:<fpage>163</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metter</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitz</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Nausea and vomiting after outpatient laparoscopy, incidence, impact on recovery room stay and cost</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg.</source>
<year>1987</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>S116</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watcha</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Postoperative nausea and vomiting. Its etiology treatment and prevention</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiology.</source>
<year>1992</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1609990</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dundee</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholl</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Studies of drugs given before anaesthesia. A method for the studying of their effects on postoperative vomiting and nausea</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth.</source>
<year>1962</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>527</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>535</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>PLF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Physiology of nausea and vomiting</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth.</source>
<year>1992</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>suppl</issue>):<fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>195</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madej</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of the use of dompri-done, droperidol and metoclopramide in the prevention of nausea and vomiting following major gynaecological surgery</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth.</source>
<year>1986</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>884</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2942164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Silva</surname><given-names>PHDP</given-names></name><name><surname>Darvish</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mac Donald</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The efficacy of prophylactic ondansetron, droperidol, perphenazine, and metoclopramide in the prevention of nausea and vomiting after major gynecologic surgery</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg.</source>
<year>1995</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7598243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawthorn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>PLR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The role of the abdominal visceral innervation and 5HT M receptors in vomiting induced by the cytotoxic drugs cyclophosphamide and cisplation in the Ferret</article-title>. <source>Quarterly J Experimental Physiology.</source>
<year>1988</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wetchler</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bancely</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Josly</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A double blind placebo controlled pilot study examining the effectiveness of intravenous ondan-setron in the prevention of postoperative nausea and emesis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Anesth.</source>
<year>1993</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brose</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coddry</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Ondansetron reduces the incidence and severity of poststrabismus repair vomiting in children</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg.</source>
<year>1994</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>476</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>479</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mchenzie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovac</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Conner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncalf</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Angel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of ondansetron versus placebo to prevent postoperative nausea and vomiting in women undergoing ambulatory gynecologic surgery</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiology.</source>
<year>1993</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8424561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leeser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Prevention of postoperative nausea and vomiting using ondansetron, a new selective 5HT3 receptor antagonist</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg.</source>
<year>1991</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>751</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1827966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kararia</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Ondansetron prevents postoperative nausea and vomiting in women outpatients</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg.</source>
<year>1994</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>845</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>851</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7978398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raphael</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Anti-emetic efficacy of prophylactic ondansetron in laparoscopic surgery: randomized double blind comparison with metoclopramide</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth.</source>
<year>1993</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>845</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8280551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
