<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9443097</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054314</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The effect of early versus late onset of temporal lobe epilepsy on hemispheric memory laterality: an intracarotid amobarbital procedure study.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Rehabilitation Psychology, Taegu University, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>1997</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><abstract><p>Thirty-three temporal lobe epilepsy (TLE) patients, 19 left TLE and 14 right TLE, underwent an intracarotid amobarbital procedure. For each patient, hemispheric memory laterality was determined by measuring the relative magnitude of recognition memory following left versus right hemisphere injection of sodium amobarbital. The patients were divided into early and late seizure onset groups, based on the median age (13 yrs) of seizure onset of the total sample. Early-onset left TLE was associated with a greater tendency toward right hemispheric representation of both verbal and visual memory compared with late-onset left TLE. Early-onset right TLE was associated with a greater tendency toward left hemispheric representation of visual, but not verbal, memory compared with late-onset right TLE. These findings indicate that interhemispheric plasticity for memory is greater in early than in late life, bidirectional, and at least partially material-specific.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

