<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11068988</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054679</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of prednisolone on eosinophils, IL-5, eosinophil cationic protein, EG2+ eosinophils, and nitric oxide metabolites in the sputum of patients with exacerbated asthma.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>I. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>Y. I.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K. Y.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. U.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Internal Medicine, Seonam University College of Medicine, Namwon, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2000</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>528</lpage><abstract><p>Corticosteroids are considered to be one of the most effective medicine for asthma by suppressing airway inflammation. This study was carried out to investigate the effects of prednisolone in the sputum of exacerbated asthmatics. Clinical severity, cell differentials, levels of interleukin (IL)-5, eosinophil cationic protein (ECP), EG2+ eosinophils, and nitric oxide (NO) metabolites were measured. Sputum was examined 2 weeks apart in 13 exacerbated asthmatics before and after prednisolone treatment, and once in 12 stable asthmatics. We used a sandwich ELISA for IL-5, fluoroimmunoassay for ECP, immunohistochemical staining for EG2+ eosinophils, a NO metabolites assay using modified Griess reaction. Exacerbated asthmatics, in comparison with stable asthmatics, had significantly higher proportion of eosinophils, higher level of ECP, higher percentage of EG2+ eosinophils, and NO metabolites. Exacerbated asthmatics after treatment with prednisolone had reduced the proportions of eosinophils, reduced level of IL-5, ECP and percentage of EG2+ eosinophils. FEV1 was correlated with the proportion of eosinophils, ECP, and IL-5 respectively. These findings suggest that prednisolone is considered to be effective medicine for asthma by suppressing eosinophil activation through IL-5.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

