<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10642935</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054446</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Detection and typing of human papillomavirus DNA by PCR using consensus primers in various cervical lesions of Korean women.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><email>tshwang@dragon.inha.ac.kr</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Pathology, Inha University College of Medicine, Inchon, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>1999</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><abstract><p>The association between cervical cancers and human papillomavirus (HPV) is now well established. To estimate the extent of infection with common HPVs among Korean women, we have examined 224 cervical scrapes of various cervical lesions. Detection and typing of HPVs were done by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using consensus primers followed by restriction enzyme digestion and PCR using type-specific primers. The prevalence of total HPV infection in patients with cervical intraepithelial neoplasia (CIN) and cervical cancer were significantly higher than those in healthy women and patients with atypical squamous cells of undetermined significance (ASCUS). HPV typing in 41 invasive carcinomas of the cervix revealed the prevalence of HPV 16 in 15 cases, followed by HPV 58, 18, 33, 31, 52 and 35. The distribution pattern of HPV types in CIN were not much different from carcinomas. HPV types except HPV 18 had a tendency to show higher prevalence in high-grade squamous intraepithelial lesion (HSIL) than low-grade squamous intraepithelial lesions (LSIL), however, HPV 18 was detected in LSIL but not in HSIL. HPV 18 tended to have the worse clinical stage, although it was not statistically significant. These findings suggest the importance of HPV typing other than HPV 16 and 18 and a different clinicopathologic significance of HPV 18.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

