<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10719814</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054586</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Foot screening technique in a diabetic population.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><email>jbshinlim@netsgo.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seong</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2000</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><abstract><p>Foot complications are a well known factor which contribute to the morbidity of diabetes and increases the chance of amputation. A total of 126 consecutive diabetic patients were evaluated by diabetic foot screening. Forty-one patients showed an impaired protective sense when tested with Semmes-Weinstein monofilament 5.07 (10 g), and 92% of them showed peripheral polyneuropathy in nerve conduction study (NCS). The mean vibration score of the Rydel-Seiffer graduated tuning fork in patients with peripheral polyneuropathy in nerve conduction (NCV) study was 5.38+/-2.0, which was significantly different from that of patients without polyneuropathy in NCS. Among the deformities identified on examination, callus, corn, and hallux valgus were the greatest. While checking the ankle/ brachial index (ABI), we also evaluated the integrity of vasculature in the lower extremities. After extensive evaluation, we classified the patients into eight groups (category 0,1,2,3,4A,4B,5,6). The result of this study suggested that the Semmes-Weinstein monofilament test, Rydel-Seiffer graduated tuning fork test, and checking the ankle/brachial index were simple techniques for evaluating pathologic change in the diabetic foot by office screening, and that this screening based on treatment-oriented classification helps to reduce pedal complications in a diabetic population.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

