<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7576291</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054132</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Preoperative chemoradiotherapy for locoregional esophageal cancer: preliminary report.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>E. K.</given-names></name></contrib><etal/></contrib-group><aff>Department of Medicine, College of Medicine, University of Ulsan, Seoul, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>1995</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><abstract><p>Conventional treatment of esophageal cancer with surgery or radiation alone has afforded few long-term survivors. In order to improve outcome and determine the efficacy of a combined modality approach, this prospective study was performed. Between May 1993 and August 1994, 27 patients with loco-regional squamous cell carcinoma of the esophagus were treated with 2 courses of combined fluorouracil(1000mg per square meter of body-surface area daily for 5 days) and cisplatin(60mg per square meter on the first day)(D1 and D29) plus 48Gy of radiation therapy(RT) over 4 weeks. A transhiatal esophagectomy was planned 3-4 weeks after chemoradiotherapy. Twenty-seven patients completed a full course of therapy. Clinical response was evaluable in 26 patients: 22 patients showed improvement and relief from dysphagia, 2 patients stable disease, and 2 patients progression. One patient died of sepsis 1 week after completion of chemoradiotherapy and was excluded from the analysis. Ten patients underwent operation after chemoradiation. Of them, 5 showed complete histologic response. One of the complete responders died of recurred disease 8.5months after operation, the other 2 patients died of sudden death, and sepsis from wound deheiscence 7 days after operation, respectively. Nine patients refused operation because of excellent relief of their dysphagia and 6 patients were denied because of disease progression(2), fear of operations(2), old age and family member's disapprovement(1), and underlying liver cirrhosis(1). The last one patient was awaiting for operation. Of 13 patients who refused or denied operation, 6 patients finished further chemotherapy and radiatherapy(external radiation 1200 cGy+intracavitary radiation 900 cGy, 2 cycles of 5FU+cisplatin). This intensive preoperative chemoradiotherapy is feasible, and allows for a high rate of resectability and a high rate of complete pathologic response in a locoregional esophageal cancer. Toxicity is considerable but manageable. This study warrants further investigation.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

