<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9250914</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054295</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Changes in arterial blood PO2, PCO2, and pH
                    during deep hypothermic circulatory arrest in adults.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Anesthesiology, Hallym University Medical Center, Seoul,
                    Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>1997</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><abstract><p>Safe limits of time and temperature during sleep hypothermic
                        circulatory arrest (DHCA) still remain controversial. Furthermore,
                        continuous changes of PaO2, PaCO2, and pH have never been measured during
                        DHCA in humans. Continuous intraarterial blood gas (CIABG) monitoring is a
                        new technology allowing us to study chronological changes occurring due to
                        metabolism during DHCA. When the patients' temperature reached 18
                        approximately 20 degrees C following establishment of cardiopulmonary bypass
                        (CPB), circulatory arrest was initiated. After a 20-minute period of DHCA,
                        reperfusion commenced with 18 degree C blood. We continuously monitored
                        PaO2, PaCO2, and pH immediately before, during and following DHCA. Data was
                        analyzed by Student's t-test. PaO2, PaCO2, and pH of pre- and 5 minutes post
                        DHCA were not significantly different from each other. However, during DHCA,
                        the PaO2 was significantly decreased from 229 +/- 34 to 30 +/- 23 mmHg at
                        20-minute intervals. But the PaCO2 increased significantly after 20 minutes
                        of circulatory arrest from 34 +/- 5 to 42 +/- 6 mmHg. However, the pH did
                        not change significantly over the 20-minute period. The PaO2 level after 20
                        minutes is much lower than before DHCA, it would be well tolerated in
                        normothermic adults. The PO2 level in the brain may be even lower given its
                        high metabolic rate. So measuring arterial PO2 continuously during DHCA may
                        provide a surrogate method for determining maximum safe time under DHCA for
                        adults.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

