<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9886171</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054538</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fanconi anemia screening by diepoxybutane and mitomicin C tests in Korean children with bone marrow failure syndromes.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kook</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><email>hoonkook@chonnam.chonnam.ac.kr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>W. P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ryang</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Pediatrics, Chonnam National University Medical School, Research Institute of Medical Sciences, Kwangju, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><abstract><p>Fanconi anemia (FA) is an autosomal recessive disorder of progressive bone marrow failure in patients with congenital malformations. FA is different from acquired aplastic anemia (AA) in terms of the natural course and treatment options. As the frequency of FA is unknown in Korea, we conducted screening tests using DNA clastogenic agents, diepoxybutane (DEB) and mitomicin C (MMC) in southwestern Korea. Forty-three children with AA or other bone marrow failure syndromes and siblings of known FA were evaluated. Six patients with AA (6/24=25.0%) and a 2-month-old patient with myelodysplastic syndrome were found to have increased chromosomal breakage to both DEB and MMC, confirming the diagnosis of FA. No overlap in chromosomal breakage to both agents was found between the FA group and non-FA group. The frequency of FA in this study, much higher than those of previous studies in Korea which did not incorporate the above tests, was similar to that of other countries. DEB and MMC tests were readily feasible and useful in screening FA in patients with AA as well as other bone marrow failure syndromes. A nation-wide screening and registry for FA should be initiated since FA requires different therapeutic and management options from idiopathic AA.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

