<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8305141</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3053713</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Botulinum a toxin treatment of hemifacial spasm and blepharospasm.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Neurology, Keimyung University School of Medicine, Taegu, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>1993</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>334</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><abstract><p>We studied the effects of botulinum A toxin in 101 patients with hemifacial spasm and 11 patients with blepharospasm in an open trial and double blind manner. All patients in the open trial and 6 patients in the double blind trial improved after the first injection of botulinum toxin. There was no improvement with placebo. The peak effect ranged from one to 6 days after injection and mean peak effect was 3.6 days in blepharospasm, and 4 days in hemifacial spasm. Of 144 treatments, 98.6% had excellent results, (below grade I). The duration of beneficial effect ranged 11 to 40 weeks (mean 16.5 weeks) in hemifacial spasm and 9 to 30 weeks (mean 14.2 weeks) in blepharospasm. Complications were encountered in 63.4% in hemifacial spasm and 72.7% in blepharospasm. The common side effects were dry eyes, mouth droop, ptosis and lid edema in order of frequency. These side effects were mild and resolved spontaneously in 1 to 3 weeks. Botulinum A toxin therapy is effective and convenient, and the treatment of choice for patients with hemifacial spasm and blepharospasm.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

