<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8835765</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3053930</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Q-switched ruby laser in the treatment of nevus of Ota.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ro</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y. T.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Dermatology, Hanyang University, College of Medicine, Kuri Hospital, Kyunggido, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><abstract><p>The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of Q-switched ruby laser in the treatment of nevus of Ota, a pigmented lesion on the face. The Q-switched ruby laser has been shown to remove tattoos without scarring. With this in mind, the nevus of Ota with pigmented cells in the dermis could be effectively treated with Q-switched ruby laser. Eighty patients (19 men, and 61 women) with nevus of Ota on the face were enlisted to be tested in evaluating the efficiency of Q-switched ruby laser therapy. The age of patients ranged from 1 to 62 years. The energy fluence used varied from 6 to 8.5 J/cm2. Treatment intervals ranged from 4 to 16 weeks, and the number of treatment sessions varied between 1 to 9 visits. During a 2-year follow-up period, more than fifty percent removal of nevus-pigment was noted in 64 of the 80 patients. Transient hyperpigmentation was noted in 32 patients lasting for 2 to 6 months after treatment; transient hypopigmentation was seen in 3 cases which recovered within one year. No patients had permanent textural or pigmentary changes or scarring. Q-switched ruby laser therapy appears to be an effective and safe modality for the treatment of nevus of Ota.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

