<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Clin Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Clinical Pharmacology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6904</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11228592</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">32172</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1472-6904-1-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6904-1-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Control Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Risk of upper gastrointestinal bleeding and perforation associated 
with low-dose aspirin as plain and enteric-coated formulations</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Abajo</surname><given-names>Francisco J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>fabajo@agemed.es</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>Luis A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>lagarcia@ceife.es</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Divisi&#x000f3;n de Farmacoepidemiolog&#x000ed;a y Farmacovigilancia, 
Agencia Espa&#x000f1;ola del Medicamento, Madrid, Spain</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Centro Espa&#x000f1;ol de Investigaci&#x000f3;n 
Farmacoepidemiol&#x000f3;gica, Madrid, Spain</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2001</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6904/1/1"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2000</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2001</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2001 de Abajo and Garc&#x000ed;a Rodr&#x000ed;guez; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article: verbatim copying and redistribution of this article are permitted in all media for any purpose, provided this notice is preserved along with the article's original URL.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2001</copyright-year><copyright-holder>de Abajo and Garc&#x000ed;a Rodr&#x000ed;guez; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article: verbatim copying and redistribution of this article are permitted in all media for any purpose, provided this notice is preserved along with the article's original URL.</copyright-holder></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The use of low-dose aspirin has been reported to be associated with an 
increased risk of upper gastrointestinal complications (UGIC). The coating of 
aspirin has been proposed as an approach to reduce such a risk. To test this 
hypothesis, we carried out a population based case-control study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>We identified incident cases of UGIC (bleeding or perforation) aged 40 to 79 
years between April 1993 to October 1998 registered in the General Practice 
Research Database. Controls were selected randomly from the source population. 
Adjusted estimates of relative risk (RR) associated with current use of aspirin 
as compared to non use were computed using unconditional logistic 
regression.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We identified 2,105 cases of UGIC and selected 11,500 controls. Among them, 
287 (13.6%) cases and 837 (7.3%) controls were exposed to aspirin, resulting in 
an adjusted RR of 2.0 (1.7-2.3). No clear dose-effect was found within the 
range of 75-300 mg. The RR associated with enteric-coated formulations (2.3, 
1.6-3.2) was similar to the one of plain aspirin (1.9, 1.6-2.3), and no 
difference was observed depending on the site. The first two months of 
treatment was the period of greater risk (RR= 4.5, 2.9-7.1). The concomitant 
use of aspirin with high-dose NSAIDs greatly increased the risk of UGIC (13.3, 
8.5-20.9) while no interaction was apparent with low-medium doses (2.2, 
1.0-4.6).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Low-dose aspirin increases by twofold the risk of UGIC in the general 
population and its coating does not modify the effect. Concomitant use of 
low-dose aspirin and NSAIDs at high doses put patients at a specially high risk 
of UGIC.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Upper gastrointestinal complications (UGIC) are the major risk associated 
with aspirin use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. As with non-aspirin non-steroidal 
antiinflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), dose appears to be a major determinant, but 
even with low (300/325 mg) or very low doses (75 mg) a residual amount of risk 
seems to persist [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p><p>It has been postulated that enteric-coated formulations of aspirin, designed 
to resist the disintegration in acid environment and pass by the stomach 
without dissolution, may have an impact in reducing the risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">
5</xref>]. The idea behind this strategy is grounded on the belief that gastric 
damage caused by aspirin is mainly due to a local effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">
6</xref>]. Results from several endoscopic studies carried out in healthy 
volunteers supported this hypothesis showing that enteric-coated aspirin caused 
less gastric erosion and microbleeding than regular formulations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. However, it 
is known that these lesions are not good predictors of major upper 
gastrointestinal complications. From an epidemiological point of view the 
question is a matter of controversy as well. Two case-control studies have 
reported data on the effect of enteric-coated preparations on upper 
gastrointestinal bleeding, yielding to apparently opposite results. Weil et al 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] concluded that "enteric-coated aspirin ... may be 
free of risk" after estimating an odds ratio of 1.6 but with a wide 95% 
confidence interval (0.5-4.9). On the other hand, Kelly et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">
4</xref>] found a risk of 2.6 (95% confidence interval, 1.4-5.3) which was 
essentially similar to the one estimated for plain aspirin when the effect of 
dose was taken into account.</p><p>In order to shed some light onto this issue and to estimate the specific 
aspirin-related risk of upper gastrointestinal bleeding and perforation, its 
relation with dose and duration of treatment, as well as the potential 
interaction between aspirin and other drugs (particularly NSAIDs), we used data 
from a case-control study designed to estimate risks of UGIC associated with 
drugs and other factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Subjects and methods</title><p>A case-control study was carried out using data from the UK-based General 
Practice Research Database. This database has been described extensively 
elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Briefly, it contains details of 
patients' demographics, medical diagnosis, referrals to consultants and 
hospitals, and prescriptions. The accuracy and completeness of these data have 
been validated in previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p><sec><title>Case definition and ascertainment</title><p>The source population was encompassed by patients aged 40 to 79 years 
between April 1993 and October 1998, with at least 2 years' enrollment with 
their general practitioner. Patients with cancer, oesophageal varices, 
Mallory-Weiss disease, alcoholism, liver disease, or coagulopathies were 
excluded. We identified incident cases of upper gastrointestinal bleeding or 
perforation, and reviewed their computerised profiles. The date of first 
diagnosis was used as the index date. Patients with any of the exclusion 
criteria mentioned above in the 2 months after index date, those discharged 
from hospital in the two previous weeks, and subjects with the source of the 
bleed/perforation in the oesophagus or lower gastrointestinal tract were not 
retained as cases. A patient was considered a case of UGIC when no exclusion 
criterion was found, and the specific site of bleed/perforation was located in 
the stomach or duodenum or the clinical diagnosis was peptic ulcer. Only 
patients referred to a specialist or admitted to hospital were retained as 
cases. To confirm the validity of our computer-based case ascertainment, we 
requested from the general practitioners a copy of the paper-based records of 
100 randomly sampled patients. We received records for 99 patients of which 98 
were confirmed as cases. We therefore decided to study all patients classified 
as cases on the basis of the review of computerised information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Patients with a fatal outcome within a month of the 
beginning of the episode were considered as fatal cases.</p></sec><sec><title>Control selection</title><p>All patients from the source population were assigned a random date during 
the study period. If such random date fell within his/her observation period, 
that patient was considered eligible as control. From this population we 
randomly selected 11,500 patients frequency-matched with cases for age 
(interval of 1 year), sex and calendar year. We applied to controls the same 
exclusion criteria used for cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Exposure definition</title><p>We defined patients as "current users" when the supply of a prescription for 
aspirin lasted until the index date or ended within the period of 30 days 
before index date, "recent users" when the supply ended between 31 to 180 days 
before the index date, "past users" if the supply ended more than 180 days 
before and "non-users" if no prescription was ever recorded before the index 
date. Among current and recent use categories we also explored narrower 
exposure windows. Among current users, we studied the effect of dose, treatment 
duration and formulation of aspirin. For the estimation of daily dose two 
different approaches were followed: 1) the dose instructed by the general 
practitioner and 2) the average dose calculated by dividing the number of 
tablets supplied (provided that at least three prescriptions were written 
before index date) over the treatment period. Although a wide range of 
different strengths of low-dose aspirin are available in the U.K., the most 
widely used by general practitioners are 75 mg and 300 mg. A number of 
physicians prescribed a 300 mg tablet to be taken in alternate days; from a 
risk perspective, we considered such patients closer to the 300 mg group and 
were included in this category. Duration of treatment was calculated by adding 
up the time corresponding to consecutive prescriptions of aspirin before the 
index date, considering two prescriptions as consecutive when the interval 
between the end of supply of one prescription and the start of the next one was 
less than 120 days (this interval was meant to make a clear separation between 
those patients actually starting a new treatment course with aspirin from those 
having a poor compliance). Further, among current users we distinguished 
between those patients whose aspirin treatment course was the first ever 
recorded in the GPRD over the study period, and those with a previous (or 
distant) use. The indication of aspirin was studied among current users in two 
random samples of 100 subjects each among cases and controls. All manual review 
was done blinded to the status of each patient (case or control).</p><p>We also evaluated the exposure to other drugs such as non-aspirin NSAIDs, 
paracetamol, steroids, anticoagulants, selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors 
and antiulcer drugs (antacids, H2-blockers and omeprazol). Among current users 
of NSAIDs, we distinguished between low-medium and high daily doses using the 
cut-off limits described in previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis</title><p>We used unconditional logistic regression to compute adjusted estimates of 
relative risk and 95% confidence intervals (95% CI) for current use of aspirin 
as compared to non-use. Two different outcomes were studied: upper 
gastrointestinal bleeding (UGIB) and perforation. The location of the lesion 
was considered in the analysis when number of cases allowed for that. Also, we 
examined separately fatal cases. The following covariates were studied as 
potential confounders: history of upper gastrointestinal disorder (dyspepsia, 
peptic ulcer, upper gastrointestinal bleeding/perforation), smoking status 
(information available for 84% of study population), alcohol consumption 
(information available for 58% of study population), and current use of drugs 
related with an increased risk of upper gastrointestinal complications: 
non-aspirin NSAIDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], anticoagulants, corticosteroids 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], high-dose (&#x0003e; 2 grams) paracetamol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] and selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The matching factors were included in the model as well. 
We studied the interaction between aspirin and other drugs by forming one 
single term in the model for the joint effect. The relative excess risk due to 
interaction (RERI) was used as a measure of interaction and was calculated as: 
Relative risk (current joint use of "a" and "b")-relative risk (current use of 
"a" only)- relative risk (current use of "b" only) + 1, being "a" and "b" the 
factors whose interaction is being studied [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We identified 1,833 cases of upper gastrointestinal bleeding and 272 cases 
of perforation. Cases and controls did not differ by age group and sex (table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Among bleeding cases, the lesion was located at the 
stomach in 764 (42%) and the duodenum in 811 (44%), remaining unspecified in 
258 (14%); 4.1% of bleeding cases were fatal. Among perforation cases, 36 (13%) 
were located in the stomach and 236 (87%) in the duodenum with a case-fatality 
rate of 21.0 %. Two hundred eighty seven cases (13.6%) of upper 
gastrointestinal bleeding (n= 248; 13.5%) or perforation (n= 39; 14.3%) were 
current users of aspirin, as compared to 837 current users among controls 
(7.3%) yielding to an adjusted RR of 2.0 (95% CI: 1.7-2.3) for all cases (table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). No material difference was found when upper 
gastrointestinal bleeding (2.0, 1.7-2.4) and perforation (1.7, 1.2-2.6) were 
considered as separate outcomes, or when location was taken into account 
(gastric 2.0, 1.6-2.5; duodenal 1.7, 1.4-2.1). The risk was essentially the 
same either for fatal (1.8, 1.1-2.9) or nonfatal (2.0, 1.7-2.4) cases. No 
modification of the relative risk estimates was observed by sex (males, 2.0 
(1.6-2.4); females, 2.0 (1.5-2.6). The relative risks by age group were as 
follows: 40-59 years, 2.4 (1.3-4.4); 60-69 years, 2.3 (1.8-3.1); 70-79 years, 
1.8 (1.4-2.2).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of study population by sex and age group</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Cases</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
Controls</bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>(N=2,105)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
(N=11,500)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Gender</bold></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold>Male</bold></td><td align="left">1,327 (63.0 
%)</td><td align="left">7,167 (62.3 %)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Age group</bold></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold>40-59</bold></td><td align="left">667 (31.7 
%)</td><td align="left">3,766 (32.8%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold>60-69</bold></td><td align="left">627 (29.8 
%)</td><td align="left">3,392 (29.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold>70-79</bold></td><td align="left">811 (38.5 
%)</td><td align="left">4,342 (37.8 %)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Risk of UGIB and perforation associated with aspirin use</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>All cases</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
Controls</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Adjusted RR<sup>*</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>(N=2,105)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
(N=11,500)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>(95%CI)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Non-use</bold></td><td align="left">1,696</td><td align="left">10,157</td><td align="left">1 (reference)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Current use (1-30)</bold></td><td align="left">287</td><td align="left">837</td><td align="left">2.0 (1.7-2.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold><italic>Use within 1-7</italic></bold></td><td align="left"><italic>259</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>771</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>2.0 (1.7-2.3)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold><italic>days time window</italic></bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold><italic>Use within 8-30</italic></bold></td><td align="left"><italic>28</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>66</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>2.3 (1.4-3.7)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold><italic>days time window</italic></bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Recent use (31-180)</bold></td><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">123</td><td align="left">1.5 (1.0-2.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold><italic>Use within 31-60</italic></bold></td><td align="left"><italic>14</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>45</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>1.7 (0.9-3.3)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold><italic>days time window</italic></bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold><italic>Use within 61-180</italic></bold></td><td align="left"><italic>23</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>78</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>1.5 (0.9-2.5)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold><italic>days time window</italic></bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Past use (&#x0003e;180)</bold></td><td align="left">85</td><td align="left">383</td><td align="left">1.1 (0.8-1.4)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup> Adjusted for sex, age, calendar year, antecedents of 
gastrointestinal disorders, smoking status, alcohol consumption and use of 
NSAIDs, anticoagulants, steroids, SSRIs and paracetamol.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The indications for aspirin among a random sample of 100 cases were 
secondary prevention of coronary heart disease (47), secondary prevention of 
cerebrovascular ischaemic events (36), peripheral vascular disease (5), other 
cardiovascular disease (2), and analgesia (2). For the remainder (8) the 
indication was not unequivocally identified from the patient profiles. The 
distribution of indications in a random sample of 100 controls was 50, 30, 5, 
3, 2 and 10, respectively.</p><p>Seventy-five mg was the daily dose most frequently prescribed (48%) in 
controls, followed by 150 mg (27%), 300/325 mg (19%), and more than 325 mg 
(6%). No dose-effect relation was observed with aspirin within the 75-300 mg 
range according to the instructions written by the general practitioner (table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). This remained true when the analysis was restricted 
to a specific lesion (either bleeding or perforation) or to a specific location 
(either gastric or duodenal) (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional material: Appendix 1</xref>). Results did 
not materially change when only patients without any antecedents of 
gastrointestinal disorders (including dyspepsia) were considered (see 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">additional material: Appendix 2</xref>), or when we controlled for use of antiulcer 
drugs. For 149 patients (45 (16%) cases and 104 (12%) controls) among current 
users the average daily dose estimated through the number of tablets supplied 
exceeded the cut-off values established to separate different dose categories 
(112, 225 and 400 mg). The replacement of the "instructed dose" by the average 
dose did not make a significant change (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Nor did 
the restriction of the analysis to patients with consistent data for both 
methods of aspirin dose assessment.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Relation between aspirin dose and risk of UGIB and perforation 
among current users as compared to non-use</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>All cases</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
Controls</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Adjusted RR<sup>*</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>(N=2,105)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
(N=11,500)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>(95%CI)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Daily dose as instructed</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;75 mg</td><td align="left">141</td><td align="left">420</td><td align="left">1.9 (1.6-2.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;150 mg</td><td align="left">84</td><td align="left">245</td><td align="left">2.0 (1.5-2.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;300 mg$</td><td align="left">54</td><td align="left">163</td><td align="left">2.0 (1.4-2.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;600 + mg</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">4.0 (1.4-11.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Average daily dose +</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x0003c;50 mg (irregular use)</td><td align="left">
4</td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">0.7 (0.2-2.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;51-111</td><td align="left">135</td><td align="left">383</td><td align="left">2.1 (1.7-2.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;112-225</td><td align="left">91</td><td align="left">258</td><td align="left">1.9 (1.5-2.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;226-400</td><td align="left">48</td><td align="left">151</td><td align="left">2.0 (1.4-2.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x0003e; 400</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">3.1 (1.3-7.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup> Adjusted for sex, age, calendar year, antecedents of 
gastrointestinal disorders, smoking status, alcohol consumption and use of 
NSAIDs, anticoagulants, steroids, SSRIs and paracetamol. Additional adjustment 
for use of antiulcer drugs (antacids, H2-blockers and omeprazol) did not change 
the estimates. $ Five cases and three controls taking 300 mg in alternate days 
were included in this category. Assigning those patients to the 150-mg category 
hardly modified the results. + Calculated by dividing the number of tablets 
supplied over the treatment period. For 161 patients (51 (18%) cases and 110 
(13%) controls) less than 3 prescriptions of aspirin were written, therefore 
the instructed dose was still considered in these patients.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Enteric-coated aspirin was associated with a risk of UGIC (RR of 2.3, 
1.6-3.2) similar to the one of plain aspirin (1.9, 1.6-2.3). Estimates hardly 
changed when analysing separately bleeding and perforation, or gastric and 
duodenal sites (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). As enteric-coated aspirin could 
have been prescribed preferentially for those patients at greater risk of 
gastrointestinal damage, we performed a sub-analysis including only individuals 
without any antecedent of upper gastrointestinal disorder: the relative risk 
estimate for enteric-coated aspirin was 2.7 (1.7-4.2) and the one for plain 
aspirin was 2.2 (1.8-2.8). The results did not change when additional 
adjustment for antiulcer drugs use was performed. Estimates of risk associated 
with aspirin formulation and stratified by dose are shown in table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>. We observed a dose-response starting at 300 mg with plain 
aspirin but could not find a similar pattern with enteric-coated.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Risk of UGIB and perforation associated with aspirin use according 
to location, type of lesion and aspirin formulation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Adjusted<sup>*</sup>
 RR (95% CI)</bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left"><bold>All cases</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>UGIB</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Perforation</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>All sites</bold></td><td align="left">Plain</td><td align="left">1.9 (1.6-2.3)</td><td align="left">2.0 (1.6-2.4)</td><td align="left">1.6 (1.1-2.5)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Coated</td><td align="left">2.3 (1.6-3.2)</td><td align="left">2.2 (1.5-3.2)</td><td align="left">2.4 (1.1-5.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Gastric</bold></td><td align="left">Plain</td><td align="left">2.0 (1.5-2.5)</td><td align="left">2.0 (1.6-2.6)</td><td align="left">- $</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Coated</td><td align="left">2.2 (1.4-3.6)</td><td align="left">2.3 (1.4-3.8)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Duodenal</bold></td><td align="left">Plain</td><td align="left">1.6 (1.3-2.1)</td><td align="left">1.5 (1.2-2.0)</td><td align="left">1.8 (1.1-2.8)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Coated</td><td align="left">2.2 (1.4-3.4)</td><td align="left">1.9 (1.1-3.2)</td><td align="left">2.9<sup>#</sup> 
(1.4-6.1)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup> Adjusted for sex, age, calendar year, antecedents of 
gastrointestinal disorders, smoking status, alcohol consumption and use of 
NSAIDs, anticoagulants, steroids, SSRIs and paracetamol $ Only 3 cases of 
gastric perforation exposed to plain aspirin and none to coated aspirin # Based 
on 9 exposed cases and 142 controls</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Effect of aspirin formulation and dose on risk of UGIB and 
perforation among current users as compared to non-use</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>All cases</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
Controls</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Adjusted RR<sup>*</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>(N=2,105)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
(N=11,500)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>(95%CI)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4"><bold>Formulation/dose as instructed</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold>Plain</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02264; 150 mg</td><td align="left">201</td><td align="left">626</td><td align="left">1.9 (1.6-2.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;300 + mg</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">69</td><td align="left">2.6 (1.6-4.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold>Enteric-coated</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02264; 150 mg</td><td align="left">24</td><td align="left">39</td><td align="left">3.5 (2.0-6.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;300 + mg</td><td align="left">32</td><td align="left">103</td><td align="left">1.8 (1.2-2.8)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup> Adjusted for sex, age, calendar year, antecedents of 
gastrointestinal disorders, smoking status, alcohol consumption and use of 
NSAIDs, anticoagulants, steroids, SSRIs and paracetamol. Additional adjustment 
for antiulcer drugs use did not change the estimates.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>As shown in table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>, the duration of treatment had an 
impact upon the risk of upper gastrointestinal complication, being the first 
two months of use the period of greater risk (4.5, 2.9-7.1). Such a pattern was 
observed across different doses (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">7</xref>) or formulations 
of aspirin (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">additional material: Appendix 3</xref>), though it was less sharp 
within the 75 mg dose and for enteric-coated preparations. The indication for 
aspirin in those patients with shorter treatment duration (less than 2 months) 
was related to cardiovascular disorders in 88% of cases and 89 % of controls. 
Among short-term users, those who used aspirin for the first time appeared to 
be at the same relative risk as those with a previous non-consecutive 
prescription of aspirin ("distant use") (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). The 
initial increased risk was clearly observed for bleeding lesions and less 
markedly for perforation (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">additional material: Appendix 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Effect of duration of treatment with aspirin on the risk of UGIB 
and perforation among current users as compared to non-use</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>All cases</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
Controls</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Adjusted RR<sup>*</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>(N=2,105)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
(N=11,500)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>(95%CI)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Days of treatment</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>(consecutive prescriptions)</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1-60 (all users)</td><td align="left">40</td><td align="left">52</td><td align="left">4.5 (2.9-7.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;First-ever users</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">32</td><td align="left">4.6 (2.7-8.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;Distant users</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">4.2 (2.0-8.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;61-180</td><td align="left">34</td><td align="left">71</td><td align="left">2.7 (1.7-4.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;181-730</td><td align="left">96</td><td align="left">286</td><td align="left">1.9 (1.5-2.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x0003e;730</td><td align="left">117</td><td align="left">428</td><td align="left">1.6 (1.3-2.0)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup>Adjusted for sex, age, calendar year, antecedents of 
gastrointestinal disorders, smoking status, alcohol consumption and use of 
NSAIDs, anticoagulants, steroids, SSRIs and paracetamol. Additional adjustment 
for antiulcer drugs use did not change the estimates.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The concomitant use of aspirin together with other non-aspirin NSAIDs at 
high dose increased substantially the risk of major UGIC (relative risk 13.3, 
8.5-20.9), far beyond the sum of their respective independent effects 
(RERI=7.9, 2.0-13.8), while no interaction was apparent when low-dose aspirin 
was taken together with NSAIDs at low-medium dose (RR of 2.2, 1.0-4.6) (table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T8">8</xref>). The interaction appeared to be greater for 
perforation (RR=30.3, 15.0-61.3; RERI=23.1, 2.2-44.2) than for bleeding 
(RR=10.8, 6.6-17.5; RERI= 5.7, 0.5-10.9). Among bleeding lesions no difference 
was found between the relative risk of the combination for those located at the 
stomach (RR=12.2, 6.8-21.9) and those located at the duodenum (14.3, 8.3-24.5). 
Both formulations of aspirin presented this interaction with high-dose NSAIDs 
(plain, 12.7 (7.7-20.8); enteric-coated, 16.6 (5.9-46.3). No relevant 
interaction beyond the sum of the independent effects was observed between 
aspirin and high-dose paracetamol (4.5, 1.9-10.9) or aspirin and steroids (1.9, 
0.9-3.8). A small interaction was observed between low-dose aspirin and 
anticoagulants (5.5, 2.4-12.7).</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The results of the present study show that the use of low-dose aspirin for 
prophylaxis of cardiovascular disorders conveys a twofold increased risk of 
upper gastrointestinal bleeding and perforation in the general population. This 
increased risk is found over different categories of age and sex. The effect of 
aspirin applies equally to gastric and duodenal sites.</p><p>We did not find a clear relation with aspirin daily dose within the range 
75-300 mg. Such a result did not change when we restricted the analysis to 
patients without any antecedent of upper gastrointestinal disorder or when we 
adjusted for use of antiulcer drugs. This reasonably excludes a potential 
selection of patients with a greater risk of UGIC to lower doses of aspirin. 
Looking for other sources of bias, we identified that in 13% of patients the 
dose instructed by the general practitioner was not consistent with the average 
daily dose calculated by counting the number of tablets supplied. We tried to 
correct this by restricting the analysis to the population having consistent 
data with both methods and by replacing the instructed dose by the average. 
Neither of those corrections yielded different results. Nevertheless, a 
suggestion of a greater risk associated with aspirin at higher doses within the 
range 75-300 mg versus lower doses was found among users of the plain 
formulation and among short-term users (first 60 days of treatment). Finally, 
although the confidence intervals for lower doses are reasonably narrow, some 
statistical uncertainty remains and a dose-effect cannot be excluded; 
therefore, the use of the lowest dose shown effective is still the best 
strategy to minimise risk.</p><p>The enteric-coated formulations appear not to protect from the 
aspirin-induced risk of upper gastrointestinal bleeding, irrespective of the 
dose, neither for gastric nor for duodenal lesions. This observation adds up to 
previous results from other investigators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Assuming 
that the coating of aspirin effectively spares the stomach from its topical 
adverse effect, such results cast doubts on the overall contribution of the 
local effect in serious bleeding lesions observed among aspirin users. Instead, 
our findings support the hypothesis that the effect of aspirin, both plain and 
enteric-coated, on upper gastrointestinal bleeding is mainly systemic mediated 
through inhibition of platelet thromboxane A<sub>2</sub> synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] and/or inhibition of protective prostaglandin synthesis in 
the gastroduodenal mucosa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. A local effect, however, 
cannot be ruled out as a relevant contributor for aspirin-induced perforation, 
as most cases were located in duodenum, and no difference or, perhaps, a 
slightly greater risk was found with the coated formulation. A preferential 
prescription of enteric-coated aspirin to patients with antecedents of 
gastrointestinal disorders does not explain our results, since enteric-coated 
aspirin users with no such antecedents present a risk similar to the one 
associated with plain aspirin.</p><p>Patients in the first two months after starting treatment with aspirin are 
at the greatest risk of presenting a major UGIC. Thereafter, the risk goes down 
and reaches a plateau at around six months. This phenomenon has been observed 
by other researchers for aspirin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] but remains 
controversial for other NSAIDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">
15</xref>]. It has been suggested that this high hazard rate at the beginning 
of treatment could be an artefact induced by the use of aspirin for early 
symptoms of peptic ulcer. This possibility can be reasonably ruled out in our 
study because almost 90% of cases who experienced bleeding or perforation early 
after starting treatment with aspirin were using it for prevention of 
cardiovascular disorders, a pattern of use identical to the one found for new 
users among controls. Another explanation argued for the decreasing risk with 
the continuation of treatment has been the "early withdrawal of population 
susceptible to damage" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. In order to explore this 
possibility we divided short-term users of aspirin (&#x0003c; 2 months) into 
"distant users" and "first-ever users", depending on the recording or not of a 
remote non-consecutive prescription for aspirin. We did not find any apparent 
difference in risk between these two groups. So, patients who stopped treatment 
with aspirin for whatever reason and then started again after a washout period 
of at least four months, presented a similar risk during the first two months 
of treatment as first-ever users. By exclusion, the duration response could be 
explained by the third mechanism postulated so far: the existence of an 
adaptation of the gastrointestinal mucosa to the toxic action of aspirin. 
According to our results, this adaptation process would take at least 2 months 
to result into clinical benefits. In striking contrast, a constant risk pattern 
has been found with non-aspirin NSAIDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. The reasons for such discrepancy are unknown and should 
be further studied. In our view, the explanation should be searched in the 
pharmacological differences of aspirin as compared to non-aspirin NSAIDs. It is 
well known that aspirin has a much greater topical adverse effect on the 
stomach lining than non-aspirin NSAIDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] and perhaps 
the adaptive process concerns mainly this mechanism of action.</p><p>The concurrent use of low-dose aspirin with high-dose NSAIDs increases the 
risk of UGIC by a factor of 13. Similar findings have been obtained by others 
for UGIB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Our results strongly suggest that the 
combination may have a particular impact on the risk of perforation (lower 
confidence interval of 15). It is important to note that the joint use of 
low-dose aspirin with high-dose NSAIDs is not unusual. In our random sample of 
11,500 controls, the prevalence of this combination was 3 per 1,000 subjects, a 
small figure in relative terms but large from a public health perspective. On 
the other hand, it is reassuring that no interaction beyond the sum of their 
respective effects was observed between aspirin and low-medium NSAIDs, aspirin 
and steroids, or aspirin and paracetamol (even when this latter was taken at 
doses higher than 2 grams a day). Although we detected a slight interaction of 
low-dose aspirin and anticoagulants, the confidence interval of the estimate is 
wide and precludes any firm conclusion.</p><p>The present study has some limitations. Aspirin prescription is 
systematically recorded in the GPRD, but its over-the-counter use is only 
recorded occasionally and this could lead to a misclassification of aspirin 
exposure. Although misclassification of exposures collected prospectively 
before the occurrence of the event of interest is usually close to 
non-differential between cases and controls, we evaluated the extent of the 
under-recording and the type of misclassification using external data from a 
recent study that analyzed the risk of peptic ulcer bleeding associated with prophylactic aspirin and was also performed in the UK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The 
authors interviewed patients aged 60 and over and asked, among other things, 
information about all prescribed and self-administered drug intake. They found 
that 27.1 % of cases and 15.9% of controls reported any use of aspirin in the 
month before (16.5% and 8.3% respectively reported a regular use). In our study 
population, the prevalence of aspirin use in the month before was 13.6% and 
7.3% (18.4% and 10.3% among the subjects aged 60 years or older). 
Interestingly, the case-control ratio of aspirin exposure for the reference 
study is 1.70, while the corresponding ratio is 1.86 in our study (1.79 for the 
older group). These figures suggest that the under-recording of OTC aspirin use 
in our study is to a major extent non-differential with respect to case status. 
We performed a sensitivity analysis assuming the worst case of a 50% 
misclassification of aspirin users. The "true" crude OR would be 2.3 instead of 
the 2.1 observed. Therefore, it seems unlikely that the underascertainment of 
OTC aspirin use could have greatly distorted the estimate of aspirin effect in 
our study. Other authors have recently reached the same conclusion for OTC 
NSAIDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. It is conceivable that the potential 
misclassification of enteric-coated preparations due to their higher price were 
less important than for the plain ones. This means that the distortion to the 
null would be weaker for the former preparations, but assuming that the 
misclassification was non-differential with respect to case status, the impact 
of such difference would be negligible. We also examined the effects of a 
differential misclassification with respect to case status and only under the 
unrealistic assumption of a strong differential misclassification selectively 
affecting the higher doses within the range 75-300 mg of plain preparations, 
could our results of lack of dose-effect and lack of protective effect of 
enteric-coated preparations be explained.</p><p>We tried to control for other potential sources of bias, including 
channelling of patients with greater risk to lower-dose or enteric-coated 
aspirin. However, as with all observational studies, unmeasured or inaccurately 
measured factors may lead to residual confounding.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Effect of duration of treatment with aspirin on the risk of UGIB 
and perforation among current users as compared to non-use by aspirin dose</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>All cases</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
Controls</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Adjusted RR<sup>*</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>(N=2,105)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
(N=11,500)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>(95%CI)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Daily dose as instructed/</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Days of treatment/</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold>75 mg</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;1-60</td><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">32</td><td align="left">3.2 (1.7-6.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;61-180</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">2.9 (1.6-5.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;181-730</td><td align="left">53</td><td align="left">166</td><td align="left">1.7 (1.2-2.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x0003e;731</td><td align="left">51</td><td align="left">185</td><td align="left">1.7 (1.3-4.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold>150 mg</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;1-60</td><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">6.6 (2.7-15.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;61-180</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">2.7 (1.2-6.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;181-730</td><td align="left">26</td><td align="left">83</td><td align="left">2.0 (1.2-3.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x0003e;730</td><td align="left">34</td><td align="left">128</td><td align="left">1.5 (1.0-2.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;<bold>300 + mg</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;1-60</td><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">6.0 (2.2-16.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;61-180</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">1.9 (0.5-7.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;181-730</td><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">2.6 (1.4-4.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x0003e;730</td><td align="left">32</td><td align="left">115</td><td align="left">1.7 (1.1-2.6)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup>Adjusted for sex, age, calendar year, antecedents of 
gastrointestinal disorders, smoking status, alcohol consumption and use of 
NSAIDs, anticoagulants, steroids, SSRIs and paracetamol.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T8"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Effect of concomitant use of aspirin and NSAIDs among current users 
as compared to non use of either drug (multiple users of NSAIDs were 
excluded).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>All cases (UGIB/Perforation)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Controls</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Adjusted RR<sup>*</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>(N=2,105)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>
(N=11,500)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>(95%CI)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Low-medium-dose NSAIDs only</td><td align="left">
83(71/12)</td><td align="left">256</td><td align="left">2.6 (2.0-3.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">High-dose<sup>#</sup> NSAIDs only</td><td align="left">254 
(202/52)</td><td align="left">413</td><td align="left">4.3 (3.6-5.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Only aspirin</td><td align="left">221 (201/20)</td><td align="left">767</td><td align="left">2.1 (1.8-2.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Aspirin + low-medium-dose NSAIDs</td><td align="left">9 
(6/3)</td><td align="left">34</td><td align="left">2.2 (1.0-4.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Aspirin + high-dose<sup>#</sup> NSAIDs</td><td align="left">57 (41/16)</td><td align="left">36</td><td align="left">13.3 
(8.5-20.9)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup>Adjusted for sex, age, calendar year, antecedents of 
gastrointestinal disorders, smoking status, alcohol consumption and use of 
anticoagulants, steroids, SSRIs and paracetamol. # High-dose NSAIDs: 
Aceclofenac &#x0003e; 100, acemetacin &#x0003e; 120, diclofenac &#x0003e; 75, etodolac 
&#x0003e; 400, fenbufen &#x0003e; 900, fenoprofen &#x0003e; 1200, flurbiprofen &#x0003e; 150, 
ibuprofen &#x0003e; 1200, indometacin &#x0003e; 75, ketoprofen &#x0003e; 100, mefenamic 
acid &#x0003e; 1000, tiaprofenic acid &#x0003e; 450, azapropazone &#x0003e; 600, meloxicam 
&#x0003e; 7.5, nabumetone &#x0003e; 1000, naproxen &#x0003e; 500, piroxicam &#x0003e; 10, 
sulindac &#x0003e; 200, tenoxicam &#x0003e; 10 (all doses in mg).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Aspirin used at doses as low as 75 mg is still associated with a moderate 
risk of developing serious upper gastrointestinal complications. The coating of 
the active principle in order to spare the stomach does not reduce the risk of 
upper gastrointestinal complications, neither for the stomach nor for the 
duodenum. The first two months of treatment seem to be the period of greater 
risk, regardless the patient is first-ever user or not. Patients using 
concomitantly low-dose aspirin and high-dose nonaspirin NSAIDs are a subgroup 
of patients with a major increased risk of upper gastrointestinal 
complications.</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>UGIB: Upper gastrointestinal bleeding; UGIC: Upper gastrointestinal 
complications; NSAIDs: Non-steroidal and anti-inflammatory drugs; RR; Relative 
risk; GPRD: General Practice Research Database.</p></sec><sec><title>Pre-publication history</title><p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/content/backmatter/1472-6904-1-1-b1.pdf"/></p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Appendix 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="1472-6904-1-1-s1.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Appendix 2</title></caption><media xlink:href="1472-6904-1-1-s2.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Appendix 3</title></caption><media xlink:href="1472-6904-1-1-s3.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Appendix 4</title></caption><media xlink:href="1472-6904-1-1-s4.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors wish to thank the general practitioners for their excellent 
collaboration. We also thank Dr. Sonia Hern&#x000e1;ndez for her helpful comments, 
Dr. Antonio Salvador for his help in revising patients' profiles and the Boston 
Collaborative Drug Surveillance Program for providing access to the data. The 
validation of cases was in part supported by a research grant from Novartis.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patrono</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aspirin as an antiplatelet drug.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1994</year><volume>330</volume><fpage>1287</fpage><lpage>1294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8145785</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>LLY</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez Gutthann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moride</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fries</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variability in risk of gastrointestinal complications with individual 
NSAIDs. results of a collaborative meta-analysis.</article-title><source>Br Med J</source><year>1996</year><volume>312</volume><fpage>1563</fpage><lpage>1566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8664664</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Colin-Jones</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Langman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawlins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vessey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wainwright</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prophylactic aspirin and risk of peptic ulcer bleeding.</article-title><source>Br Med J</source><year>1995</year><volume>310</volume><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7711618</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurgelon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheehan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koff</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk of aspirin-associated major upper-gastrointestinal bleeding with 
enteric-coated or buffered product.</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1996</year><volume>348</volume><fpage>1413</fpage><lpage>1416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8937281</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tozer</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical pharmacokinetics- concepts and applications.</article-title><source>Lea &#x00026; Febiger, Philadelphia:</source><year>1980</year></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aspirin and the stomach.</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>1986</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3511824</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoftiezer</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvoso</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Burks</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivey</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the effects of regular and enteric-coated aspirin on 
gastroduodenal mucosa of man.</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1980</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6107406</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanza</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Royer</surname><given-names>GL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endoscopic evaluation of the effects of aspirin, buffered aspirin, 
and enteric-coated aspirin on gastric and duodenal mucosa.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1980</year><volume>303</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6966762</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawthorne</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahida</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkey</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aspirin-induced gastric mucosa damage: prevention by enteric-coating 
and relation to prostaglandin synthesis.</article-title><source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>1991</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1888645</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The risk of upper gastrointestinal complications among users of 
paracetamol and other non-steroidal antiinflammatory drugs.</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><comment></comment></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez Gutthann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of the UK General Practice Research Database for 
pharmacoepidemiology.</article-title><source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>1998</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9643612</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jick</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jick</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Derby</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of information recorded on general practitioner based 
computerised data resource in the United Kingdom.</article-title><source>Br Med J</source><year>1991</year><volume>302</volume><fpage>766</fpage><lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2021768</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jick</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk of upper gastrointestinal bleeding and perforation associated 
with individual nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs.</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1994</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>769</fpage><lpage>772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7907735</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Case-control studies: sampling the source population.</article-title><source>Walker AM. Observation and Inference: An introduction to the 
methods of epidemiology. Chestnut Hill, MA: Epidemiology Resources 
Inc.,</source><year>1991</year><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>80</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez Gutthann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Raiford</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Individual non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs and hospitalizations 
for upper gastrointestinal bleeding and perforation.</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><year>1997</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9116088</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Abajo</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors and upper 
gastrointestinal bleeding: a population based case-control study.</article-title><source>Br Med J</source><year>1999</year><volume>319</volume><fpage>1106</fpage><lpage>1109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10531103</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Modern Epidemiology, 1st ed, Little, Brown and Company, Boston:</source><year>1986</year></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosmer</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemeshow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Confidence interval estimation of interaction.</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><year>1992</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1391139</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiessen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasma acetylsalicylate and salicylate and platelet cyclo-oxygenase 
activity following plain and enteric-coated aspirin.</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>1980</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7355437</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtenstein</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastrointestinal toxicity of nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>340</volume><fpage>1888</fpage><lpage>1899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10369853</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanza</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of gastric ulcer and gastroduodenal injury in normal 
volunteers receiving aspirin and other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory 
drugs.</article-title><source>Scand J Gastroenterol Suppl</source><year>1989</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2683026</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yood</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jick</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using prescription claims data for drugs available over-the-counter 
(OTC).</article-title><source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><year>2000</year><volume>9 (suppl 1)</volume><fpage>S37</fpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


