<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Neurol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Neurology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2377</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15601479</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">544890</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2377-4-24</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2377-4-24</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Controversial significance of early S100B levels after cardiac surgery</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000f6;nsson</surname><given-names>Henrik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>henrik.jonsson@thorax.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Johnsson</surname><given-names>Per</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>pelle.johnsson@skane.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000e4;ckstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>Martin.Backstrom@psychology.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alling</surname><given-names>Christer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>Christer.Alling@neurokemi.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dautovic-Bergh</surname><given-names>Cecilia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>Cecilia.dautovic_bergh@thorax.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Blomquist</surname><given-names>Sten</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>sten.blomquist@skane.se</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Heart-Lung Diseases, Lund University Hospital, Lund, Sweden</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Departments of Psychology, Lund University, Lund, Sweden</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Medical Neurochemistry, Lund University Hospital, Lund, Sweden</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2377/4/24"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>6</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 J&#x000f6;nsson et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>J&#x000f6;nsson et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               J&#x000f6;nsson
               Henrik
               
               henrik.jonsson@thorax.lu.se
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Controversial significance of early S100B levels after cardiac surgery
         </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Neurology 4(1): 24-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2377(2004)4:1&#x0003c;24&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2377</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The brain-derived protein S100B has been shown to be a useful marker of brain injury of different etiologies. Cognitive dysfunction after cardiac surgery using cardiopulmonary bypass has been reported to occur in up to 70% of patients. In this study we tried to evaluate S100B as a marker for cognitive dysfunction after coronary bypass surgery with cardiopulmonary bypass in a model where the inflow of S100B from shed mediastinal blood was corrected for.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>56 patients scheduled for coronary artery bypass grafting underwent prospective neuropsychological testing. The test scores were standardized and an impairment index was constructed. S100B was sampled at the end of surgery, hourly for the first 6 hours, and then 8, 10, 15, 24 and 48 hours after surgery. None of the patients received autotransfusion.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In simple linear analysis, no significant relation was found between S100B levels and neuropsychological outcome. In a backwards stepwise regression analysis the three variables, S100B levels at the end of cardiopulmonary bypass, S100B levels 1 hour later and the age of the patients were found to explain part of the neuropsychological deterioration (r = 0.49, p &#x0003c; 0.005).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this study we found that S100B levels 1 hour after surgery seem to be the most informative. Our attempt to control the increased levels of S100B caused by contamination from the surgical field did not yield different results. We conclude that the clinical value of S100B as a predictive measurement of postoperative cognitive dysfunction after cardiac surgery is limited.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Despite the fact that incidence figures between 4&#x02013;79% have been reported for cognitive dysfunction after cardiac surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], diagnostic steps are seldom taken to diagnose this impairment. The golden standard for detecting cognitive dysfunction is neuropsychological tests, which are complex and difficult to use as a routine procedure. Lately the brain derived protein S100B has been proposed as a simple method for detecting brain dysfunction after cardiac surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The protein is a member of the larger S100 family, where S100B is one isoform, and considered to be brain specific, and the other is the S100A isoform [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The S100B chain is uniform in contrast to the S100A chain which exhibits several subgroups. The dimers of interest in studies concerning cerebral events are those containing S100B (S100BB and S100A1B). The physiological roles of S100B are pleiotropic including neurotrophic and neuroprotective functions, mediated by calcium dependent regulation of phosporylation, enzyme activation and proliferation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. On the other hand, high concentrations of S100B have been shown to be toxic and induce apoptosis in neuronal cell cultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. At least five experimental studies have indicated a possible role of S100B in learning and memory function, three of which reported impaired memory and learning effects in transgenic S100B mice and two reported memory deficits after injection of S100B antiserum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>].</p><p>Several studies in humans suffering from stroke of different ethiologies, have shown a rather strong correlation between serum levels of S100B and size of lesion(s) as well as outcome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>Lately a number of studies have addressed the question whether S100B can be considered as a marker for cognitive dysfunction after cardiac surgery; however the conclusions presented are disparate. One major reason for this could be the fact that S100B is present in high concentrations in shed mediastinal blood that is retransfused to the patient by cardiotomy suction and autotransfusion, thus obscuring the measured levels of S100B early after surgery. To date, only one study have been published where this contamination was taken into account [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. We recently reported the half life of S100B in serum to be 25 min [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. With the present study we wanted to use our knowledge of inflow and elimination to obtain a more reliable measurement of cerebral release of S100B after cardiac surgery and correlate it with neuropsychological outcome.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Study design</title><p>The study group comprised 56 patients who underwent coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery at the Division of Cardiac Surgery, University Hospital MAS, Malmoe, Sweden and Department of Cardiothoracic Surgery, Lund University Hospital, Lund, Sweden. Only patients planned for elective CABG with cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) as their sole procedure were included. The study protocol was approved by the local ethics committee, and patients gave a written informed consent before the study protocol was initiated. Patients with a history of stroke, transient ischemic attack (TIA), reversible neurological disorder (RIND), known carotid artery disease or other brain diseases were excluded. In order to avoid possible influence of renal disorder on the elimination of S100B, patients with known renal failure (Creatinin &#x0003e; 160 &#x003bc;mol/L) were excluded.</p><p>The patients were examined for signs of neurological dysfunctions daily during the hospital stay by either experienced cardiac anesthesiologists or by experienced cardiac surgeons.</p></sec><sec><title>Perioperative management</title><p>Anesthesia was induced with midazolam 3&#x02013;5 mg iv (Dormicum<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, Roche, Basel, Switzerland) or propofol (Diprivan<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, Zeneca Ltd, Cheshire, England) 10 mg/kg. It was subsequently maintained with fentanyl 10 &#x003bc;g/kg (Leptanal<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, Janssen Pharmaceutica, Beerse, Belgien), a continuous infusion of propofol 3&#x02013;6 mg/kg/h or inhalation of isoflurane 0,5&#x02013;1% (Forene<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, Abbott Laboratories). Nitrous oxide (Aga Industries, Stockholm, Sweden) was used before CPB but not during or after CPB.</p><p>CABG surgery was performed during aortic cross clamping with the distal anastomosis preceding the proximal anastomosis. A tangential occluder replaced the cross-clamp during the proximal anastomosis. Antegrade cold S:t Thomas crystalloid cardioplegia was used (Cardioplegi<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, Pharmacia-Upjohn, Uppsala, Sweden) and administered in the ascending aorta and the anastomosed vein-grafts intermittently.</p><p>Perfusion was performed with a roller pump (Cobe Industries, Denver, Colorado, USA). The perfusion catheters and circuit were made of polyvinylchloride in the line and silicon in the pumphead. The arterial cannulation was made in the ascending aorta and venous cannulation in the right atrium by a two-stage venous cannula. All circuits contained a heparin-coated 40 &#x003bc;m arterial filter (Cobe Sence, Cobe Industries) and a membrane oxygenator (Cobe Duo oxygenator, Cobe Industries). The circuit was primed with approximately 1000 ml of Ringer's lactate (Pharmacia-Upjohn), 250 ml 15% Mannitol (Pharmacia-Upjohn) and 75 mmol Addex tromethamine (Pharmacia-Upjohn). Perfusion flow was non-pulsatile with a flow rate of 2.4 l/min/m<sup>2 </sup>at normothermia. The perfusate was cooled to approximately 32&#x000b0;C. Heparin (400 U/kg bodyweight) was given prior to cannulation and reversed with equal doses of protamine sulphate at decannulation.</p><p>After surgery, the patients patient were transferred to the ICU for recovery and enrolled in the sampling scheme for S100B analysis. None of the patients received autotransfusion.</p></sec><sec><title>S100-protein analysis and calculations</title><p>Serum for S100B analysis was sampled before surgery, at the end of CPB, and then 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 15, 24 and 48 hours after surgery. The S100B levels at these time points will be referred to as T0, T1, T2....T48. Blood samples, both arterial and venous samples, were cooled and centrifuged within 5 hours. All samples were measured by a monoclonal two-site immunoluminometric assay (Sangtec 100, AB Sangtec Medical, Bromma, Sweden).</p></sec><sec><title>S100B kinetic calculations</title><p>Since early levels of S100B are contaminated by S100B from cardiotomy suction, an attempt was made to exclude this S100B from the levels measured one and two hours after surgery. Assuming that all of the measured S100B at the termination of CPB was a contamination, this non-cerebral S100B was eliminated with a half-life of 25 minutes, as illustrated in figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1b</xref>. The estimated true levels cleansed from the contamination 1 and 2 hours after the end of surgery were thereby calculated by the formula:</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>1a &#x02013; Measured S100B release pattern in one patient and the calculated residual levels from the S100B from cardiotomy suction during surgery, a half-life of 25 minutes was used. 1b &#x02013; Estimated true release, calculated by subtracting the residual levels (from 1a) from measured levels. 1c &#x02013; Measured levels and estimated true release from one patient with high S100B at T0 and low estimated true release at T1. This patient also had a good neuropsychological outcome. 1d &#x02013; Measured levels and estimated true release from one patient with low S100B at T0 and high estimated true release at T1. This patient had a bad neuropsychological outcome.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2377-4-24-1"/></fig><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2377-4-24-i1.gif"/></p><p>where C<sub>e </sub>is the estimated true levels of S100B at time t, C<sub>t </sub>= the measured concentration of S100B at T1 or T2, C<sub>0 </sub>the concentration at the end of CPB, t the time after T0 and t<sub>1/2 </sub>the half-life of S100B.</p><p>We have earlier suggested that the elimination rate could be used as another measure of cerebral release [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], and the elimination rates of S100B between the end of CPB (T0) and 1 hour later, between T1 and T2, and between T2 and T3 were calculated accordingly. The differences between measured S100B levels at T0 and T1, T0 and T2 were also calculated.</p></sec><sec><title>Neuropsychological method</title><p>The patients underwent neuropsychological testing by the same trained neuropsychologist 1&#x02013;2 days before and 5&#x02013;7 days after surgery. The tests used were: Mental Control, Figural Memory, Logical Memory (A/B), Visual Reproduction, Rey Auditory/Verbal Learning Test (RAVLT), Trail Making A, Trail Making B, Digit Symbol, Digit Span, Visual Memory Span, Visual Paired Associates II or Verbal Paired Associates I and RAVLT, Delayed Retention. The tests were chosen from the Wechsler Memory Scale-Revised (WMS-R), the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale (WAIS &#x02013; R) and the Halsted-Reitan Neuropsychological Battery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>].</p><p>Differences for each sub-test were first calculated and then standardized to z-values. All sub-tests were then aggregated to create an impairment index [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The impairment index was a continuous variable, where a positive value reflected an improvement in neuropsychological test and a negative value reflected deterioration. The incidence of neuropsychological impairment in the study group was calculated according to the 1 standard deviation criterion (SD) as defined by Newman and the 20% criterion as defined by Stump [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All results were analyzed with the Statistica version 5.0 for PC. Regression analysis was performed with the least square method with a casewise deletion of missing data. For the multiple regression a backwards stepwise regression was performed to determine which variables to include in the final analysis. The initial variables included in this analysis were age, gender, perfusion time, years of education, and S100B levels at all sampling times. A p-value &#x0003c; 0,05 was considered significant. Unless otherwise stated numerical values are presented as mean &#x000b1; 1 standard deviation.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Patient demographics are presented in table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. None of the patients suffered a clinically detectable stroke. The incidence of neuropsychological impairment was 37,5% (n = 21, 95% C.I 26,0&#x02013;50,6%) according to the 1 standard deviation criterion, and 80,4% (n = 45, 95% C.I. 68,1&#x02013;88,6%) according to the 20% criterion.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographics for the study group.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left">Mean</td><td align="left">St. dev.</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Number</td><td align="left">56</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sex (M/F)</td><td align="left">47/9</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left">60.4</td><td align="left">9.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Education (years)</td><td align="left">9.6</td><td align="left">3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Perfusion time (Minutes)</td><td align="left">82.8</td><td align="left">31.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">X-clamp (minutes)</td><td align="left">53.9</td><td align="left">23.5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The appearance of S100B protein followed the same pattern in all patients with high levels at the end of CPB and a decrease or slight increase the first hour (figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Thereafter a subsequent decrease was observed during the rest of the study period, except in one patient in whom the concentration of S100B increased to 2,0 &#x003bc;g/L 48 hours after surgery. Mean estimated true release of S100B, calculated according to equation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], was lower at T1 and T2 compared to measured S100B levels (1.43 &#x000b1; 1.37 &#x003bc;g/L vs. 2.11 &#x000b1; 1.81 &#x003bc;g/L and 1.22 &#x000b1; 1.10 &#x003bc;g/L vs. 1.32 &#x000b1; 1.17 &#x003bc;g/L). Three representative examples of this calculation are shown in figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1d</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>S100B release pattern after cardiac surgery with cardiopulmonary bypass shown as a boxplot.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2377-4-24-2"/></fig><p>We found a correlation between patient age and S100B levels measured up to 24 hours after bypass (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). No significant correlation was found between measured S100B levels at the sampling times and neuropsychological impairment in simple regression analysis (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Neither did age, years of education and duration of perfusion correlate with neuropsychological impairment when tested in simple regression analysis (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The relation between S100B levels and patient age tested in univariate linear regression analysis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left">r-value</td><td align="left">p-level</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">S100B at T0</td><td align="left">0.19</td><td align="left">n. s</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T1</td><td align="left">0.30</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T2</td><td align="left">0.30</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T3</td><td align="left">0.34</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T4</td><td align="left">0.37</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T5</td><td align="left">0.32</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T6</td><td align="left">0.37</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T8</td><td align="left">0.38</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T10</td><td align="left">0.42</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T15</td><td align="left">0.36</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T24</td><td align="left">0.46</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T48</td><td align="left">0.004</td><td align="left">n.s</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The relation between S100B levels, demographic variables and neuropsychological impairment index, expressed as r-value from linear regression analysis (* = p &#x0003c; 0.05). Mean (&#x000b1; SD) S100B levels are also presented. (Est. true release = estimated true release when residual levels from contamination have been excluded)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left">Mean &#x000b1; St.dev.</td><td align="left">r-value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">S100B at T0</td><td align="right">3.63 &#x000b1; 2.84</td><td align="right">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T1</td><td align="right">2.11 &#x000b1; 1.81</td><td align="right">-0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T2</td><td align="right">1.32 &#x000b1; 1.17</td><td align="right">-0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T3</td><td align="right">0.87 &#x000b1; 0.73</td><td align="right">-0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T4</td><td align="right">0.60 &#x000b1; 0.42</td><td align="right">-0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T5</td><td align="right">0.49 &#x000b1; 0.38</td><td align="right">-0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T6</td><td align="right">0.42 &#x000b1; 0.33</td><td align="right">-0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T8</td><td align="right">0.38 &#x000b1; 0.25</td><td align="right">-0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T10</td><td align="right">0.31 &#x000b1; 0.21</td><td align="right">-0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T15</td><td align="right">0.25 &#x000b1; 0.16</td><td align="right">-0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T24</td><td align="right">0.21 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td align="right">-0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100B at T48</td><td align="right">0.21 &#x000b1; 0.27</td><td align="right">-0.09</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Est. true release at T1</td><td align="right">1.43 &#x000b1; 1.37</td><td align="right">-0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Est. true residual at T2</td><td align="right">1.22 &#x000b1; 1.10</td><td align="right">-0.12</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Elimination rate T0-T1</td><td align="right">0.50 &#x000b1; 0.46</td><td align="right">0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Elimination rate T1-T2</td><td align="right">0.48 &#x000b1; 0.25</td><td align="right">-0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Elimination rate T2-T3</td><td align="right">0.68 &#x000b1; 0.32</td><td align="right">-0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Difference T0-T1</td><td align="right">1.53 &#x000b1; 1.66</td><td align="right">0,30*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Difference T0-T2</td><td align="right">2.31 &#x000b1; 2.01</td><td align="right">0,18</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age</td><td></td><td align="right">0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Education</td><td></td><td align="right">-0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Perfusion time</td><td></td><td align="right">0.12</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>In multiple regression analysis, measured S100B levels at the end of CPB (T0), one hour later (T1) and age were found to explain part of the neuropsychological impairment (r = 0.49, p &#x0003c; 0.005, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). It is worth noting that the correlation was positive at T0 and negative at T1, implicating a better outcome if S100B was high at T0 and worse if the levels were high at T1. Age had a negative correlation. Furthermore the combination of age, S100B at T0 and S100B at either T3 or T6 gave significant correlations in the same manner (r = 0.41, p &#x0003c; 0.05 and r = 0.42, p &#x0003c; 0.05 respectively). The difference between S100B levels at T0 and T1 was found to correlate positively with neuropsychological outcome (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). No correlation was found when the estimated true release of S100B was tested against neuropsychological outcome, neither did the elimination rate fall out significantly in simple regression analysis (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The results of the backwards stepwise multiple regression analysis model to explain the neuropsychological impairment index (r = 0.49, p &#x0003c; 0.005).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Variable</td><td align="left">Partial correlation</td><td align="left">Beta</td><td align="left">p-value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">S100 at T0</td><td align="left">0.45</td><td align="left">0.845</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S100 at T1</td><td align="left">-0.47</td><td align="left">-0.939</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age</td><td align="left">0.31</td><td align="left">0.307</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Regression</td><td></td><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.005</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>This study presents some interesting findings that may be relevant in clinical practice. There is a clear relation between patient age and release of S100B up to 24 hours after cardiac surgery. This correlation is strong and not influenced by the perioperative contamination of S100B caused by the use of coronary suction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p><p>The univariate analysis did not provide a clear answer to the question whether there is a relationship between neuropsychological outcome and S100B release. However, from table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref> it is worth noting that the r-values in univariate regression analysis are negative at all sampling points except at T0 (immediately after bypass). The consistent finding of a negative correlation 1 hour and onwards after bypass is intriguing and warrants further exploration.</p><p>The multiple regression analysis resulted in a significant correlation between neuropsychological deterioration and the three variables: S100B at T0, S100B at T1 and patient age. The r-value in the multiple regression analysis was 0.49, which evokes the question why the multiple regression is stronger than the univariate regression. One possible explanation could be that by including the S100B level at the end of CPB we compensate for some part of the contamination in the S100B levels one hour after surgery.</p><p>Age correlated also with outcome. As expected, the older the patient the higher the risk for neuropsychological deterioration, which is in accordance to the fact that age is a risk factor for decline in neuropsychological tests after surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>].</p><p>Our results are to some extent in concordance with other reports in this field. Two groups have reported no relation between S100B and neuropsychological test results, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] and two groups have found a relation using a composite S100B end-point [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Only one of these studies was designed to exclude the extracerebral inflow of S100B [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. These contradicting findings support our notion that S100B kinetics after cardiac surgery are complicated.</p><p>Interestingly, in the multiple regression analysis there was a positive correlation between S100B levels at T0 and outcome, a finding that stands in contrast to the hypothesis that S100B could be used as serum marker for cognitive dysfunction. This finding is especially interesting since most of the measure S100B at T0 is contamination. In an earlier study we found that approximately 80% of measured S100B at this point is from extracerebral sources in CABG patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. We offer no explanation for this unexpected finding, but it is intriguing and calls for further investigations.</p><p>When interpreting the results of our study, as well as comparing them with those of other reports, several issues need to be addressed. To begin with the origin of S100B measured after CPB is not exclusively cerebral. From our previous study as well as from reports by Anderson et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>], it is clear that shed blood in the mediastinum contains very high levels of S100B. When this blood is retransfused either directly by cardiotomy suction or later in the course by autotransfusion during the postoperative care, the systemic levels of S100B are affected. The source of this S100B is non-cerebral, probably from S100B containing tissue such as fat, skin and bone marrow. No autotransfusion was used in this study, however reabsorbtion of S100B from injured fat tissue may contribute to the measured serum levels of S100B.</p><p>Since we previously have been able to determine the half life of S100B in blood to be 25 min, it was possible to control for the peri-operative contribution from cardiotomy suctions by using the equation mentioned to obtain the estimated true release at T1 and T2. When these values were entered in simple regression analysis, no correlation was found to neuropsychological outcome. However, if multiple regression analysis was used, a positive correlation was found, these results were identical to those obtained with the measured S100B values, and therefore we can conclude that the use of the correction procedure represented by the equation does not contribute to the evaluation of the results. Moreover, we should be careful to overinterpret the significance of correlations in a study of relatively few patients and several end-points, i.e sampling times for S100B. There is always a risk of accepting a false hypothesis. Preferably, a study of this sort should contain a large number of patients and only one or few end-points. However, the aim of this study was to clarify the complex kinetics of early S100B release and its possible connection to a neuropsychological decline, not to determine the perfect use of S100b for detecting neuropsychological outcome after cardiac surgery.</p><p>In the mathematical correction model suggested here, we assume that all S100B measured at T0 is of extrecerebral origin. This is of course not the case, but we do not know the relation between cerebral and extracerebral S100B at this time-point in each individual. By assuming that none of the S100B measured at T0 is of cerebral origin, we can be sure that our mathematical model does not include non-cerebral S100B at T1 and later. However, these levels might be lower than the true levels of cerebral S100B since we could have excluded cerebral S100B present at T0. This could also be an explanation that the multiple regression analysis showed stronger correlations.</p><p>One important issue, which must be considered in this type of study, is the strength that can be expected in the correlation between two different measures of brain function. The functional domains in the brain covered by neuropsychological tests vary depending on the tests used and are by no means complete in any test battery. By the same reasoning, the magnitude of a possible cerebral release of S100B after an injury may vary according to the severity of the insult as well as the location of the insult, since glia dense areas express more S100B than others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>In conclusion, with the present knowledge, a single S100B sampled in the postoperative course after cardiac surgery can not be of use in clinical practice in order to predict neuropsychological outcome with an acceptable sensitivity.</p><p>However, utilizing a statistic model, an association between S100B levels the first hours after surgery and neuropsychological outcome was found, where the most informative time point seems to be 1 hour after the termination of CPB.</p><p>The controversial significance of an increased S100B immediately after surgery is indeed intriguing and it inspires further studies of the mechanisms of S100B release after cardiac surgery as well as other fields of brain damage.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>HJ: Principal investigator recruited, enrolled patients analyzed and wrote the paper</p><p>PJ: Had an integral role in the planning and the analysis, also help with writing</p><p>MB: Designed neuropsychological test battery. Analyzed neuropsychological data</p><p>CB: Performed all neuropsychological testing with patients</p><p>CA: Did the S100B-analyzes</p><p>SB: Mentor an principal leader of the project, who also helped with the writing.</p></sec><sec><title>Pre-publication history</title><p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2377/4/24/prepub"/></p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgement</title><p>We would like to acknowledge Sangtec-Diasorin AB, Bromma, Sweden for supporting us with kits for S100B analysis.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahanna</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Croughwell</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Clancy</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining neuropsychological dysfunction after coronary artery bypass grafting</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>1996</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1342</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8633938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-4975(95)01095-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wimmer-Greinecker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Matheis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brieden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oremek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Westphal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Neuropsychological changes after cardiopulmonary bypass for coronary artery bypass grafting</article-title><source>Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>1998</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9776494</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kilminster</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Treasure</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuropsychological change and S-100 protein release in 130 unselected patients undergoing cardiac surgery</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>1999</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1869</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10471438</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000f6;nsson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Alling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;ckstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Blomquist</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S100&#x003b2; after Coronary Artery Surgery: Release Pattern, Source of Contamination and Relation to Neuropsychological Outcome</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>1999</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>2202</fpage><lpage>08</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10617003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-4975(99)00851-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Galazky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunderlich</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Huth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurobehavioral outcome prediction after cardiac surgery : role of neurobiochemical markers of damage to neuronal and glial brain tissue</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>2000</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10700498</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donato</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional roles of S100 proteins, calcium-binding proteins of the EF-hand type</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>1999</year><volume>1450</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10395934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-4889(99)00058-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barger</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolchok</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Eldik</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disulfide-linked S100 beta dimers and signal transduction</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>1992</year><volume>1160</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1420327</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selinfreund</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Barger</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pledger</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Eldik</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurotrophic protein S100 beta stimulates glial cell proliferation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1991</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>3554</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1902567</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Memory and the effect of cold shock in the water maze in S100 beta transgenic mice</article-title><source>Physiol Behav</source><year>1996</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8840925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9384(96)80038-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conspecific exploration in the T-maze: abnormalities in S100 beta transgenic mice</article-title><source>Physiol Behav</source><year>1996</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>6(b)</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8804639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0031-9384(95)02247-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial and nonspatial learning in mice: effects of S100 beta overexpression and age</article-title><source>Neurobiol Learn Mem</source><year>1996</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8946407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nlme.1996.0055</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gromov</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Syrovatskaya</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ovinova</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional role of the neurospecific S-100 protein in the processes of memory</article-title><source>Neurosci Behav Physiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1614614</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Dowd</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>WQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chicks injected with antisera to either S-100 alpha or S-100 beta protein develop amnesia for a passive avoidance task</article-title><source>Neurobiol Learn Mem</source><year>1997</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9159758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nlme.1997.3766</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000fc;ttner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Weyers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Postert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprengelmeyer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S-100 Protein: Serum marker of Focal Brain damage after Ischemic Territorial MCA Infarction</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>1997</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1961</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9341704</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abraha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Butterworth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bath</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wassif</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gartwhaite</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherwood</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serum S-100 Protein, relationship to clinical outcome in acute stroke</article-title><source>Ann Clin Biochem</source><year>1999</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9247667</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Backstrom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Luhrs</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Alling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased S100B in blood after cardiac surgery is a powerful predictor of late mortality</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2003</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12537211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-4975(02)04318-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Missler</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiesmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaps</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S-100 protein and neuron-specific enolase concentrations in blood as indicators of infarction volume and prognosis in acute ischemic stroke</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>1997</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1956</fpage><lpage>1960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9341703</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westaby</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saatvedt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsumata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>van Oeveren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatnagar</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Halligan</surname><given-names>PWl</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is there a relationship between serum s-100beta protein and neuropsychologic dysfunction after cardiopulmonary bypass?</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2000</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10612772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mtc.2000.105826</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000f6;nsson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;glund</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Alling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Blomquist</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Elimination of S100B and Renal Function after Cardiac Surgery</article-title><source>J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth</source><year>2000</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>698</fpage><lpage>701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11139112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/jcan.2000.18444</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wechsler Memory Scale-Revised</article-title><source>The Psychological corporation, Harcourt, Brace Jovanovich Inc</source><year>1987</year><publisher-name>San Antonio, Texas</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Halsted Reitan Battery (HRB)</article-title><source>Reitan and Wolfson</source><year>1993</year></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahanna</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Croughwell</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methodological issues in the assessment of neuropsychologic function after cardiac surgery</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>1995</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1345</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7733766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-4975(95)00055-P</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Croughwell</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowry</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Spillane</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Glower</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahanna</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predictors of cognitive decline after cardiac operation</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>1995</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1326</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7733762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-4975(95)00076-W</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stump</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection and clinical significance of neuropsychologic tests</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>1995</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1340</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7733765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-4975(95)00108-W</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><name><surname>Liska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Settergren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaage</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of cardiotomy suction on the brain injury marker S100beta after cardiopulmonary bypass</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2000</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10750771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-4975(99)01526-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gombos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipowicz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincendon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast and slow components of S-100 protein fraction: regional distribution in bovine central nervous system</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1971</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4926239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(71)90244-7</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


